<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The description and use of an instrument called the dovble scale of proportion by which instrument, all questions in arithmetick, geometry, trigonometry, astronomy, geography, navigation, fortification, gunnery, gaging vessels, dialling may be most accurately and speedily performed without the assistance of either pen or compasses / by Seth Partridge.</title>
            <author>Partridge, Seth, 1603-1686.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 222 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 101 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56521</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P630A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R40063</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18676365</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18676365</idno>
            <idno type="VID">108157</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56521)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 108157)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1658:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The description and use of an instrument called the dovble scale of proportion by which instrument, all questions in arithmetick, geometry, trigonometry, astronomy, geography, navigation, fortification, gunnery, gaging vessels, dialling may be most accurately and speedily performed without the assistance of either pen or compasses / by Seth Partridge.</title>
                  <author>Partridge, Seth, 1603-1686.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 188 [i.e. 186] p., [2] leaves of plates : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Leybourn for William Wright ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 188.</note>
                  <note>Errors in paging: p. 7-8 omitted in numbering only; p. 55 misprinted 57.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Slide-rule --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:108157:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108157:1"/>
            <p>THE DESCRIPTION and USE OF AN INSTRUMENT, Called the DOVBLE SCALE OF <hi>PROPORTION.</hi> By which Inſtrument, all Queſtions in
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Arithmetick,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Geometry,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Trigonometry,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aſtronomy,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Geography,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Navigation,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fortification,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gunnery,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gaging Veſſels,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dialling,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> May be moſt accurately and ſpeedily perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, without the aſſiſtance of either Pen or Compaſſes.</p>
            <p>By SETH PARTRIDGE.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>William Leybourn</hi> for <hi>William Wright</hi> under <hi>Grace-Church</hi> in <hi>Grace-Church-Street,</hi> and at the Hand and Bible in <hi>Duck-Lane.</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:108157:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108157:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipful, Sir RICHARD COMBE Knight, The Authour preſents theſe, with his other beſt Services.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He tranſcendencie of your knowledge in all noble and learned Sciences, hath heightened my ambition preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to affix on you this Dedication, and to this boldneſse its your love and favour that invites me, and prevents me too, of all Apologies for my thus doing. For truly I ſhould not ſo boldly have adventured to ſhroud this unworthy Piece under the wings of your worthy Patronage, were I not aſſured, that as in ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gement you are able to diſcern of it; ſo in your noble diſpoſition willing favourably to accept it. The poor Widows two mites being the utmost of her ability, was accepted of by him, who was greater than the greateſt of Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, far above the great gifts of the Rich: which <pb facs="tcp:108157:3"/> imboldens me (without doubt of obtaining) humbly, to deſire your Worſhip, to vouchſafe me both pardon for my preſumption, and acceptance of my little mite, which having obtained, I ſhall think my ſelf and work, to have a ſufficient protection against all Cy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nical and ill-affected Detractors, a thing which all mens works (how excellent ſoever) are ſubject unto, (much more mine) and therefore into the wide Ocean I dare not commit my weak veſſel, without ſome able Pilot, ſuch as your Noble Self, whoſe ſound judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and great learning is ſo well known, that your name prefixt before my Book, will be not onely a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence againſt the carping of <hi>Zoyliſts,</hi> but alſo to beget a good affection in the Readers. Not ta trouble your Worſhip more with words, my hope is, that this my boldneſse will be imputed to a will, rather to do you ſervice than otherwiſe, might your Worſhip be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thereof ſo to make conſtruction, I have attained my deſired end, who am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips ever to ſerve you, <hi>Seth Partridge.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:108157:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>FRiendly Readers, you have here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to your view thoſe moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Soales,</hi> or <hi>Lines</hi> of <hi>Numbers, Sines,</hi> and <hi>Tangents</hi> doubled, by means of the moving whereof, the uſe of Compaſſes is wholly avoided, and the queſtion reſolved, by applying the Scales one to another. Some men (I know) have laid aſide the uſing of the ſingle Scales, becauſe with an ordinary pair of Compaſſes on a large Scale, they could not work many examples they deſired. But by theſe double Scales, how large ſoever, he ſhall never be troubled with any Compaſſes, nor the work never to out-run the Scale. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, upon the Inſtrument may be inſerted any other Scales or Lines, as are for meaſura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or otherwiſe, ſuch as each mans calling and occaſions do moſt require, and ſo make the Inſtrument of general uſe. To plead for my Book, I will not, the Subject whereon it treats, will do that better than I can, I am ſure here is a good Subject, a good piece of cloath, if rhe garment be not marred in the making, if it be, the fault is in the botching Taylor, not <pb facs="tcp:108157:4"/> in the ſtuffe. The Ingenious (I know) will wink at faults, for they know themſelves ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to them, and faults declare men to be but men. As for curioſity in the method, here is none, nor was any intended, my diſhes being dreſt, not as at a Feaſt, but as at an Ordinary, nor placed in ſo methodical an order as they might have been, I taking <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hings not orderly, but at an adventure, and as it happened to come into mind: I know my Subject, nor method, will pleaſe all, yet I doubt not, but it will pleaſe ſome. What the ignorant ſay of it, I care not, they are like the Fox, that deſpiſed the grapes, becauſe they grew ſo high he could not reach them. And what the ſpiteful ſpeak of it, I paſſe not, they are like the filthy Fly, that ſeeks all over the body for a ſore, and when it cannot find one, it makes one. It is the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the impartial, judicious and ſolid Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which I reſpect, to whom I will ſtand, and to which onely I will ſubmit, reſting Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to all ſuch, while I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Seth Partridge.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:108157:4"/>
            <head>THE Double Scale of Proportion.</head>
            <head type="sub">The Deſcription and Uſe of an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment conſiſting of <hi>Doubled Scales.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Whereby all Concluſions Mathematical may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed onely by Application of <hi>Scales.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. The Inſtrument deſcribed.</head>
               <p>THe Inſtrument whereof I treat in this Book, I call the
<hi>Double Scale,</hi> for that the Scales, or Lines thereupon, are doubled; ſo and in ſuch manner, that by applying the one to the other, they will of themſelves reſolve any queſtion Mathematical, that may be done by the Pen, or by Tables of Sines, Tangents, and Logarithms. The Scales principally inſcribed thereupon, are thoſe moſt <pb n="2" facs="tcp:108157:5"/> admirable Lines of Numbers, of Sines, and of Tangents, whoſe uſe hath been heretofore ſet forth, onely to be wrought upon with a pair of Compaſſes, and no otherwiſe. But I have ſo contrived them double, upon an Inſtrument to move, or ſlide along one by the other, in ſuch manner, that upon the ſame, without any aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Compaſſes, I can work all Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions Mathematical, that can be wrought by the ſingle Lines, with the help of Compaſſes, both in <hi>Arithmetick, Geometry, Trigonometry, Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy, Geography, Navigation, Gaging of Veſſels, Fortification, Gunnery, Dialling.</hi> Yea, and the Uſurer too, may hereby alſo compute the true intereſt of his money. In all which, I ſhall give you ſome examples for your inſtruction, in the uſe of my Double Scale.</p>
               <p>The body, or matter whereof the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is made, may be either of Braſſe, or of very good and well ſeaſoned Box. It conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of three pieces, or Rulers, each one about half an inch in breadth, and about a quarter of an inch in thickneſſe, more or leſſe, as the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker and Vſer of them pleaſeth; and for their length, they may be made to what length you will, either one foot, two foot, three foot, or more or leſſe, for they are not limited to any length, onely the longer they are, the larger and more will be the diviſions of the Scales, <pb n="3" facs="tcp:108157:5"/> and ſo conſequently the more exact in opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Theſe three Rulers, or pieces of this <hi>Scale,</hi> are to be all of one even length and thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the edges ſo evenly joynted, that they may juſtly ſlide along cloſe one by the other, having at each end a little plate of Braſſe, or wood fitted to hold them cloſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, &amp; ſo faſtened to the two out-ſide pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that they may be kept ſteady, and the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle Ruler to ſlide to and fro between them.</p>
               <p>The Lines, or Scales ingraven on this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, are the ordinary lines of Numbers, of Sines, and of Tangents, onely they are ſet on double, that is, once upon one Ruler, and once upon the other, upon one and the ſame joynt; as the line of Numbers is ſet both upon one of the out-ſide pieces, and on the middle piece, that is, on both ſides the joynt, and num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bered on both, and ſo ſet to the very edges of both Ruſers, that both lines being joyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, may appear to be but as one line of Numbers, and this line of Numbers is (as it were) twice repeated, or doubled in the length of the Ruler, that is, beginning with 1 at one end of the Ruler, which I call the lower end, and continued to 1 or 10 at the middle, and from thence begin again, and continued to 10 or 100 at the upper end. Alſo upon the other ſide of the Rulers, upon the ſame joynt, is in <pb n="4" facs="tcp:108157:6"/> like manner ſet a like line of Numbers, and this line of Numbers is fitteſt to be uſed with the line of Tangents, as that on the other ſide is with the lines of Sines, without any turning of the Inſtrument. But you may omit on the line of Numbers upon one ſide, onely obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to turn the Inſtrument, when the work requireth to be done on ſeveral lines, as in the ſequel it will appear.</p>
               <p>The Scales, or Lines of Sines, are in like manner ſet on twice, that is, once upon the other edge of the middle piece, and alſo on the in-ſide of the other out-ſide piece, and they are to be ſet on, upon both ſides the joynt, that they may appear as one line of Sines, being laid cloſe together, and nnumbers ſet to the Diviſions on both parts, and is in the lines of Numbers.</p>
               <p>The lines of Tangents is ſet upon the other ſide of the Rulers, oppoſite to the lines of Sines upon the ſame joynt with them, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſo ſet upon both parts of the Inſtrument, that the parts being laid cloſe together, the lines may appear to be both as one line of Tangents, and numbered on both parts to 45 at the upper end, againſt 90 on the lines of Sines, and from 45 back again to 89 at the lower end, as is uſually done in the lines of Tangents.</p>
               <p>This Inſtrument having thoſe <hi>Scales,</hi> or (as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:108157:6"/> it pleaſed their firſt Inventor to call them)
<hi>Lines,</hi> thus ingraven or ſet on it, will work all concluſions, as may be wrought by Mr. <hi>Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> Lines, or Mr. <hi>Wingates,</hi> by onely applying the Lines one to another, without the uſe of Compaſſes, which muſt be alwayes had and uſed with theirs; yet you may uſe Compaſſes with theſe Scales, if you pleaſe, and ſo try and examine your work by both wayes, and when you have made ſuch trial, uſe which way you like beſt, and that (for ought I know) may be my Double Scales.</p>
               <p>To ſhew the making of the <hi>Scales</hi> of <hi>Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, Sines</hi> and <hi>Tangents,</hi> is a thing altogether needleſſe, the making of them being already ſo ſufficiently ſet forth by others, that for me to do it again, were but labour loſt, both to me in writing, and to the Reader in reading. And thoſe that are makers of Mathematical Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, do already well underſtand the making of them, and for a man to make one for his own uſe, is but vain, for that he may buy one at a cheaper rate than make it, I ſhall therefore proceed to the uſe: Wherein note, that for diſtinction of the ſides of the Scales, or Lines on the Rulers, I uſe the Termes of <hi>First</hi> and <hi>Second,</hi> as being as proper for the purpoſe as any other could have been: For evermore, that ſide of any Line, whereon the firſt term <pb n="6" facs="tcp:108157:7"/> in the rule of Proportion is taken, I call the firſt ſide; and the other ſide of the Line, whereon the ſecond term in the Rule is taken, I call the ſecond ſide. And then for the third term in the Rule, it is alwayes taken on the ſame ſide that the firſt term is taken on: and for the fourth term, which is the term ſought, it is evermore found on that ſame ſecond ſide, whereon the ſecond term is taken. As if the firſt term be taken on any Scale, upon the out-ſide Ruler, then the ſecond term is on the middle Ruler, and if the firſt term be taken on the middle Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, then the ſecond term is on the ſame Scale upon an out-ſide Ruler: And when the work is by ſeveral Lines, then the two out-ſide Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers both bear the name of
<hi>First,</hi> or <hi>Second.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Other Scales may be added to this Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſet on the ſides and edges thereof, as a Scale of equal parts, or a Line of inches, a Meridian-line, a Gage-line, a line of Chords, the lines of Board and Timber-meaſure, or any others, ſuch as your calling and occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have moſt uſe for.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:108157:7"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe and application of the double Scale of Numbers upon the Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the principal Rules of Arithmetick.</head>
               <div n="1" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM I. Of Multiplication.</head>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Two numbers being given to be multiplyed together, to find their Product, by the double lines.</head>
                     <p>IN Multiplication the Analogie is this;
<list type="analogy">
                           <item>As 1 is to one of the numbers given, to be multiplyed together:</item>
                           <item>So is the other of them, to the Product.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Wherefore it may be ſaid,
<list type="analogy">
                           <item>As 1 is to the Multiplicator;</item>
                           <item>So is the Multiplicand to the Product.</item>
                        </list> Or,
<list type="analogy">
                           <item>As 1 is to the Multiplicand;</item>
                           <item>So is the Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicator, to the Product.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>When two numbers are to be multiplied together, the greater of them is uſually count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Multiplicand, and the leſſer for Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicator.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="10" facs="tcp:108157:8"/>To multiply two numbers by the double lines, the manner of working is thus: Place 1 on the firſt ſide, to the Multiplicator on the ſecond ſide; And then againſt the Multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cand on the firſt ſide, is the Product on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſide.</p>
                     <p>Or elſe, place 1 on the firſt, to the Multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cand on the ſecond, and then right againſt the Multiplicator found on the firſt, is the Product on the ſecond.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Example</hi> 1. Let 8 and 4 be two numbers given to be multiplied together, to find their Product, do thus: upon any one of the ſides, look out 1. (This ſide whereon I take the 1, I call the fitſt ſide) I ſet this 1 to 4 on the other ſide (which I call the ſecond ſide,) and then right againſt 8 on the ſame firſt ſide, whereon I did take 1; is 32 on the ſecond ſide, whereon the 4 was taken: This 32 is the Product of 8 multiplied by 4, the thing required. Or otherwiſe thus.</p>
                     <p>Set 1 on the firſt, to 8 on the ſecond, and then right againſt 4 on that firſt, is 23 on the ſecond, as before.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Example</hi> 2. Let 25 be a Multiplicator, and 30 the Multiplicand, and the Product of them multiplied together, required.</p>
                     <p>Set 1 on the firſt, to 25 on the ſecond, and then right againſt 30 on the firſt, is 750 on the <pb n="11" facs="tcp:108157:8"/> ſecond. This
750 is the Product of 30 multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied by 25, the thing required. In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, If you ſet 1 to 30, then againſt 25 taken on the ſame ſide the
1 was, is 730 on the other ſide whereon the 30 is.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Example</hi> 3. Let 45 and 25 be two numbers given to be multiplied together, and their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct required. To reſolve this by the double lines, ſet 1 on the firſt, to 25 on the ſecond; and againſt the other number given 45 on the firſt, is 1125 on the ſecond. This 1125 is the Product of 45, multiplied by 25, which was deſired. Or,</p>
                     <p>Set 1 on the firſt, to 45 on the ſecond, and then right againſt 25 on the firſt, is 1125 on the ſecond, as before.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Example</hi> 4. Let 8 75/100 be given to be multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied by 6 45/100. To perform this work, ſet 1 on the firſt, to 6 45/100 on the ſecond, and then againſt 8 75/100 found on the ſame ſide that the 1 is on, is 56 43/100 and ſomething more: therefore 56 43/100 is the Product of 8
75/100, multiplied by 6 45/100, the thing ſought.</p>
                     <p>Or thus, Set 1 or 10 at the upper end of the line on the firſt, to 8 75/100 on the ſecond, and then againſt 6 45/100 on the firſt, is 56 43/100 on the ſecond, as before. The like practice is to be obſerved in multiplying any other numbers.</p>
                     <p>Note, that in working by the double lines,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:108157:9"/> it will be all one, whether you work from 1 at the beginning of the line upwards, or from 10, at the upper end of the lines downwards. As if you ſet 10 at the upper end on the firſt, to 4 on the ſecond, and then againſt 8 on that firſt, you ſhall have 32 on the ſecond.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>How to ſquare any number, or to multiply a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber by it ſelf, as alſo to cube any number.</head>
                     <p>Set 1 on the firſt, to the number to be ſquared on the ſecond, and then againſt that given number on the firſt, is its ſquare on the ſecond. As if 12 be a number to be ſquared, then ſet 1 on the firſt, to 12 on the ſecond, and then againſt 12 on the ſame firſt, is
144 on the ſecond. Therefore 144 is the ſquare of 12. And then again, againſt 144 on the firſt, is 1728 on the ſecond, which is the Cube of
12.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM II. Of Diviſion.</head>
                  <head>Any number being given, to be divided by another number, to find the Quotient.</head>
                  <p>IN Diviſion, the Analogie is thus:
<list type="analogy">
                        <item>As the Diviſor, is to an Vnite:</item>
                        <item> So is the Dividend, to the Quotient.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wherefore the work by the double lines is <pb n="13" facs="tcp:108157:9"/> thus; Look out the Diviſor on the firſt, and ſet it to 1 on the ſecond, and then right againſt the Dividend on the firſt, is the Quotient on the ſecond.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example</hi> 1. Let 273 be a number given to be divided by
13. Look 13 the Diviſor on any one ſide, which we call the firſt ſide, and ſet it to 1 on the ſecond ſide. And then right againſt the Dividend
273 upon that firſt, is 21 on the ſecondd. Wherefore 21 is the Quoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of
273 divided by 13, which was required.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example</hi> 2. Again, if 1728 be given to be divided by
12, then ſet 12 the Diviſor on the firſt, to 1 on the ſecond; and when that is done, you ſhall right againſt 1728, the Dividend on that firſt, ſee 144 on the ſecond, which 144 is the Quotient of 1728, divided by 12, and ſo of any other.</p>
                  <p>In Diviſion note this, that ſo many times as the Diviſor may be placed under the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dend, ſo many places of figures ſhall be in the Quotient. As if 34785, be to be divided by 75, the Quotient ſhall conſiſt of three figures onely, and no more; becauſe 75 can be pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced onely three times under 34785: And un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der 1728 the Dividend given, the Diviſor 12 can three times be placed, and therefore three figures in the Quotient. And if you will di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide 144 by 12, then ſet 12 on the firſt, to 1
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:108157:10"/> on the ſecond; which done, againſt 144 on the firſt, you have 12 on the ſecond.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example</hi> 3. Let 46 75/100 be given, to be divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by
8 5/10, and the quotient required. In this caſe, as in all other: Set the Diviſor 8 5/10 on the firſt, to 1 on the ſecond, and then againſt the Dividend 46 75/100 on that firſt, is 5 5/10 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond: therefore 5
5/10 is the quotient required, very ſpeedily and exactly found.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM III. Of Reduction of Fractions.</head>
                  <head>To reduce any vulgar Fraction into a decimal Fraction.</head>
                  <p>LEt 63/84 be a vulgar Fraction propounded, to be reduced into a decimal Fraction. Now it is to be noted, that vulgar Fractions are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced into decimals by the rule of proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in this manner:
<list type="analogy">
                        <item> As the Denominator of the Fraction given,</item>
                        <item>Is to the Numerator thereof:</item>
                        <item> So is an Vnite with cyphers, one, two, or three</item>
                        <item> To a new Numerator, which Numerator wil have ſo many places of figures in it, as the new Denominator hath cyphers, and therefore the Fraction given is thus redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced into a Decimal.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:108157:10"/>As the Denominator 84, Is to the Nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator 63.</p>
                  <p>So an Unite with two cyphers, thus 100, to 75, which 75 is the new Numerator to that new Denominator 100. Therefore 75/100 is a decimal Fraction, equal in value to 63/84. To work this kind of reduction by the double lines, do thus:</p>
                  <p>Set 84 (the Denominator of the vulgar fraction given) on the firſt, to 1 on the ſecond, &amp; then right againſt 63, the Numerator on the firſt, is 75 on the ſecond, which 75 is the new Numerator of a decimal Fraction, whoſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominator is an Vnite with two cyphers. Thus is 63/84 changed into 75/100, which new Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is equal in value with the former.</p>
                  <p>Again, if 8 12/40 be a number given to be redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced into a decimal; ſet 40, the Denominator of the fractional part, to 1, and then right a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt 12, on that part as you took the 40, is 2 on that ſecond ſide whereon the one was, and ſo the Fraction is become 3/10, which joyned to the
8, makes the mixt number that before was 8 22/40, to be 8 3/10, and of equal value.</p>
                  <p>Note that the point 1 repreſenteth alſo 10, 100, or 1000, and therefore the new Deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minator may be taken either 10, or 100, or 1000, as in your own judgement it ſhall ſeem moſt fitting. As here in this laſt Example, we <pb n="16" facs="tcp:108157:11"/> found 3 to ſtand right againſt 12, and therefore we put but one cypher to the unite, and made the Fraction 3/10. And in the laſt Example be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, we found 75 to be againſt the 63, which becauſe it conſiſteth of two places of figures, we put two cyphers to the unite for Denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nator of the new Fraction, and ſo made it 75/100, and ſo of all other.</p>
                  <p>Alſo be it remembered, throughout the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue of this work, that all Fraction figures are ſet right in the line, like whole numbers, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Denominator under them, being ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated or diſtinguiſhed from the whole part of that number by a Comma, as all ſuch Fractions as theſe 46 75/100, 6 45/100, 8 5/10, and 5 5/10, are thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed 46,75. 6,45. 8,5. and 5,5. which man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of writing Fractions being well obſerved, is a readier way than that other, of one num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber above, and another below, with a line be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween. Alſo note, that the Fractions ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed are all Decimal Fractions, whoſe Deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minator is a Vnite with ſo many Cyphers as there be Fraction figures, as the Denominator of the Fraction figures of the 75 belonging to the whole number 46 is 100, being a unite with two cyphers, becauſe two figures and the Denominator to 5 is 10, being a unite with one cypher, becauſe but one figure. And when a Fraction is to be expreſſed alone without a <pb n="17" facs="tcp:108157:11"/> whole number, then the Numerator is firſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and after it the Denominator right on in the line, with a Comma betwixt, as 75/100, and 5/10, are thus expreſſed
75,100. 5,10. and ſo of other the like.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM IV. Of Continual Proportionals.</head>
                  <head>Two numbers being given, to find a third, a fourth, a fifth (or many numbers) in continual pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion Geometrical to them two.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example.</hi> LEt the two numbers given be 2 and 4, and it be required to find ſeveral numbers in continual Geometrical pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to them two.</p>
                  <p>Set 2 on the firſt, to 4 on the ſecond, and then againſt
4 on that firſt, is 8 on the ſecond, which is the third number in continual pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion Geometrical to them two; and then againſt 8 on the firſt, is 16 on the ſecond, which 16 is the fourth number in continual propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to them two; and againſt 16 on the firſt, is 32 on the ſecond, the fifth continual propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional; and againſt 32 on the firſt, is 64 on the ſecond, the ſixth continual proportional; and againſt 64 on the firſt, is 128 on the ſecond, the ſeventh continual proportional; and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:108157:12"/> againſt 128 on the firſt, is 256 on the ſecond, which is the eighth proportional to the two propoſed numbers. Wherefore 8,
16, 32, 64, 128, and 256, are a rank of numbers in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Geometrical proportion, to 2 and 4, the thing that was required.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example</hi> 2. Let it be required to find a rank of numbers in continual proportion, as 2 to 3. Here ſet 2 on the firſt to 3 on the ſecond, and then without moving the Inſtrument, againſt 3 on the firſt, you have 4,5 on the ſecond, and againſt the ſame 4,5, found on the firſt, is 6,75 on the ſecond; and againſt 6,75 on the firſt, is
10,125 on the ſecond. Therefore 4,5, 6,75, and 10,125, are a rank of numbers in continual proportion to 2 and 3, as is required.</p>
                  <p>If it be required, to find ſuch a rank of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionals to the numbers 2 and 4, which may bear the ſame proportion to one another, as 2 bears to 4: Set 4 to 2, and then againſt 2 on that firſt ſide whereon the
4 is, you have 1 on the ſecond ſide, which is the third proportional to 4 and 2, bearing the ſame proportion to 2, as 2 doth to 4. And againſt 1 on the firſt, is 5,10 on the ſecond, the fourth proportional; and againſt
5,10 on the firſt, is 25,100 on the ſecond, which is the fifth number in continual proportion inverſe, or backward.</p>
                  <p>If the two numbers given be 10 and 9, and a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:108157:12"/> rank of numbers to them in an inverſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion Geometrical be required; ſet 10 on the firſt, to 9 on the ſecond, and then againſt 9 on the firſt, is 8,1 on the ſecond, which is the third proportional; and then againſt 8,1 is 7,29 the fourth proportional: wherefore
10,9 8,1 and 7,29 are numbers in a continual pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion. But if the numbers given be 1 and 9, and a third and fourth numbers in proportion to them, as 9 is to 1, be required, then muſt the numbers found be accounted 81 and 729, they being the third and fourth numbers in a Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrical proportion to 1 and 9. In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, if the two numbers given be 10 and 12, then if you ſet 10 to
12, you ſhall ſee on the firſt againſt 12, 14,4; which is the third pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portional: and againſt 14,4 on the firſt, is 17,28 on the ſecond, which is the fourth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portional. But had the two numbers given been 1 and 12, then bring 1 on the firſt, to 12 on the ſecond, and you ſhall have againſt 13 on the firſt, 144 on the ſecond, for the third pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portional, and the fourth will be 1728, and ſo of all other.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="problem">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:108157:13"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM V. Of the Rule of Proportion direct.</head>
                  <head>Three numbers being given, to find a fourth, the Analogie ſtandeth thus.</head>
                  <p>
                     <list type="analogy">
                        <item> AS the firſt number, is to the ſecond,</item>
                        <item> So is the third number, to a fourth.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore work thus: Set the firſt number in the proportion on the firſt ſide, to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond number in the proportion on the ſecond ſide: And then againſt the third number on the firſt, is the fourth number ſought for on the ſecond.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example</hi> 1. Let the Diameter of a known circle be 7, and its circumference 22, and it be required to know what the circumference of another circle is, whoſe Diameter is 14. To reſolve this <hi>quaere:</hi> Set 7 on the firſt to 22 on the ſecond, and then againſt 14, the Diameter of the other circle found on the firſt, is 44 on the ſecond: This 44 is the circumference of that other circle, whoſe Diameter is 14.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example</hi> 2. If 45 yards of Stuff coſt 30 pound, what will 84 yards of it coſt?</p>
                  <p>Set 45 (the firſt number in the Rule) on the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:108157:13"/> firſt, to 30 (the ſecond number) on the ſecond; and then againſt 84 (the third number in the Rule) on the firſt, is 56 on the ſecond, which 56 is the fourth number, and ſheweth that 84 yards will coſt 56 pounds. Or,</p>
                  <p>If 45 acres of land be worth 30 pounds a year, what will 84 acres be worth by the year? The anſwer is as before 56 pounds.</p>
                  <p>And if 26 of any thing give 64, what will 36 of the ſame give? Set 26 to 64, and then againſt 36 on the firſt, is 88,615 the anſwer to the queſtion demanded on the ſecond.</p>
                  <p>Note, that generally in the Rule of direct proportion; If the third number be greater than the firſt, then will the fourth number be greater than the ſecond. But if the third num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber be leſſe than the firſt, then the fourth number will be leſſe than the ſecond.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example.</hi> 3. If the circumference of a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle be 22, and its Diameter 7, what will the Diameter of another circle, whoſe circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is 44?</p>
                  <p>Here ſet 22 on the firſt, to 7 on the ſecond; and then againſt 44 on the firſt, is 14 on the ſecond, which 14 is the Diameter of that cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, whoſe circumference is 44, be their mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures taken in inches, feet, or any other mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure whatſoever.</p>
                  <p>To make proof of the work, whether truly <pb n="22" facs="tcp:108157:14"/> wrought, or not. Multiply the firſt term in the Rule, and the fourth term newly found, the one by the other, and likewiſe the ſecond and third terms; and if the two Products be equal, the work is truly wrought, or elſe not.</p>
                  <p>To prove the laſt queſtion by the lines; Set 1 on the firſt, to 22 on the ſecond, and then againſt 14 on the firſt, is 308 on the ſecond: Next, ſet 1 to 7, and then againſt 44 on that firſt, is 308 on the ſecond, here both Products being equal, proves the work to be truly wrought.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM VI. The Rule of Proportion Inverſe.</head>
                  <head>Three numbers being given, to find a fourth in an Inverſed Proportion.</head>
                  <p>IT is to be noted, in this Inverſe Rule of Proportion, that if the third number be grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than the firſt, then will the fourth number be leſſe than the ſecond. And contrariwiſe, if the third number be leſſe than the firſt, then the fourth number is to be greater than the ſecond.</p>
                  <p>But in the Rule of Proportion direct; If the ſecond number, or term, be more than the <pb n="23" facs="tcp:108157:14"/> firſt, then the fourth term is alſo more than the third. And if the ſecond term be leſſe than the firſt, then is the fourth term leſſe than the third.</p>
                  <p>This Inverſe Rule may be wrought two wayes on our double lines. One way is thus:</p>
                  <p>Set the firſt term, on the firſt, to the other term of the ſame denomination on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond: And then againſt the other term of contrary denomination, ſought out on that ſecond, is the fourth number ſought for, on the firſt; Or elſe, ſet the third term on the firſt, to the firſt term on the ſecond, and then againſt the ſecond term on the firſt, is the anſwer on the ſecond.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example</hi> 1. If 60 Pioneers can make a trench in 45 hours; In how long time can 40 Pio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners make it?</p>
                  <p>Set 40 on the firſt, to 60 on the ſecond (the two numbers of the ſame denomination:) and then againſt 45 on that firſt, (the number of contrary denomination) is 67,5 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, which 67,5 is the fourth term in reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procal proportion to the other three, and of the ſame denomination with 45, <hi>viz.</hi> hours, and is the anſwer to the queſtion demanded, ſhewing that 40 men can do as much in 67,5 hours, as 60 men can do in 45 hours. Or ſet 60 on the firſt, to 40 on the ſecond, and then <pb n="24" facs="tcp:108157:15"/> againſt 45 on that ſecond, is 67,5 on the firſt.</p>
                  <p>Another way is thus: Set 40 the third term, on the firſt, to
45 on the ſecond, (which is the term of contrary denomination to the other two) and then right againſt 60, on the firſt, (which is the number of the ſame deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination with the 40) is 67,5 on the ſecond, the number ſought. Thus one way of working proves the other.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example</hi> 2. If 45 men do a work in 30 dayes: In how many dayes will 270 men do it?</p>
                  <p>Set 270 on the firſt, to 45 on the ſecond, and then againſt 30 on the firſt, is 5 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond. Or,</p>
                  <p>Set 270 on the firſt, to 30 on the ſecond, and then againſt 45 on the firſt, is 5 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond: And therefore the fourth number ſought for is 5, ſhewing that 270 men will do as much work in 5 dayes, as 45 men can do in 30 dayes.</p>
                  <p>This Rule is proved by multiplying toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the firſt and ſecond terms, and alſo the third and fourth: And if the two Products be equal, the work is truly wrought, or elſe not.</p>
                  <p>By the lines it is thus proved: Set 1 on the firſt, to 30 on the ſecond, and then againſt 45 on the firſt, is 1350 on the ſecond. This done: Set 1 on the firſt to 5 on the ſecond, and then
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:108157:15"/> againſt 270 on the firſt, is 1650 on the ſecond; here both Products being equal, declareth the work to be truly wrought.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM VII. Of Duplicated Proportion.</head>
                  <head>Three numbers being given, to find the fourth in a Duplicate Proportion.</head>
                  <p>THis Rule chiefly concerns the proportion of Lines to Superficies, or of Superficies to Lines.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="section">
                     <head>1 Of the Proportion of Lines to Superficies.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Example</hi> 1. If the diameter of a circle be 14 inches, and its Content 154 inches; What will the Content be of another circle, that is 28 inches in diameter?</p>
                     <p>Set 14 on the firſt, to 28 on the ſecond, (they being the terms of one denomination, <hi>viz.</hi> Lines) and then againſt 154 on the firſt, (the content of the circle given) is 308 on the ſecond: This 308 ſeek on the firſt, and againſt it on the ſecond is 616, which 616 is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of that other circle of 28 inches diameter.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Example</hi> 2. Let the diameter of one circle be 7 foot, and the Area of it 38,5 foot, and let it be demanded, What the ſuperficial Area of another circle is, whoſe diameter is 18 foot.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="26" facs="tcp:108157:16"/>Becauſe 7 and 18 be terms of one denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, <hi>viz.</hi> Lines; Set 7, (the diameter of the the circle, whoſe Content is known) on the firſt, to 18 on the ſecond, being the diameter of the other circle, whoſe Content is ſought, and then againſt
38,5 (the Content known) on the firſt, is 99 on the ſecond, and then ſeek this 99 on the firſt, and againſt it is 254,5 tenths on the ſecond, which is the ſuperficial Area, or Content in feet of that other circle which was demanded.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Example</hi> 3. If a peece of land that is 20 pole ſquare be worth 30 pounds; What is a peece of land of the ſame goodneſſe worth, that is 35 pole ſquare?</p>
                     <p>Set 20 on the firſt, to 35 on the ſecond, and then againſt 30 on the firſt, is 52,5 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond; and laſtly, againſt
52,5 on the firſt, is 91,8 on the ſecond: that is 91 pounds, and eight tenths of a pound, or 16 ſhillings. So much is the worth of that piece of land of 35 pole ſquare.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Example</hi> 4. How many acres of land of our Engliſh meaſure of 16,5 foot to the pole, are contained in 30 Iriſh acres, of 21 foot to the pole.</p>
                     <p>Place 16,5 on the firſt to 21 on the ſecond, and then againſt 30 on the firſt, is 38,2 on the ſecond; and againſt 38,2 on the firſt, is 48,6 <pb n="27" facs="tcp:108157:16"/> on the ſecond. So many Engliſh acres are in 30 Iriſh acres.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="section">
                     <head>2 Of the Proportion of Superficies to Lines.</head>
                     <p>If the two terms of like denomination be of ſuperficial Contents, and a diameter, or a line ſought for.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Example.</hi> Let two circles be given, the Content of the one being 154, and its diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter 14: the Area of the other circle is 616, and its diameter is required.</p>
                     <p>Set the Area of the circle known, <hi>viz.</hi> 154 on the firſt, to its diameter 14 on the ſecond, and then againſt 616 on the firſt, is 56 on the ſecond. The half whereof, <hi>viz.</hi> 28, is the dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter of that other circle, whoſe Content is 616, which 28 is feet, or inches, or any other meaſure, ſuch as the diameter of the other cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle was meaſured by.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM VIII. Of Triplicate Proportion.</head>
                  <head>Three numbers being given, to find a fourth in a Triplicated Proportion.</head>
                  <p>THis Rule concerneth the proportion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Lines and Solids.
<hi>Example</hi> 1. There is a Bullet whoſe diameter is 4 inches, weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth 9 pounds: What will another Bullet <pb n="28" facs="tcp:108157:17"/> weigh, whoſe diameter is 8 inches, and of the ſame metal.</p>
                  <p>Set 4 on the firſt, to 8 on the ſecond, (rhat is the one diameter to the other:) And then againſt 9 on the firſt, (which is the weight of the Bullet of 4 inches diameter) is 18 on the ſecond, and againſt
18 on the firſt, is 36 on the ſecond; and thirdly, againſt 36 on the firſt, is 72 on the ſecond. This third ſumme found, is the fourth proportional number, which was required, ſhewing that the weight of that other Bullet of 8 inches diameter, is 72 pounds.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example</hi> 2. If a Gun of 5 inches diameter, require for her due charge 16 pound of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; How much powder will a Gun of 4 in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches diameter in the bore require, for her due charge, of the ſame powder?</p>
                  <p>Place 5 on the firſt, to 4 on the ſecond, and then againſt 16 on that firſt, is 12,8 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond; and next againſt 12,8 on the firſt, is 10,24 on the ſecond; and thirdly, againſt that 10,24 on the firſt, is 8,2 on the ſecond, which third number 8,2 is the anſwer to the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: ſhewing that 8 pounds, and 2 tenth parts of a pound of powder, is a due charge for a Gun of 4 inches bore.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="problem">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:108157:17"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM IX. A Company of men laying down ſeveral ſums of money together into one ſtock, wherewith they trade and get gain; to find out how much each mans part of the gain must be, anſwerable to his part of money laid down in ſtock.</head>
                  <p>LEt five men, whoſe names let be repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by theſe five letters, A, B, C, D, E, make a ſtock of 300 pounds, of which ſtock A put in 84 pounds, B put in 72 pounds, C put in 48 pounds, D put in 54 pounds, and E put in 42 pounds, which all together make the 300 pounds. Now at the end of a time, having traded therewith, they gained clearly 50 pounds: And let it be demanded, what por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the gain each man muſt have, according to his proportion of mony laid down in ſtock.</p>
                  <p>The Rule to anſwer this demand is thus:
<list type="analogy">
                        <item> As 300, the whole ſtock,</item>
                        <item>To 50 pounds the whole gain;</item>
                        <item> So is each mans portion of the ſtock,</item>
                        <item>To his portion of the gain.</item>
                     </list> Therefore,</p>
                  <p>Set 300, the ſtock on the firſt, to 50 the gain on the ſecond; and then againſt each mans particular portion laid down, being ſought out on the firſt, is his portion of the gain on the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:108157:18"/> ſecond. As againſt 84, the portion laid down by A on the firſt, is 14, his portion of the gain on the ſecond; and againſt 72, the portion of B, is 12 pounds, his portion of the gain; againſt 48, the portion of C, is 8 pounds, his portion of the gain; againſt 54, the portion of D, is 9, his portion of the gain; and againſt 42 pounds on the firſt, the portion of E, is 7 pounds on the ſecond, his portion of the 50 pounds gain. Thus much is each mans ſeveral portion of the 50 pounds gain; all which ſeveral portions of the gain added together, make up the whole gain of 50 pounds.</p>
                  <p>Thus upon our lines can we work that rule of Arithmetick, called <hi>The Rule of Fellowſhip;</hi> which is, when diverſe men adventure a ſtock of money together, and therewith trade, and either gain or loſe a certain ſum of money, to find each mans portion of the gain or loſſe, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to his portion of money put into the ſtock.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM X. Of Intereſt and Annuities.</head>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>To find the Interest of any ſum of money, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter any rate by the 100 propounded.</head>
                     <p>WHat is the Intereſt of 65 pounds for a year, after the rate of 8 in the 100?</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="31" facs="tcp:108157:18"/>By the rule of Proportion, the queſtion is thus reſolved:
<list type="analogy">
                           <item>As 100, is to 108;</item>
                           <item>So is 65, to the fourth term.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Set 1 or 100 on the firſt, to 108 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and then againſt 65 on the firſt, is 70,2 on the ſecond, which is 70 pounds 4 ſhillings; ſo much doth the principal and intereſt ariſe unto in a year, that is to ſay, five pounds and four ſhillings: And without ſtirring the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument againſt any other ſum of Principal on the firſt, is the Principal and Intereſt thereof on the ſecond. As againſt
40 pounds, is 43 pounds 4 ſhillings; and againſt 80 pounds, is 86 pounds and 8 ſhillings. From whence it appeareth, that 3 pounds 4 ſhillings is the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of 40 pounds for a year; and 6 pounds 8 ſhillings, the Intereſt of 80 pounds for a year. In like manner, againſt 27 pounds 14 ſhillings Principal, or 27,7 is 29 pounds 18 ſhillings, and a little more. Or elſe work thus:</p>
                     <p>Set 1 or 100 back to 8, and then againſt 65 on that firſt, is 5,2 on the ſecond; and againſt 40 pounds on the firſt, is 3,2 on the ſecond: So the Intereſt of the one is 5 pounds 4 ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and of the other 3 pounds 4 ſhillings.</p>
                     <p>If the rate of the Intereſt propoſed be 6 in the 100, then ſet 100 on the firſt, to 106 on the <pb n="32" facs="tcp:108157:19"/> ſecond; and then againſt 65 pounds on the firſt, is 68 pounds 18 ſhillings on the ſecond, which is the Principal and Intereſt together of 65 pounds for a year. Or,</p>
                     <p>Set 100 on the firſt, to 6 on the ſecond, and then againſt 65 on the firſt, is 3,9 on the ſecond; this 3,9 is 3 pounds 18 ſhillings, the Intereſt alone of 65 pounds for a year, and ſo of any other.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Of Intereſt of money continued from year to year.</head>
                     <p>The increaſe or Intereſt of money from year to year, for many years, is in continual proportion to the Principal, as 100 is to its In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt; as if 40 pounds were to be continued at Intereſt for many years, at the rate of 6 in the 100.</p>
                     <p>Set 100 on the firſt, to 106 on the ſecond, and then againſt 40 on the firſt, is 42,4 on the ſecond, that is 42 pounds 8 ſhillings, ſo much is the firſt years Principal and Intereſt. And now, if you look 42,4 on the firſt, you ſhall have right againſt it 44,9 and more, that is 44 pounds 18 ſhillings and more, for the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal and Intereſt of two years; and againſt 44,9 on the firſt, is 47,6 and better, on the ſecond, that is 47 pounds 12 ſhillings 8 pence, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and Principal of 40 pounds in three years. Again, againſt 47,6 on the firſt, is
50,45 <pb n="33" facs="tcp:108157:19"/> and better, that is 50 pounds 9 ſhillings 7 pence: So much is the Principal and Intereſt together of 40 pounds at the end of 4 years, and ſo forth to as many years as is required.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Of Annuities.</head>
                     <p>When lands are ſold at certain years pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, according to the yearly rent, to find what their value upon the purchaſe will be: Set 1 on the firſt, to the number of years pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe on the ſecond; and then againſt their yearly rent on the firſt, is the value of the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe on the ſecond.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Example.</hi> Let a houſe and land worth 16 pounds a year, be ſet to ſale at 14 years pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, and demand made, how much money it will ariſe unto at that rate.</p>
                     <p>Set 1 on the firſt, to 14, the number of years purchaſe on the ſecond; and then againſt 16; the yearly rent on the firſt, is 224 on the ſecond, which is 224 pounds: So much money doth the purchaſe ariſe unto, of 16 pounds a year bought at 14 years purchaſe.</p>
                     <p>If the price of the lands be given, and that it coſt after
14 years purchaſe, to find what yearly rent it was ſold at. In this caſe, Set 14 on the firſt, to 1 on the ſecond; and then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſum of money paid 224 pound, is 16, which is 16 pounds: So much is the yearly rent ſought.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="34" facs="tcp:108157:20"/>A man borrowed 666 pounds 13 ſhillings and 4 pence for 2 years, and covenanted that he would repay at the 12 years end
1333 pounds 6 ſhillings and 8 pence. It is deſired to know after what rate of Intereſt by the 100, he paid for his money borrowed.</p>
                     <p>Set 1333<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> on the firſt, (the ſum of money to be paid, to 666<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> on the ſecond (the ſumme lent) and then againſt 12 on the ſecond (the term of years it was lent) is 5,95, which is 5 pounds 19 ſhillings: So much by the 100 doth he pay for the money lent.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>A Sum of money being due at a certain time to come, to find what it is worth in preſent money, to take in.</head>
                     <p>There is 402 pounds 2 ſhillings due at the end of 5 years to come, I would know what it is worth in ready money, abating Intereſt for the money received in, before due, after the rate of 8 in the 100.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, ſet 108 on the firſt, to 100 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and then againſt 402,1 on the firſt, is 37,1 on the ſecond: Secondly, againſt 37,1 on the firſt, is 34,46 on the ſecond: Thirdly, againſt
34,46 on the firſt, is 31,95 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond: Fourthly, againſt 31,95 on the firſt, is 29,71 on the ſecond: Fifthly, againſt 29,71 on the firſt, is 373 on the ſecond. So much, <pb n="35" facs="tcp:108157:20"/> namely, 373 pounds may be received in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent money for the 402 pounds and 2 ſhillings due five years hence, as being the preſent worth thereof.</p>
                     <p>Here take notice, that as the Principal and Intereſt of money forborn for many years, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth in a proportion direct; So in this caſe, where money is paid many years before due, it decreaſeth in the like proportion.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:108157:21"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the double Scale of Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in Superficial meaſure, as Board, Glaſſe, Land, and the like.</head>
               <div n="1" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM I. The length and breadth of any ſquare, or long ſquare Superficies being given, to find the Content thereof.</head>
                  <p>IF the length and breadth be given in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, Then,
<list type="analogy">
                        <item>As 1 to the breadth in inches,</item>
                        <item>So is the length in inches,</item>
                        <item>To the Content in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example.</hi> Let a plain Superficies, as a Board or Plank be given to be meaſured, the breadth is found 30 inches, and its length 183, and the Content required.</p>
                  <p>Set 1 on the firſt, to 30 on the ſecond, and then againſt 183 on the firſt, is 5490, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſought in inches.</p>
                  <p>If the Superficies given, be a piece of land, 30 perches broad, and 183 long, the Content is 5490 perches.</p>
                  <p>Again, let a piece of Wainſcot be 2,5 foot
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:108157:21"/> in breadth, and 15,25 foot in length, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent will be found 38,12 foot. For,</p>
                  <p>Set 1 on the firſt, to 2,5 on the ſecond, and then againſt 15,25 on the firſt, is 38,12 foot, the Content ſought.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM II. The breadth and length of any Superficies being given in one kind of meaſure, to find the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in another kind of meaſure.</head>
                  <p>LEt the length and breadth be given in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and the Content required in feet. The Rule is thus:
<list type="analogy">
                        <item>As 144 to the breadth in inches,</item>
                        <item>So is the length in inches,</item>
                        <item>To the Content in feet.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example.</hi> Let the breadth be 30 inches, and the length
183 inches, and the Content in feet required.</p>
                  <p>In this caſe, becauſe 144 inches make a foot of ſuperficial meaſure, Set 144 on the firſt, to 30 the breadth on the ſecond, and then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt 183, the length on that firſt, is 38 foot, and a Fraction of a foot, being a little more than one tenth part of a foot: So many foot are in that Board, or what other platform it be, that is given to be ſo meaſured.</p>
                  <p>If the platform were a piece of land 30 per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches broad, and
183 perches long, then the <pb n="38" facs="tcp:108157:22"/> Analogie is thus: As 160, (the perches ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king an acre) to the breadth in perches; So is the length in perches, To the Content in acres.</p>
                  <p>And therefore in this caſe of land meaſure, Set 160 on the firſt, to 30 the breadth on the ſecond; and then againſt 183, the length on that firſt, is 34,31 on the ſecond: So many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres of land are contained in that ground.</p>
                  <p>If the place, whoſe Content is to be caſt up, be a Triangle, a Trapezia, or of any other form whatſoever, the Analogie in general is this.</p>
                  <p>As 144, or 160, &amp;c. Is to one of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers given to be multiplyed together; So is the other of them, to the Content in Feet or Acres, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>There is a piece of Wainſcot, that is 3,5 foot broad, and 21 foot long: How many yards is in it?</p>
                  <p>Seeing that in a yard are contained 9 foot; Therefore, Set 9 on the firſt, to 3,5 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond; and then againſt 21 on the firſt, is 8,16 on the ſecond: So many yards is in that piece.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="problem">
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:108157:22"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM III. The breadth of a Superficies being given in one kind of meaſure, and the length in another, to find the Content in the greater meaſure.</head>
                  <p>LEt the breadth of a Superficies given be in inches, and the length in feet, and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in feet required:</p>
                  <p>Here the Analogie is:
<list type="analogy">
                        <item>As 12 to the breadth in inches;</item>
                        <item>So the length in feet, to the Content in feet:</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>So that if the breadth be 30 inches, and the length 15,25 foot, the Content will be 38,12 foot: For,</p>
                  <p>Set 12 on the firſt, to 30 on the ſecond; and then againſt 15,25 on the firſt, is 38,12 on the ſecond, being the Content ſought for: Or elſe,</p>
                  <p>Set 12 to 15,25, and then againſt 30 on that firſt, is
38,12 on the ſecond.</p>
                  <p>By this rule alſo: If the breadth of a plot of land be given in perches, and the length in chains (being meaſured by a chain of 4 per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches long) the Content in Acres is readily had.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example.</hi> Let a piece of land be in breadth 30 perches, and in length 15,25 chains, meaſured by a chain of 4 perches in length.</p>
                  <p>In this caſe the Analogie is thus:
<list type="analogy">
                        <item>As 4 is to the breadth in poles,</item>
                        <item>So is the <pb n="40" facs="tcp:108157:23"/> length in chains to the Content in Acres.</item>
                     </list> Therefore, Set 4 to 30, and then againſt 15,25 on that firſt ſide whereon the 4 is, you ſhall have 11,4 on the ſecond ſide: So much is the Content in Acres of that piece of land.</p>
                  <p>Again, let a piece of land be 36 poles broad, and the length
23 chains and an half; to find the Content.</p>
                  <p>Set 4 on the firſt, to 36 on the ſecond, and then againſt 23,5 on that firſt, is 21,1 and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter on the ſecond: the Content ſought.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM IV. The length and breadth of a Superficies being gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in feet, to find the Content in yards.</head>
                  <p>TAke this for a general Rule: As 9 is to the breadth in feet; So is the length in feet, To the Content in yards.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example.</hi> Let the breadth of a pane of Wain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcot be
4 foot, and the length 12 foot, and the Content in yards be ſought for.</p>
                  <p>Here is no more to be done, but to ſet 9 on the firſt, to
4 on the ſecond; and then againſt 12 on the firſt, is 5,35 on the ſecond: The Content in yards of that pane. which is almoſt 5 yards, a quarter and an half, or rather 5 yards and one third part of a yard.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="problem">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:108157:23"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM V. The breadth of any Superficies being given in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches or feet, to find how much in length will make a ſuperficial foot.</head>
                  <p>The Rule is thus.
<list type="analogy">
                        <item>AS the breadth in inches, to 144;</item>
                        <item>So is 1 to the length in inches, to make a foot.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example.</hi> Let the breadth given be 30 in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and the length to make a foot at that breadth be required.</p>
                  <p>Set 30 on the firſt, to 144 on the ſecond, and then againſt 1 on the firſt, is 4,8 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond: So much in length makes a foot at 30 inches broad.</p>
                  <p>But if the breadth be given in feet; Then,
<list type="analogy">
                        <item>As the breadth in feet is to 1,</item>
                        <item>So is 1 to the length to make a foot:</item>
                     </list> Therefore,</p>
                  <p>Set 2,5 on the firſt, to 1 on the ſecond, and then againſt 1 on the firſt ſide, is 4 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, which 4 ſignifieth four tenth parts of a foot: So much in length makes a foot at that breadth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="problem">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:108157:24"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM VI. The length and breadth of a plot of land being given in chains, to find the Content in Acres.</head>
                  <p>HAving a chain of 4 perches long, divided into 100 links, that is, 25 in the perch; meaſure the length and breadth of the land to be meaſured in chains and links: And then caſt up the Content into Acres thus:
<list type="analogy">
                        <item>As 10 to the breadth in chains;</item>
                        <item> So is the length in chains, to the Content in Acres.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example.</hi> Let the breadth given be 7 chains, 50 links, and the length 45 chains, 75 links, and the Content in Acres ſought.</p>
                  <p>Set 10 on the firſt, to 7,5 on the ſecond, and then againſt 45,75 on the firſt, is 34,31 on the ſecond, which is the Content in Acres of that plat of land. Or,</p>
                  <p>Had the breadth been 15 chains, 25 links, and the breadth 22 chains, 50 links; then ſet 10 or 1 on the firſt, to 15,5 on the ſecond, and then againſt 22,50 on the firſt, is 34,31 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecond, the Content in Acres ſought for: which Fraction 31 above the 34 Acres, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains
1 rood 10 perches. So that the true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent is 34 Acres, 1 rood and 10 pole.</p>
                  <p>If the plot of land be of a Triangle form, or
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:108157:24"/> any other figure whatſoever, the Analogie is this:
<list type="analogy">
                        <item> As 10 is to one of the two numbers of chains, that are to be multiplyed together:</item>
                        <item> So is the other of them, to the Content in Acres.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>As if the half perpendicular of a Triangle be 3,75 chains, and the Baſe 45,75, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent will be found to be 17,15 Acres.</p>
                  <p>For ſet 10 on the firſt, to 3,75 on the ſecond, and then againſt 45; 75 on that firſt, is 17,15, the content.</p>
                  <p>Or elſe, having the whole Baſe, and whole perpendicular, ſay thus: As 20 to the whole perpendicular 7,50; So is the whole Baſe
45,75; To 17,15 the content in Acres, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: For,</p>
                  <p>Set 20 on the firſt, to 7,50 on the ſecond, and then againſt 45,75 on the firſt, is 17,15 on the ſecond.</p>
                  <p>Or if the Baſe of a Triangle be 36,83 chains, and the perpendicular 17,59 chains, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent will be found by either way of work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to be 32,39, which is 32 acres, 1 rood 22 perches.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="problem">
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:108157:25"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM VII. The Content of a piece of land being meaſured by one kind of perch, to find the Content there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, after another kind of perch.</head>
                  <p>THeſe kind of proportions are wrought by the Rule of Three reverſe, after a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicated proportion; and the Analogie is thus:
<list type="analogy">
                        <item> As the length of the ſecond perch, is to the length of the firſt perch:</item>
                        <item> So the content in acres given, to a fourth number: and ſo is that fourth number to a fifth number, which is the content ſought.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Suppoſe a piece of land meaſured by the 16½ foot-pole, do contain 34,3 acres, and it be demanded; How much it would contain, if it were meaſured by an 18 foot-pole.</p>
                  <p>Note that I call the 16½ foot-perch, the firſt perch, becauſe by it the land was meaſured; and the 18 foot-perch I call the ſecond perch, becauſe according to it the content is ſought for. Wherefore,</p>
                  <p>Set the ſecond perch 18 on the firſt, to 16,5 on the ſecond, (the perch firſt uſed) and then againſt 34,3, the content in acres given, on the firſt, is 31,45 on the ſecond; and then againſt that
31,45 on that firſt, is 28,8 on the ſecond: <pb n="45" facs="tcp:108157:25"/> So much is the content in acres by the 18 foot-pole, which was demanded.</p>
                  <p>In like manner, were the content given 5 acres, 2 roods, 20 pole, or 5,62: Set 18 on the firſt, to 16,5 on the ſecond, and then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt 5,62 on the firſt, is 5,15 on the ſecond. And laſtly, againſt that 5,15 on that firſt, is neer about 4,7 on the ſecond: So much is the content of that cloſe by the 18 foot-pole.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. VIII. The one ſide of any piece of land being given, to find how much in breadth the other way will make an acre of land.</head>
                  <p>LEt the ſide of a cloſe be 20 pole, and it be required; How much in breadth will make an acre of land at that length.</p>
                  <p>Set the breadth given, 20 on the firſt, to 160 on the ſecond; and then againſt 1 or 10 on that firſt, is 8 on the ſecond. So much in breadth makes an acre at 20 pole long.</p>
                  <p>Or if the ſide meaſured be 25, then ſet 25 to 160, and againſt 1 on that firſt, is 6,4 on the ſecond, the breadth ſought for. And if the length be 32 pole, the breadth to make an acre will be 5 pole.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="problem">
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:108157:26"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM. IX. A plot of land being laid down, and caſt up by any Scale, to find how much it will contain by any other Scale, either greater or leſſer.</head>
                  <p>SUppoſe a plot of land being laid down, and caſt up by a Scale of 10, in the inch, does contain 28,5 acres; and it is required to know how many acres it will contain, ſhould it be caſt up by a Scale of 12 in the inch.</p>
                  <p>Here becauſe 12, the Scale to be uſed, is leſſer than
10, the Scale formerly uſed: And ſo by conſequence, the content of the given plot by the Scale of 12, will be more acres than it is by the Scale of 10 in the inch. Therefore,</p>
                  <p>Set the Scale uſed 10 on the firſt, to the Scale to be uſed 12 on the ſecond, and then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the content known 28,5 on the firſt, is 34,2 acres, or neer thereabouts on the ſecond: So much is the content by the Scale of 12 in the inch.</p>
                  <p>But if the plot had been laid down, and caſt up by a Scale of 12, and the content re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by a Scale of 10 in the inch, which is the greater Scale, and therefore the content is the leſſer. Then,</p>
                  <p>Set 12 on the firſt, to 10 on the ſecond,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:108157:26"/> which done, right againſt the content in acres by the Scale of 12 on the firſt, is the content by the Scale of 10 on the ſecond: As if the content by the Scale of 12 be 34,2 acres, then the content by the Scale of 10, will be found to be 28,5 acres neer. For,</p>
                  <p>Set 12 on the firſt, to 10 on the ſecond, and then againſt 34,2 on the firſt, is 28,5 on the ſecond.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. X. The Diameter of a circle being given, to find the Circumference.</head>
                  <p>The Analogie ſtands thus:
<list type="analogy">
                        <item>AS 1 is to the Diameter;</item>
                        <item>So is 3,142 to the Circumference.</item>
                     </list> Or,</p>
                  <p>As 7 to 22; So is the Diameter to the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference. If the Diameter be 15 inches, what is the Circumference? Set 1 on the firſt, to 15 on the ſecond, and then right againſt 3,142 on the firſt, is 47,13 on the ſecond: So much is the Circumference of that circle. Or,</p>
                  <p>Set 7 on the firſt, to 22 on the ſecond, and then againſt 15 on the firſt, is 47,13 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, as before.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="problem">
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:108157:27"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM XI. The Circumference of a circle being given, to find the Diameter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <list type="analogy">
                        <item>AS 22 is to 7,</item>
                        <item>So is the Circumference to the Diameter.</item>
                     </list> Or,
<list type="analogy">
                        <item>As 3,142 to 1,</item>
                        <item>So is the Circumference to the Diameter.</item>
                     </list> So if the Circumference be 47,13, what is the Diameter?</p>
                  <p>Set 22 on the firſt, to 7 on the ſecond, and then againſt 47,13 on the firſt, is 15 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond: So much is the Diameter of that cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle. Or,</p>
                  <p>Set 3,142 to 1, and then againſt 47,13 is 15, as before.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM XII. The Diameter of a circle being given, to find the ſide of a Square equal to it.</head>
                  <p>THe Diameter of a circle is 15 inches, what is the ſide of the ſquare equal to it in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent?</p>
                  <p>Set 1 on the firſt, to 15 on the ſecond, and then right againſt this number 8862 on the firſt, is 13,29 on the ſecond: So much Is the ſide of a ſquare, that is equal in Content to that circle.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="problem">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:108157:27"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM XIII. The Circumference of a circle being given, to find the ſide of a ſquare, equal in Content to that circle.</head>
                  <p>LEt the Circumference of a circle be 47,13, and the ſide of a ſquare equal to it be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired.</p>
                  <p>Set 1 on the firſt, to 47,13 on the ſecond, and then alwayes againſt this number 2821 on the firſt, is 13,29 on the ſecond: So many inches is the ſide of a ſquare, that is equal in Content to the circle given.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. XIV. The Diameter of a circle being given, to find the ſide of a ſquare, that may be inſcribed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it.</head>
                  <p>LEt the Diameter of a circle be 15 inches, and it be required, what the ſide of that ſquare will be, that may juſtly be inſcribed within it?</p>
                  <p>Set 1 on the firſt, to that 15 on the ſecond, &amp; then againſt this number 7071 on the firſt, is neer about 10,6 on the ſecond: Therefore 10,6 inches, is the ſide of a ſquare that may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed within a circle of 15 inches Diameter. <pb n="50" facs="tcp:108157:28"/>Or thus it may be found:</p>
                  <p>Double the ſquare of the Semidiameter, the Root ſquare of that Product is the ſide of the ſquare inſcribed; but this is by the By.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. XV. The Circumference of a circle being given, to find the ſide of a ſquare that may be inſcribed within it.</head>
                  <p>LEt the Circumference given be 47,13, and the ſide of a ſquare that may be inſcribed within it, be required.</p>
                  <p>Set 1 on the firſt, to the Circumference 47,13 on the ſecond; and then againſt this general number 2251 on the firſt, is neer about 10,6 on the ſecond: So many inches is the ſide of that ſquare, that can be inſcribed within the circle given.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. XVI. The Diameter or Circumference of a circle, either of them being given, to find the ſide of an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilater triangle, to be inſcribed within that circle.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt, having the Diameter given, which ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe 14 inches and it be required, to find the ſide of the Equilater Triangle that may be inſcribed in that circle.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:108157:28"/>Set 1 on the firſt, to 14 on the ſecond, (that is, to the Diameter given) and then againſt this general number 8,65 on the firſt, is 12,1 on the ſecond: Therefore conclude, that
12 in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and one tenth part of an inch, is the length of the ſide of that Equilater Triangle, which may be inſcribed within a circle of 14 inches Diameter.</p>
                  <p>Or you may ſet 1 to the general number 865, and then againſt 14 is 12,1, as before.</p>
                  <p>Having the Circumference given, which let it be ſuppoſed to be 44, then to find the ſide of that Equilater Triangle, the work is thus.</p>
                  <p>Set 1 on the firſt, to the Circumference gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven 44 on the ſecond, and then againſt this general number 272,6 on the firſt, is 12,1 on the ſecond, the ſide of the Equilater Triangle ſought for.</p>
                  <p>Or, Set 1 to that general number 272,6, and then againſt 44, is 12,1, and ſo of any other.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. XVII. The Diameter or Circumference of any circle being given, to find the ſuperficial Content.</head>
                  <p>LEt the Diameter of a circle propoſed be 15 inches, and the ſuperficial Content of it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded.</p>
                  <p>Set 1 on the firſt, to 15 on the ſecond, &amp; then
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:108157:29"/> then againſt this general number 7854 on the firſt, is
11,83 on the ſecond; and then again againſt that 11,83 on the firſt, is
176,74 on the ſecond: This 176,74 is the Content of that circle propoſed.</p>
                  <p>But if the Circumference of any circle only be given, as if it were given 47,13, and the Content required. Then,</p>
                  <p>Set 1 on the firſt, to the Circumference gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, 47,13 on the ſecond; and then againſt this general number 7958 on the firſt, is neer 37,8 on the ſecond: And laſtly, againſt this 37,8 on the firſt, is
176,74 on the ſecond, the Content required.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. XVIII. The Diameter, with the ſuperficial Content of any circle given, to find the Content of any other circle that is twice the Diameter of the first.</head>
                  <p>LEt the Diameter of a circle given be 7 in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and the Content 38,5 inches, and the demand be, to know what another circle is, that is double in Diameter to the former.</p>
                  <p>Set 7 on the firſt, to 14 on the ſecond, and then againſt the known Content 38,5 on the firſt, is 77 on the ſecond; and then again, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that 77 found on the firſt, is 154 on the ſecond: So much is the Content of that other <pb n="53" facs="tcp:108157:29"/> circle, whoſe Diameter is double to the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter of the circle given, that is to ſay, of 14 inches Diameter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. XIX. The Content of a circle being known, to find the Diameter and Circumference.</head>
                  <p>LEt the Content of a circle be known to be 176,74 inches, and it be required to know what the Diameter of that circle is, as alſo what the Circumference is.</p>
                  <p>For the Diameter, Set 1 on the firſt, to 1,273 on the ſecond, and then againſt the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent known, 176,74 on the firſt, is 225 on the ſecond; the ſquare root of this 225 is 15: So many inches is the Diameter of that circle.</p>
                  <p>For the Circumference, Set 1 on the firſt, to this general number 12,57, and then againſt 176,74 on the firſt, is neer 2221, whereof the ſquare root is 47,13: So many inches is the Circumference of that circle.</p>
                  <p>The Root ſquare of the Content of any cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, is the ſide of a ſquare equal to it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:108157:30"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the double ſcales in ſolid meaſure, ſuch as Timber, Stone, &amp;c.</head>
               <div n="1" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. I. The ſide of a ſquare ſolid being given in inches, or feet, to find how much in length will make a foot ſolid in inches or feet.</head>
                  <p>SVppoſe the ſide of a ſqure log be 25,45 inches, and demand is made, How many in length will make a foot.</p>
                  <p>Set the breadth given, 25,45 on the firſt, to this general number 41,57 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond; and then againſt 1 on the firſt, is 1,63 on the ſecond, and againſt this 1,63 found on the firſt, is 2,67 on the ſecond: So much in length makes a foot of Timber, <hi>viz.</hi> 2 inches, and
67 parts of 100.</p>
                  <p>If the breadth be given in parts of a foot (the foot being divided into 100 or 1000 equal parts) to find what parts of a foot in length will make a foot of Timber. As if the breadth of a piece of Timber be 2 foot and 120 parts of 1000 of a foot; then to find how much in length will make a foot ſolid.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:108157:30"/>Set 2,120 on the firſt, to 1 on the ſecond, and then againſt 1 on the firſt, is 471 on the ſecond; and laſtly, againſt that 471 on the firſt, is 222: So many parts of a foot (it being divided into 1000) do make a foot of Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber at that breadth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. II. The breadth and depth of an unequal ſquare ſolid being given in parts of a foot, or in inches, to find how much in length will make a foot.</head>
                  <p>LEt the breadth of a piece of Timber be 2,5 foot, and the depth 1,8 foot. Here firſt, by Multiplication find out the Content of the Baſe or end, which you ſhall find to be 4,5, which being had, get the length of a foot ſolid thus.</p>
                  <p>Set the Content of the head found, 4,5 on the firſt, to 1 on the ſecond; and then againſt 1 on the firſt, is 222 on the ſecond: So many parts of a foot divided into 1000, do make a foot of Timber.</p>
                  <p>But if the breadth be given 30 inches, and the depth 21,6, then the Content of the Baſe will be 648, and the work thus wrought.</p>
                  <p>Set 648 on the firſt, to 1728 on the ſecond, and then againſt 1 on the firſt, is 11,27 on the ſecond; and laſtly, look this
11,27 on the <pb n="56" facs="tcp:108157:31"/> firſt, and right againſt it on the ſecond, is 2,67 inches, the length of a foot of Timber in that log, whoſe breadth is 30 inches, and depth 21,6. Or you may work thus:</p>
                  <p>Set 12 on the firſt, to 21,6 on the ſecond, and then againſt 30 on the firſt, is 54 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond; This done, Set the new found number 54 on the firſt, to 144 on the ſecond; and then againſt 1 on the firſt, is 2,67 on the ſecond, the length to make a foot, as before.</p>
                  <p>Such an unequal ſquared piece of timber, as is here mentioned, may be reduced into a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſquare, and wrought as in the firſt Problem. And ſo the perfect ſquare of this unequal ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red log, whoſe breadth is 30 inches, and depth 21,6, will be found to be 2,120 foot. Or 25,40 inches, and now you may proceed here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, as in the firſt Problem you do with ſquare Timber.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM III. The breadth of a ſquare ſolid, or the ſide of a ſquare equal to the Baſe of any unequal ſquare ſolid, and the length of the ſame ſolid being gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in inches or feet, to find the Content in feet.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt, ſuppoſe the breadth and length be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in inches, as let the breadth be 25 in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, <pb n="57" facs="tcp:108157:31"/> and 45 parts of an inch, and the length 183 inches, and the Content demanded.</p>
                  <p>Set this general number 41,57 on the firſt, to the ſide of the ſquare given 25,45 on the ſecond, and then againſt the length in inches 183 on the firſt, is 112 on the ſecond: And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, againſt that
112 on the firſt, is 68,62 on the ſecond: Therefore the Content of the piece of Timber propoſed is 68 foot, and 62 parts of a foot, into 100 divided.</p>
                  <p>But if the breadth be given in feet, and parts of a foot; As let the breadth of the ſolid be 2 foot, and 12 parts of a foot, ſuch as the whole foot is divided into 100, and the length 15 foot, and 25 parts. Then,</p>
                  <p>Set 1 on the firſt, to 2,12 on the ſecond, that is to the breadth given; and then againſt 15,25 on the firſt, is 32,35 on the ſecond: And laſtly, againſt that 32,35 on the firſt, is 68,62 on the ſecond: So much is the Content in feet of that ſolid.</p>
                  <p>If an unequal ſquared ſolid be to be meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, it is as good a way as any, to reduce it to a perfect ſquare, and then compute the Content as here before, and this reduction is eaſily made; for multiply the breadth by the thickneſſe; and the Product is the Content of the Baſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the ſquare root is the ſide of a perfect equal ſquare; to that unequal ſquare given.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="problem">
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:108157:32"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM IV. The ſide of a ſquared ſolid given in inches, and the length in feet, to find the Content in feet.</head>
                  <p>LEt the ſide of a perfect ſquare ſolid be 25 in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and 45 parts of an inch, ſuch as the whole inch is divided into 100; and the length 15 foot, and 25 parts of a foot, Such as the whole foot is divided into
100, and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in feet required.</p>
                  <p>Set alwayes 12 on the firſt, to the breadth in inches 25,45 on the ſecond; and then againſt 15,25 the length in feet, is 32,35 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond: This 32,35 found on the firſt, and right againſt it on the ſecond is 68,62: So many foot of Timber, and parts of a foot, are in that log.</p>
                  <p>If an unequal ſquare ſolid be to be meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, reduce the Baſe of that unequal ſquare ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid into a perfect ſquare, and then find the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, as here is taught.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM V. The length, breadth and depth of a ſquare ſolid being given in inches, to find the Content in feet.</head>
                  <p>BY the breadth and depth, get the Content of the Baſe; as let the length of a piece of <pb n="59" facs="tcp:108157:32"/> Timber be 183 inches, the breadth 20 inches, and the depth 13 inches, and the Content in feet deſired: Here 20 and 13 multiplied to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, make 260 for the Content of the Baſe.</p>
                  <p>Now, Set 1728 on the firſt, to 260, the Content of the Baſe on the ſecond; and then againſt 138, the length on the firſt, is
27,<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> neer on the ſecond: Wherefore you may conclude, that in the piece of Timber propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, is contained 27 foot and an half, with a little more, which is inconſiderable. Or elſe you may work it thus:</p>
                  <p>Set 12 on the firſt, to 13 the depth on the ſecond, and then againſt 20 the breadth on the firſt, is a fourth number, <hi>viz.</hi>
21,70 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond. This done, Set 144 on the firſt, to this fourth number new found 21,70 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and then againſt 183, the length of the piece on the firſt, is 27,5 on the ſecond: So that the Content of that piece of Timber, is 27 foot and an half, as before.</p>
                  <p>Or you might have ſet 12 on the firſt, to 20 on the ſecond, and then againſt 13 on the firſt, you ſhould have had 21,70 on the ſecond, for the fourth number, as afore; to which ſet 144 on the firſt, and then againſt 183, is 27 foot and an half.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="problem">
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:108157:33"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM VI. The Baſe of any ſquare ſolid being given in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and the length in feet, to find the Content in feet.</head>
                  <p>LEt the Baſe of a piece of Timber contain 260 inches, and the length 15 foot and a quarter, and the Content thereof in feet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired.</p>
                  <p>Set 144 on the firſt, to the Content of the Baſe 260 on the ſecond; and then againſt 15,25 on the firſt, is 27,5 on the ſecond. So then 27 foot and an half is the Content deſired.</p>
                  <p>If both the length and content of the Baſe be given in feet; then, Set 1 on the firſt, to the Content of the Baſe in feet on the ſecond, and then againſt the length in feet on the firſt, is the Content in feet on the ſecond: As if the length of a piece of Timber be 15 foot and a quarter, and the Content of the Baſe 4 foot and an half.</p>
                  <p>Set 1 on the firſt, to 4 and an half on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and then againſt 15 and a quarter on the firſt, is 68,62 on the ſecond; that is 68 foot and an half, and almoſt half a quarter: So much is the Content of that piece.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="problem">
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:108157:33"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM VII. The Diameter of a Cylender given in inches or feet, to find the length of a foot, according to that Diameter.</head>
                  <p>LEt the Diameter of a Cylender, or round piece of Timber or Stone be 15 inches, and it be demanded, How much in length makes a foot ſolid?</p>
                  <p>Set the Diameter 15 on the firſt, to this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral number
46,90 on the ſecond, and then againſt 1 on the firſt, is 3,13 on the ſecond; and then againſt that 3,13 found on the firſt, is 9,78 on the ſecond: So much in length makes a foot of Timber, that is 9 inches, and 78 parts of 100, of an inch.</p>
                  <p>But if the Diameter be taken in feet, and parts of feet, then ſet the Diameter 1,25 on the firſt, to this general number 1128 on the ſecond, and then againſt 1 on the firſt, is 9027 on the ſecond, and againſt this 9027 found on the firſt, you have 8,15 on the ſecond, that is 8 parts of a foot, ſuch as the whole foot is divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into 10 parts, and
15 parts of 100 of one tenth over: So much in length makes a foot.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="problem">
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:108157:34"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM VIII. The circumference of a Cylinder given in inches, or tenth parts of feet, to find the length to make a ſolid foot.</head>
                  <p>LEt the circumference of a round log be 47 inches, and 13 hundred parts of an inch, and the length to make a foot, deſired.</p>
                  <p>Set the circumference 47,13 on the firſt, to 147,36 on the ſecond, and then againſt 1 on the firſt, is 31,2 on the ſecond, and againſt that 31,2 on the firſt, is 9,78 on the ſecond: So many inches and parts in length make a foot ſolid.</p>
                  <p>But if the circumference be given in feet, and parts of feet, as let the fore-mentioned Cylinder be meaſured by feet, and parts of feet, and be found to contain 3 foot and 93 parts of a foot. Then,</p>
                  <p>Set the circumference 3,93 on the firſt, to this number 3545 on the ſecond, and then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt 1 on the firſt, is 903 on the ſecond; and then againſt 903 found on the firſt, is neer 8,15 on the ſecond: So much is the length in foot meaſure to make a foot.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="problem">
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:108157:34"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM. IX. The Diameter and length of a Cylinder given in inches or feet, to find the Content in inches, or tenth parts of feet.</head>
                  <p>LEt the Diameter of a Cylinder be 15 in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and the length
105 inches, and the Content in inches ſought for.</p>
                  <p>Set this number 1128 on the firſt, to 15 on the ſecond, the Diameter known; and then againſt the length 105 on the firſt, is 1396 on the ſecond; and again, againſt this 1396 on the firſt, is 18553,5 on the ſecond: The whole Content in inches, which divided by 1728, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth 10 foot, and almoſt three quarters.</p>
                  <p>But if the Diameter and length be taken by foot-meaſure, as let the Diameter be 1,25 foot, and the length 8,75 foot. Then,</p>
                  <p>Set the number 1128 on the firſt, to 1,25 (the Diameter in foot-meaſure) on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond; and then againſt 8,75, the length on the firſt, is 9,69 on the ſecond. And laſtly, againſt 9,69 on the firſt, is 10,737 foot, or 10 foot, and almoſt three quarters: the Content ſought for, as before.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="problem">
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:108157:35"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM. X. The Diameter and length of a Cylinder given in inches, to find the Content in feet.</head>
                  <p>LEt the Diameter of a circle be 15 inches, and the length 105 inches, and the Content in feet deſired.</p>
                  <p>Set this number 4690 on the firſt, to 15 the Diameter on the ſecond, and then againſt 105, the length on the firſt, is 33,58 on the ſecond; and again, againſt this 33,58 on the firſt, is 10,737 on the ſecond: So then 10 foot, and almoſt three quarters, is contained in that Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lender.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. XI. The Diameter of a Cylinder given inches, and the length in feet, to find the content in feet.</head>
                  <p>LEt a Cylinder be given to be meaſured, whoſe Diameter is
15 inches, and the length 8 foot, and 75 parts of 100 of a foot, and let it be required by theſe meaſures onely, to give the Content in feet.</p>
                  <p>Set this general number 1354 on the firſt, to 15 the Diameter on the ſecond; and then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt 8,75 the length in feet on the firſt, is 969 on the ſecond: And laſtly, againſt this 969 on
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:108157:35"/> the firſt, is 10,74 on the ſecond: So much doth that Cylinder contain, <hi>viz.</hi> 10 foot and almoſt three quarters.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. XII. The circumference and length of a Cylinder given in inches, to find the content in inches.</head>
                  <p>LEt a Cylinder be given to be meaſured, whoſe length is
105 inches, and its circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence 47,13 inches, and let it be required only by theſe meaſures, to give the Content in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, which to do:</p>
                  <p>Set this general number 3545 on the firſt, to 47,13 on the ſecond (that is the circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence) and then againſt 105, the length on the firſt, is 1396 on the ſecond. Now again, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this 1396 on the firſt, is 18555: So ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny inches are contained in that Cylinder.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM XIII. The circumference and length of a Cylinder given in inches, to find the content in feet.</head>
                  <p>LEt the fore-mentioned Cylinder be propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, whoſe length is 105 inches, and the circumference 47,13 inches, and the content in feet required by this meaſure onely. In this caſe:</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:108157:36"/>Set this general number 14736 on the firſt, to 47,13 on the ſecond, and then againſt 105, the length in inches, is 33,58 on the ſecond, and againſt this 3358 on the firſt, is
10,74 on the ſecond, which is 10 feet and 74 parts of 100 of a foot.</p>
                  <p>But if the circumference and length be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in foot-meaſure, as if the circumference be 3,927 foot, and the length 8,75 foot, and the Content in feet required. Then,</p>
                  <p>Set this general number 3545 on the firſt, to 3,927 the circumference on the ſecond, and then againſt 8,75 the length on the firſt, is 969 on the ſecond; and again, againſt that 969 on the firſt, is 10,74 on the ſecond: So much is the Content in feet required.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. XIV. The circumference of a Cylinder taken in inches, and the length in feet, to find the content in feet.</head>
                  <p>IN the Cylinder afore propoſed, having the circumference in inches 47,13, and the length in feet 8,75. I thereby to find the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in feet, do work thus:</p>
                  <p>Set this general number 4254 on the firſt, to the circumference in inches 47,13 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and then againſt 8,75 the length in feet <pb n="67" facs="tcp:108157:36"/> on the firſt, is 969 on the ſecond; and laſtly, againſt this 969 on the firſt, is 10,74 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond: So much is the content in feet.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. XV. The Diameters of any veſſel at the head, and at the bung, with the length in inches had, to find the content thereof, firſt in inches, and then in gallons, either of Wine or Beer.</head>
                  <p>LEt the length of a veſſel be 40 inches, the Diameter at the head 18 inches, and the Diameter at the bung 32 inches, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the veſſel in inches and gallons is ſought for. Which to find,</p>
                  <p>You muſt firſt get two third parts of the Content of a circle anſwerable to the Diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at the bung; and one third part of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of a circle anſwerable to the Diameter at the head, and add them two numbers together, and their total multiply by the length of the veſſel, and the Product is the Content in inches.</p>
                  <p>Now to get the two third parts of the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle at the bung; Set
1 on the firſt, to this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral number 5236 on the ſecond, and then againſt 1024, the ſquare of 32, the Diameter at the bung is 536,166, which is two third parts of the Content of that circle at the bung.</p>
                  <p>For the one third part of the circle at the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:108157:37"/> head; Set 1 on the firſt, to this general num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber 2618 on the ſecond, and then againſt 324, the ſquare of 18 the diameter at the head on the firſt, is 84,823 on the ſecond, which is one third part of the content of the circle at the head.</p>
                  <p>Theſe two numbers 536,166 and 84,823 added together, make
620,989. This 620,989 multiply by 40, and it giveth 24839,56: So many inches are contained in it.</p>
                  <p>And now to know how many Wine-gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons are in this veſſel, divide the content in inches 24839,56 by 231, which is the number of inches contained in a Wine-gallon, and the quotient is 107,53: So many Wine-gallons are in that veſſel.</p>
                  <p>To know how many Ale or Beer-gallons are in it, divide
24839,56 the content in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. By 272,25, which is the number of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in a Beer-gallon, the quotient is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the veſſel in Beer-gallons. How to multiply and divide is ſhewed before, and therefore I need not ſhew it here again.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:108157:37"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the double ſcales of Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in Spherical Bodies, ſuch as Globes, Bullets, &amp;c.</head>
               <div n="1" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. I. The Diameter of any Spherical Body being known, to find the circumference.</head>
                  <p>LEt the Diameter of a Bullet be 9 in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and the circumference ſought for.</p>
                  <p>Set 7 on the firſt, to 22 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and then againſt 9 on the firſt, is 28,28 on the ſecond: So many inches is the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of a Bullet of 9 inches diameter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. II. The circumference of any Spherical Body being known, to find the Diameter.</head>
                  <p>LEt the circumference of a Bullet be 28,28 inches, and the diameter ſought for.</p>
                  <p>Set 22 on the firſt, to 7 on the ſecond, and then againſt 28,28 on the firſt, is 9 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, <pb n="70" facs="tcp:108157:38"/> that is, 9 inches is the diameter of that Bullet, whoſe circumference is 28 inches, and 28 hundred parts of an inch.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. III. The Diameter and circumference of any ſpheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Body being known, to find the ſuperficial content.</head>
                  <p>LEt the diameter of a Globe be 9 inches, and the circumference
28,28 inches, and it is demanded, How many ſquare inches, the Superficies of that Globe doth contain? Then,</p>
                  <p>Set 1 on the firſt, to 9 the diameter on the ſecond, and then againſt 28,28 on the firſt, is very neer 254,5 on the ſecond: So then 254,5 inches and an half, are contained in the Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies of that Globe.</p>
                  <p>Or elſe by knowing onely the diameter, work thus; Set 1 on the firſt, to this number 3,1416 on the ſecond; and then againſt 81, the ſquare of the diameter on the firſt, is 254,5 on the ſecond, as before; here you ſee are two wayes of working, and both agreeing: So that one proveth the other.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="problem">
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:108157:38"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM. IV. The Axis or Diameter of a Globe being known, to find the ſolid content.</head>
                  <p>IF the diameter of a Globe be 9 inches, what is the ſolid content in ſquare cubicle inches?</p>
                  <p>For reſolving this and the like queſtions, the Rule is this; As the diameter is to the Cube of it ſelf, So is 11 to the ſolid Content, The Cube of 9 the Diameter known is 729, which Cube, if you know it not, is thus found.</p>
                  <p>Set 1 on the firſt, to 9 on the ſecond, and then againſt
9 on the firſt, is 81, the ſquare of 9, on the ſecond; and laſtly, againſt this 81 on the firſt, is 729 on the ſecond, which is the Cube of
9, the Cube being had.</p>
                  <p>Set 9 on the firſt, to 729 on the ſecond, and then againſt 11 on the firſt, is 891 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond: Therefore 891 cubick inches are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the ſolid body of that Globe. Or,</p>
                  <p>Set 1 on the firſt, to 9 on the ſecond, and then againſt
11 on the firſt, is 99 on the ſecond, and next againſt this 99 on the firſt, is 891 on the ſecond, as before.</p>
                  <p>If the Diameter be 21 inches, then ſet 21 on the firſt, to
9261, its Cube on the ſecond; and then againſt 11 on the firſt, is 4851 on the <pb n="72" facs="tcp:108157:39"/> ſecond: So many cubick inches are in a Globe of
11 inches diameter. Or,</p>
                  <p>Set 1 to 21, and then againſt 11 is 235, and aginſt that
235 is 4851, as before.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM V. The Diameter of a Bullet being given, with the weight; to find the weight of another Bullet of the ſame metal, but of another Diameter, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther greater or leſſer.</head>
                  <p>LEt there be propounded an Iron Bullet of 6 inches diameter, weighing 30 pound, and let the queſtion be put, What another Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let of the ſame metall will weigh, that is of 7 inches diameter.</p>
                  <p>Set 6 on the firſt, to 7 on the ſecond, and then againſt
30, the weight on the firſt, is 35 on the ſecond; Secondly, againſt 35 on the firſt, is 40; 8 on the ſecond; Thirdly, againſt 40,8 on the firſt, is 47,7 on the ſecond: So then the concluſion is, that 47 pounds, and 7 tenth parts of a pound, is the weight of that other Bullet of 7 inches diameter, which was ſought for.</p>
                  <p>If a Bullet of 6 inches diameter weigh 32 pounds, what will a Bullet of the ſame metal weigh, that is of 3 inches diameter?</p>
                  <p>Set 6 on the firſt, to 3 on the ſecond, and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:108157:39"/> then againſt 32, the weight on the firſt, is 16 on the ſecond; Secondly, againſt 16 on the firſt, is 8 on the ſecond; and laſtly, againſt 8 on the firſt, is 4 on the ſecond: So then 4 pounds is the weight of that Bullet of 3 inches diameter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM VI. Having the ſide of a cubick body of ſilver with the worth thereof, to find the worth of another cubick body of ſilver, whoſe ſide is greater or leſſer than that of the body given.</head>
                  <p>IF a Cube body of ſilver being 4 inches ſquare be worth 12 pounds, What will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Cube body of the ſame metal be worth that is 5 inches ſquare?</p>
                  <p>Set 4 (the ſide of the body whoſe worth is known) on the firſt, to 5 (the ſide of that body whoſe worth is ſought) on the ſecond; and then againſt 12, the worth known on the firſt, is 15 on the ſecond; next againſt 15 on the firſt, is 18,57 on the ſecond; and thirdly, againſt 18,57 on the firſt, is 23,4 on the ſecond, which is 23 pounds and four tenths of a pound; that is 8 ſhillings: So then the worth of that cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bick body of ſilver of 5 inches ſquare is 23 pounds and 8 ſhillings.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="problem">
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:108157:40"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM VII. Having the weight of a Bullet of one kind of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, to find the weight of a Bullet of another kind of metal, being equal in magnitude.</head>
                  <p>BEfore I proceed to reſolve this Problem, I will ſhew the proportions between ſome ſeveral metals uſed for this purpoſe, as of Braſs, Iron, Lead and Stone, according to the beſt approved Authours, as followeth.</p>
                  <p>The proportion between Lead and Iron is as 2 to 3; So that a Leaden Bullet of 3 pounds weight, is equal in diameter with an Iron Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let of
2 pounds weight.</p>
                  <p>The proportion between Iron and Stone is as 3 to 8: Therefore a Stone of 3 pounds weight is equal in bigneſſe to a piece of Iron of 8 pounds weight, and a Stone body of 30 pounds weight, is equal in magnitude to an Iron body of 80 pounds weight, of the ſame form.</p>
                  <p>The proportion between Lead and Stone is as 4 to 1: So that a Bullet of Lead of 4 pounds weight, and a Stone Bullet of one pound weight, are equal in diameter; and a Leaden Bullet of 40 pounds weight, and a Stone Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let of 10 pounds weight, are equal in diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or magnitude.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="75" facs="tcp:108157:40"/>The proportion between Iron and Braſſe, is as 16 to 18; and the proportion between Lead and Braſſe, is as 24 to 19.</p>
                  <p>Remember that ſome Stone is heavier than other, and ſo likewiſe of metals, the finer they are, the heavier they be, being of the ſame mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude: but we ſpeak of the ordinary ſort in uſe. And now for reſolving the Problem.</p>
                  <p>Having the weight of a Bullet of Lead, to find the weight of a Bullet of Marble of the ſame bigneſſe.</p>
                  <p>If a Bullet of Lead weigh 106 pounds, What will a Bullet of Marble weigh?</p>
                  <p>By the former Rule it is found, that a Bullet of Lead to the like Bullet of Marble, beareth ſuch proportion as 4 doth to 1. Therefore,</p>
                  <p>Set 4 on the firſt, to 1 on the ſecond, and then againſt
106 on the firſt, is 26,5 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond: So much is the weight of a Stone Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, that is equal in bigneſſe to that Leaden one of 106 pounds weight.</p>
                  <p>On the contrary, having the weight of a Stone Bullet, to find the weight of a Leaden Bullet, of the ſame magnitude.</p>
                  <p>Set 1 on the firſt, to 4 on the ſecond, and then againſt
26,5; the weight of the Stone Bullet on the firſt, is 106 on the ſecond, the weight of the Iron Bullet.</p>
                  <p>There is a Bullet of Iron weigheth 72 <pb n="76" facs="tcp:108157:41"/> pounds, What will a Bullet of Lead weigh, that is equal to it in bigneſſe?</p>
                  <p>Set 2 on the firſt, to 3 on the ſecond, and then againſt
72, the weight known on the firſt, is 108, the weight ſought for on the ſecond.</p>
                  <p>But if the weight of the Leaden Bullet be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven 108, then to get the weight of the Iron Bullet, Set 3 on the firſt, to 2 on the ſecond, and then againſt 108 on the firſt, is 72 on the ſecond: So much is the weight of the Iron Bullet. What is ſaid of a Bullet, is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood alſo of all round bodies.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:108157:41"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the double Scales in the Meaſuration of Concave Cylinders, ſuch as great Ordnance.</head>
               <div n="1" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM I. The Diameter and weight of any one Cylinder, or Piece of great Ordnance being known, to find the weight of any other Piece of the ſame me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal and ſhape, either greater or leſſer, its Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter being onely known.</head>
                  <p>IF a Braſſe Saker, whoſe Diameter is 11,5 inches, do weigh 1900 pounds, What will another Piece weigh, whoſe Diameter is 8,75 inches? For anſwer:</p>
                  <p>Set 11,5 on the firſt, to 8,75 on the ſecond, and then againſt 1900 on the firſt, is 1440 on the ſecond; Secondly, againſt that 1440 on the firſt, is 1100 on the ſecond; Thirdly, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the 1100 on the firſt, is 837 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond: So much is the weight of that other Piece of Ordnance of 8,75 inches Diameter, it being of the ſame metal and ſhape as the other.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:108157:42"/>If a Piece of Ordnance of 4 inches Diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter weigh 1600 pounds, What will another Piece weigh that is 6 inches Diameter, being of the ſame metal and ſhape?</p>
                  <p>Set 4 on the firſt, to 6 on the ſecond, and then againſt
1600, the weight known, is 2400 on the ſecond; Next againſt 2400 on the firſt, is 3600 on the ſecond; And laſtly, againſt 3600 on the firſt, is 5400 on the ſecond: The weight ſought for of that other Piece of 6 in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Diameter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. II. Having the Diameter and weight of any Piece of great Ordnance, of one metal; to find, the weight of another Piece of Ordnance of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther metal, that retaineth the ſame ſhape.</head>
                  <p>A Piece of Ordnance being of another ſort of metal, there will be required a double work to find out its weight; As let there be a Braſſe Piece of Ordnance given, of 11,5 in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Diameter, weighing 1900 pounds; and let the queſtion be, to find the weight of an Iron Piece of Ordnance of the ſame ſhape, that is 8,75 inches Diameter.</p>
                  <p>In this and the like caſes, you muſt in the firſt place, by the former Problem, find the weight of that Piece of 8,75 inches Diameter,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:108157:42"/> as if it were a Braſſe Piece, and having found that the weight of it, had it been Braſſe, would have been 837 pounds: You muſt next ſeek the proportional numbers of the two metals, which by the ſeventh Problem of the laſt Chapter, you found was 16 and 18: Such is the proportion between Braſſe and Iron, Braſſe being the heavier metal. Therefore,</p>
                  <p>Set 18 on the firſt, to 16 on the ſecond, and then againſt 837 on the firſt, (the weight the Piece would have been of, had it been Braſſe) is 744 on the ſecond, the weight of that Piece it being Iron.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. III. To find the ſuperficial Content of the concave Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficies of any Piece of Ordnance, and alſo the ſolid Content of the Concavity thereof.</head>
                  <p>SVppoſe the Circumference of the Conca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity be 22 inches, and the length of it 12 foot, or 144 inches, &amp; the queſtion put, What is the ſuperficial Content of the concave Face, and what the ſolid Content of the concave Bore. For the concave Superficies.</p>
                  <p>Set 1 on the firſt, to 22, the Circumference of the Concavity on the ſecond, and then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt 144, the length in inches on the firſt, is 3168 on the ſecond: So many ſquare inches <pb n="80" facs="tcp:108157:43"/> are in the Superficies of the concave face of the ſame Piece, which in feet makes 22. For the ſolid Content.</p>
                  <p>Firſt get the Semidiameter, which in this example is 3,5 inches; and alſo the Semicir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference, which here is 11: Theſe being had,</p>
                  <p>Set 1 on the firſt, to 3,5 the Semidiameter on the ſecond, and then againſt 11, the Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumference on the firſt, is 38,5 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond: So many ſquare inches are contained in the Baſe or Plane of the Concavity of the mouth. This Baſe had:</p>
                  <p>Set 1 on the firſt, to 38,5 the Content of the Baſe on the ſecond; and then againſt 144, the length in inches, is 5544 on the ſecond: So many cubick inches are in the ſolid Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the Concavity of that Cylinder, which is 3 foot and 360 parts of 1728 of a foot.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM IV. To know how much of every kind of metal is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in any Braſſe Piece of Ordnance.</head>
                  <p>IT is ſaid to be an uſual thing with Gun-foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, that for every 100 pounds of Copper, to put in 10 pounds of Latten, &amp; 8 pounds of pure Tin. Now ſuppoſing this mixture to be true, let it be demanded, How much of every ſort of theſe metals is in a Gun of 5600 pounds weight?</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:108157:43"/>For anſwer to this &amp; the like queſtions; Firſt, joyn all the ſeveral mixtures together, that is 100,
10, &amp; 8, and this muſt be the firſt number in the rule of proportion; the weight of the Piece the ſecond number, which here is 5600; and the third number is each ſeveral ſort of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal in the mixture, which here be 100,
10, and 8: wherefore by our double lines, this <hi>quaere</hi> is very eaſily reſolved. For,</p>
                  <p>Set 118, the total of the common mixture on the firſt, to
5600, the weight of the Piece on the ſecond, and then againſt 100 on the firſt, is 4745,7 on the ſecond; againſt 10 on the firſt, is 474,6 on the ſecond, being one place leſſe than the former, becauſe 10 is one place leſſe than 100; ſo much Latten is in that Piece: and againſt 8 on the firſt, is 379,7 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, ſo much Tin is in the Gun.</p>
                  <p>Now if all theſe three ſums thus found be added together, they make the juſt weight of the Piece propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, as here it doth appear,
<table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>4745,7</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>474,6</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>379,7</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell role="total">5600,0</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the work truly wrought.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="problem">
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:108157:44"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM. V. By knowing what quantity of powder will load ſome one Piece of Ordnance, to find how much of the ſame powder will load any other Piece of Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, greater or leſſer.</head>
                  <p>IF a Saker of 3,75 inches Diameter in the Bore, require four pounds of powder for its load, What will a Demi-Cannon of 6,5 in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Diameter in the Bore require?</p>
                  <p>Set 3,75 on the firſt, to 6,5 on the ſecond, and then againſt 4, the weight known on the firſt, is 6,93 on the ſecond, and then againſt that 6,93 on the firſt, is 22 on the ſecond; and laſtly, againſt that 12 on the firſt, is 20,8 on the ſecond, very neer; that is,
20 pounds of powder, and 8 tenth parts of a pound: So much doth the Demi-Cannon require.</p>
                  <p>But note, that it is here underſtood, that the Demi-Cannon ought to be as well fortified as the Saker is, that is, it ſhould bear the ſame proportion to the Saker in weight and thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of metal, that the bore thereof beareth to the bore of the Saker, as in this example; The bore of the Saker is 3 inches and 3 quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, the Cube whereof is 52,73, and its weight is 1600 pounds; The bore of the Demi-Cannon is 6 inches and an half, the Cube <pb n="83" facs="tcp:108157:44"/> whereof is 274,62. Now the queſtion is, How much the weight of that Demi-Cannon ought to be, that is proportional in its weight and thickneſſe to the Saker, that ſo it may be able to bear a load of powder proportional to the Saker.</p>
                  <p>The weight of ſuch a Demi-Cannon is thus found; Set 52,37 the Cube of 3,75 on the firſt, to 274,62 the Cube of 6,5 on the ſecond, and then againſt the weight of the Saker 1600 on that firſt, is 8351 on the ſecond: The weight that the Demi-Cannon ought to be of, that is proportional in weight to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, and able to carry a load of powder pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portional to the Saker. Or you may work it thus without the Cubes.</p>
                  <p>Set 3,75 on the firſt, to 6,5 on the ſecond, and then, firſt againſt 1600 on the firſt, is 2766 on the ſecond; ſecondly, againſt this 2766 on the firſt, is 4800 on the ſecond; and thirdly, againſt that 4800 is 8351 on the ſecond, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: So the one work proveth the other.</p>
                  <p>But if the Demi-Cannon be found to want of its proportional weight with the Saker, as if it weigh but 6000 pounds, then to find its due load in powder, anſwerable to its ſtrength and weight of metal; Multiply the weight thereof 6000, by 20,8 the charge already calculated, &amp; divide the Product by 8351, the weight it <pb n="84" facs="tcp:108157:45"/> ought to have had, and the quotient is 14,8: Therefore 14 pounds, and 8 tenth parts of a pound, is a ſufficient charge for ſuch a Gun.</p>
                  <p>By our lines, Set 1 on the firſt, to 20,8 on the ſecond, and then againſt 6000, is 1248000, the Product. Now ſet 8351 the Diuiſor on the firſt, to 1 on the ſecond, &amp; then againſt 1248000 on the firſt, is 14,8 on the ſecond, the quotient ſought.</p>
                  <p>But ſuppoſe there be another ſort of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der brought to be uſed, that is ſtronger than the former, by ſuch proportion as 5 is to
2. How much of this ſort will ſerve to charge that Gun, which required 14,8 pounds of the other ſort. For anſwer of this <hi>quaere.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Set 5 on the firſt, to 2 on the ſecond, and then againſt
14,8 on the firſt, is 5,9 and a little above: Therefore 5 pounds of powder and 8 parts of 10 of a pound, of this new ſort of powder, will charge the Gun, having as much ſtrength to carry forth the Bullet, as 14 pounds and 8 tenths of the other.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="problem">
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:108157:45"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM. VI. Knowing how far any Piece of Ordnance will carry her Bullet at point-blank, and at the best of her Randon, to find how far any other Piece of Ordnance will carry her Bullet at her best Randon, her level-range being known.</head>
                  <p>A Saker at point-blank conveyes her Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let 200 paces, and at her beſt Randon 900 paces. Now how far will a Cannon carry her Bullet at her beſt Randon, that carrieth it at point-blank 360 paces.</p>
                  <p>Set 200 on the firſt, to 900 on the ſecond, and then againſt 360, the other Pieces point-blank on the firſt, is 1620 on the ſecond: The number of paces it will carry at point-blank.</p>
                  <p>If the beſt Randon and point-blank of the one Piece be given, with the beſt Randon of the other Piece, to find the point-blank theerof.</p>
                  <p>Set 900, the beſt Randon on the firſt, to 200 its point-blank on the ſecond, and then againſt 1620, the other Pieces beſt Randon on the firſt, is 360, its point-blank on the ſecond.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="problem">
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:108157:46"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM VII. By knowing how far any piece of Ordnance will carry a Bullet at the best of her Randon, to find how far ſhe will carry her Bullet at any other degree of Randon.</head>
                  <p>IF a Piece at her beſt Randon, which is 45 degrees of Mounture, carry her Bullet 1440 paces, How far will ſhe carry it at 30 degrees of Randon?</p>
                  <p>Set 45, the beſt Randon on the firſt, to 30, the other Randon on the ſecond; and then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt 1440, the paces of her carriage at her beſt Randon on the firſt, is 960, the paces of her carriage at 30 degrees of Randon; and if you take 960, from 1440, the remain is 480: So much doth ſhe ſhoot ſhort of her beſt Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</p>
                  <p>If a Gun carry a Bullet 700 yards at her beſt Randon, which as aforeſaid is at 45 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and the mark to ſhoot at be diſtant but
500 yards; To what degree muſt the Gun be mounted to make a good ſhoot?</p>
                  <p>Set 500 on the firſt, to 700 on the ſecond, and then againſt 45 on the firſt, is 63 on the ſecond; or bring 500 to 45, and then againſt 700 is 63, which is 63 degrees: Therefore the Piece muſt be raiſed to 63 degrees of <pb n="87" facs="tcp:108157:46"/> Mounture, to make a good ſhoot into the place.</p>
                  <p>Note, this queſtion is reſolved by the back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Rule of Three.</p>
                  <p>If a Gun at her beſt Randon ſhoots 500 yards, How much will ſhe ſhoot ſhort of it, being elevated two degrees above her beſt Randon?</p>
                  <p>Set 45, the degrees of beſt Randon on the firſt, to 2 the degrees ſhe is elevated above it on the ſecond, and then againſt 500, is
22,22: So many yards will ſhe ſhoot ſhort of her beſt Randon, being elevated 2 degrees above it.</p>
                  <p>How far is it to the place where a Bullet falleth, the Piece being mounted 15 degrees above her beſt Randon, ſhe abating 22,22 for 2 degrees elevation?</p>
                  <p>Set 2 on the firſt, to 22,22 on the ſecond, and then againſt 15 on the firſt, is 167 on the ſecond; therefore the Gun being raiſed 15 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees above her beſt Randon, abateth 167 yards of the 500, her carriage at her beſt Randon, wherefore 167 taken from 500, leaveth 333: So many yards is the place diſtant where the Bullet falleth.</p>
                  <p>If a Gun ſhoot point-blank 240 paces, and being mounted to one degree, doth out-ſhoot the point-blank 30 paces, What will ſhe out-ſhoot it at 20 degrees of Mounture?</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:108157:47"/>Set 1 on the firſt, to 30 on the ſecond, and then againſt 20 on the firſt, is 600 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond: So many paces will ſhe out-ſhoot her point-blank, being mounted 20 degrees, in the whole ſhot 840 paces.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM VIII. To find out how much wide of the mark any Piece of Ordnance will ſhoot, by knowing how far it is to the mark ſhot at, and how wide the Pieces mouth lieth from the right line to the mark.</head>
                  <p>A Gun of 10 foot, or 120 inches long, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſhoot at a mark 700 yards diſtant, her mouth lying one inch beſide the right line to the mark, How far will ſhe ſhoot her Bullet wide of the mark at that diſtance?</p>
                  <p>For anſwer: Firſt, bring 700 yards into in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and they make 25200, which is done by Multiplication thus.</p>
                  <p>Set 1 on the firſt, to 36 on the ſecond, for that is the number of inches in a yard, and then againſt 700, the diſtance on the firſt, is 25200, the inches in 700 yards. And then,</p>
                  <p>Set 120 on the firſt, the Guns length in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, to 1; and then againſt 25200, the diſtance in inches, is 210 inches, or 17 foot and an half: So far the Bullet goeth wide of the mark.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="problem">
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:108157:47"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM IX. Knowing the quantity of each ſort of Ingredients for the making of Gun powder, to find how much of every ſort is to be put into any uuantity of powder that ſhall be required to be made.</head>
                  <p>J Have read in ſome Authours, that for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the beſt ſort of ordinary Gun-pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, there is uſed to be taken 12 parts of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury, three parts of Cole, and two parts of Sulphur, in all 17 parts. Now a Gun-powder-maker is appointed to make 1000 pound weight of powder, How much muſt he take of each ſort of theſe Ingredients, to make that quantity of powder?</p>
                  <p>Set 17, the ſum of the parts on the firſt, to 1000, the quantity to be made, on the ſecond; and then without more ado, on the firſt, right againſt 12, is 706, and againſt 3 is 176,5; and laſtly, againſt 2 is 117,5 on the ſecond. Theſe three ſums being added together, make juſt 1000. Therefore you may conclude, that to make 1000 pounds of Gun-powder, he muſt take of Mercury 706 pounds, of Cole 176,5, and of Sulphur 117,5 pounds, the thing requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. This Problem is grounded upon the rule of Proportion thus: <pb n="90" facs="tcp:108157:48"/>
                     <list type="analogy">
                        <item> As 17, the whole parts taken,</item>
                        <item> Is to 1000, the quantity to be made:</item>
                        <item> So is each ſeveral part of the mixture,</item>
                        <item> To the quantity thereof to be taken to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the making of 1000 weight.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>I might have put down the Analogies of Proportion all along, as I did at the beginning; but I thought thoſe things would have filled my book too faſt, and every man that knowes the rule of Proportion, cannot but ſee how every Problem is reſolved thereby.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:108157:48"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the double Scales in For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>THe ſide of a Pentagonal Fort being propounded, with the perpendicular and all the other lines, with the Area: To find the ſides and all other lines and Content of any other Pentagonal Fort, that ſhall be required to be made, either grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or leſſer, according to any proportion aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned.</p>
                  <p>Suppoſe there be a Pentagonal Fort made, ſuch an one as is repreſented by this Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gram annexed, noted by the letters A B S T X K O G F E D N M L H P and C, whoſe ſides AB, BS, SX, XR, and KA, are each 662 yards. And let it be required, to make another Fort that ſhall be a juſt fourth part in Content of ground of that propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Fort. Now the Content of the propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Pentagonal Poligon, deſcribed by the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ABSXK, is
754680 yards, and the ſides and lines of the Fort thereon made are as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item> The ſide of the Pentagon AB, is 662 yards.</item>
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:108157:49"/>
                     <item> The Perpendicular CI, 456 yards.</item>
                     <item> The Semidiameter of the Pentagon CA, 564 yards.</item>
                     <item> The Gorge-lines of the Fort AD, AO, NB, BP, each one of then 119 yards.</item>
                     <item> The Flanks of the Bulwark DE, and OG, 100 yards.</item>
                     <item> The Curtain DN, 424 yards.</item>
                     <item> The Fronts lines FE, FG, and LM, LH, 264 yards.</item>
                     <item> The Head-lines, or Capital AF, or BL, 224 yards.</item>
                     <item> The Breadth of the Bulwark from G to E, or M to H, 330 yards.</item>
                     <item> The Lines of Defence DL, and NE, 700 yards.</item>
                     <item> The diſtance between the points of the Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark F and L, is 926 yards.</item>
                     <item> The Line perpendicular to the Line FL, <hi>viz.</hi> CR, 637 yards.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>By theſe Lines and lengths known, it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to make another Pentagonal Fort, whoſe quantity or Content in land ſhall be the juſt fourth part of the propoſed Pentago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Fort propounded: where note, that the half of the ſides and lines of the Fort made will make another Fort, that will contain the fourth part of the ground in that Fort made: And that you may readily have half of all the lines of the Fort made, do thus:</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:108157:49"/>Set 2 on the firſt, to 1 on the ſecond, and then againſt the number of any line on the firſt, is its half on the ſecond: As againſt 662, the length of the ſide of the Pentagon given, is 331, the length of the Pentagons ſide to be made. The Lines thus remaining without any moving, againſt 119 on the firſt, the length of the Gorge-line in the made Fort, is 59,5, the length of the Gorge-line in that Fort to be made: And againſt 424, the length of the Curtain in the made Fort, is
212 on the ſecond, the length of the Curtain in that Fort to be made: And againſt 456, the length of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Poligons perpendicular which is made, is 228, the length of the perpendicular in that Poligon which is to be made: And againſt the Semidiameter 564, is 282: And againſt 100, the length of the preſent Bulwarks flank, is 50, the length of the Flank in the Bulwark to be made. And againſt 224, the length of the Bulwarks head-line, is 112, the length of the head-line in the Fort to be made: And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>againſt 310, the diſtance of the ſhoulders GE, or MH in the Fort made, is 155, for the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the ſhoulders in that Fort which is to made: And in like manner, againſt the length of any Line in the propoſed Fort is the length of that ſame Line in the Fort to be made.</p>
                  <p>Thus very ſpeedily is found out the true <pb n="94" facs="tcp:108157:50"/> length of all the Lines in and belonging to ſuch a Fort as is required to be made, whoſe lines and ſides ſhall be juſt half the length of thoſe in the Fort already made: And being drawn on the ground, and made up, will in all parts be like &amp; proportional to the ſame propoſed Fort. The like manner of working is to be uſed for any other proportion whatſoever, either grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or leſſer.</p>
                  <p>Suppoſe it were required to make a Penta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonal Fort, whoſe ſides, and ſo all the lines thereof, ſhould be the one third part in length of the ſides and lines in that propoſed Fort, which in the annexed Diagram is repreſented by the letters CABSTXKOGFEDNMLPH. To which demand, to give a ready anſwer, do thus:</p>
                  <p>Becauſe one third part is ſought for, Set 3 on the firſt, to 1 on the ſecond, and then againſt 662 on the firſt, the ſide of the Pentagon gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, it 220⅔ on the ſecond, which is one third part of 662, &amp; ſheweth that the length of the ſide of the Pentagon to be made is 220⅔ yards; and againſt 119, the length of the Gorge-lines in the propoſed Fort, is 39⅔, that is 39 yards 2 foot, which is the third part of 119, and is the juſt length of the Gorge-lines in the Fort to be made. In like manner, againſt any Line or diſtance in th propoſed Fort, is the length <pb n="95" facs="tcp:108157:50"/> of the ſame Line in that Fort to be made. For to be ſhort, Take any number on the firſt, and right againſt it on the ſecond, is the one third part thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>How to make a Fort greater than the Fort propoſed.</head>
                  <p>SVppoſe there be a Fort made, ſuch an one as is that repreſented in the afore-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Diagram, and another Fort is to be made like to it; ſo that in all the lines and ſides there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, it be double to thoſe in the Fort that is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready made.</p>
                  <p>In this caſe and the like, we have no more to do, but to ſet 1 on the firſt, to 2 on the ſecond, and then againſt the number of the length of any ſide or line on the firſt, is the double of it on the ſecond. As if you ſet 1 on the firſt, to 2 on the ſecond, then againſt 456 on the firſt, the length of the perpendicular in the Pentagonal Fort given, you ſhall have 912 on the ſecond, the double of 465, which is the length of the perpendicular in that Fort to be made; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt 662, the length of the Curtain in the Fort made, is 1322, the length of the Curtain in the Fort to be made: And ſo of all the reſt of the Lines.</p>
                  <p>If it ſhall be required to make ſuch a Fort, as in its ſides and lines ſhall be one third part longer than thoſe in the propoſed Fort: Then <pb n="96" facs="tcp:108157:51"/> take any one line, as for example, CI 456 yards, and thereof take the one third part, which is 152: This add to the ſame 456, and it makes 608. This done, Set 456 on the firſt, to 608 on the ſecond, and then againſt any line of the Fort made on the firſt, is its match-line in the Fort to be made: As againſt DN, the Curtain in the made Fort, 424 yards, is 565<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: So many yards will the Curtain be in that Fort to be made, and ſo of all other lines. And if a Fort be to be made, whoſe ſides and lines muſt be half ſo much more in length, as are the ſides and lines of the propoſed Fort: Then take the half of any number, and add it to the ſame number, and ſo proceed as before.</p>
                  <p>Note, that the lines in the Type or Diagram annexed, may be accounted in their lengths there ſet down, either ſo many foot, or ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yards, or ſo many perches, or what other meaſure you are to uſe: And ſo the ſide of the Pentagon 662, may be accounted 662 yards, or 662 foot, or 662 perches. Thus by ſuppoſing a Pentagonal Fort to have lines and ſides in length, as thoſe in the Diagram, you may by theſe double lines very eaſily diſcover all the lines and ſides of any other Pentagonal Fort, either greater or leſſer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="diagram">
                  <pb facs="tcp:108157:51"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:108157:52"/>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:108157:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>geometrical diagram of a pentagonal fort</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:108157:53"/>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:108157:53"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the double Scale of Sines in Aſtronomy.</head>
               <div n="1" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. I. The Suns greatest declination, with his place or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from the next Equinoctial point being gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to find his preſent declination for the time given.</head>
                  <p>THe Suns greateſt declination in this our age, is found to be 23 degrees 30 minutes. This is general, his place given on the day propoſed, is 0 degr. of <hi>Taurus,</hi> which point is diſtant from the next Equinoctial point af <hi>Aries</hi> 30 degrees.</p>
                  <p>The Analogie for Solution of this Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is thus:
<list type="analogy">
                        <item>As the Radius, or Sine of 90 degrees,</item>
                        <item>Is to the Suns greateſt declination 23 deg. 30 min.</item>
                        <item> So is the diſtance of the Sun 30 deg. from the next Equinoctial point which is <hi>Aries,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>To the Sine of the declination 11 degr. 30 min. ſought for.</item>
                     </list> Wherefore,</p>
                  <p>Set 90 degres on the firſt, to the Suns grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt declination 23 deg. 30 min. on the ſecond, <pb n="98" facs="tcp:108157:54"/> and then againſt 30 deg. the Suns diſtance from the next Equinoctial point on the firſt, is 11 deg. 30 min. on the ſecond: So much is his declination ſought for, his place being the very beginning of <hi>Taurus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Suppoſe the Sun be in the beginning of <hi>Leo,</hi> which is 60 degrees diſtant from the Equino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctial point of <hi>Libra;</hi> then ſet 90 deg. on the firſt, to 23 deg. 30 min. on the ſecond, and then againſt 60 deg. on the firſt, is 20 deg. 10 min. on the ſecond: The declination of the Sun, when he is entering into <hi>Leo.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. II. The Suns greatest declination, and his preſent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination for any time propoſed being had, to find his diſtance from the next Equinoctial point, and thereby his place in the Ecliptick.</head>
                  <p>SEt the Suns greateſt declination, 23 deg. 30 min. on the firſt, to 90 degrees on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond; and then againſt his preſent declination, being given 11 deg. 30 min. on the firſt, is 30 degrees on the ſecond: So much is his diſtance from the next Equinoctial point, which is
<hi>Aries;</hi> therefore his true place is juſt leaving <hi>Aries,</hi> and entering <hi>Taurus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again, ſuppoſe the Suns preſent declination be given 20 deg. 10 min. and his place ſought: <pb n="99" facs="tcp:108157:54"/> Set 23 deg. 30 min. on the firſt, to 90 deg. on the ſecond, and then againſt 20 deg. 10 min. on the firſt, is 60 degrees on the ſecond: So much is the Suns diſtance from the next Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctial point.</p>
                  <p>Now if the Sun be in the firſt quarter of the Ecliptick, between <hi>Aries</hi> and <hi>Cancer,</hi> then he is diſtant from the Equinoctial of <hi>Aries</hi> 60 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>degrees, and therefore in the beginning of
<hi>Gemini:</hi> But if he be in the ſecond quarter of the Ecliptick, as in this propoſal he is, his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance is to be accounted from the Equinoctial of <hi>Libra,</hi> and then his place muſt be in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of
<hi>Leo;</hi> If he be in the third quarter of the Ecliptick, and 60 degrees from the next Equinoctial point, then he is in the beginning of
<hi>Sagittarius:</hi> And if he be in the fourth quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Ecliptick, and diſtant 60 degrees from the next Equinoctial point, then he muſt be in the beginning of <hi>Aquarius.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. III. The Suns declination, and the Latitude of the place being given, to find the Suns Amplitude.</head>
                  <p>LEt be given the Suns declination, 11 deg. 30 min. and the Latitude of the place pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed 51 degrees 30 minutes, whoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement to
90 degrees, is 38 degrees, 30 mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes: <pb n="100" facs="tcp:108157:55"/> And the Amplitude ſought for.</p>
                  <p>Set the Co-ſine of the Latitude 38 deg. 30 min. on the firſt, to the Radius, or 90 degrees on the ſecond, and then againſt the ſine of the Suns declination, 11 deg. 30 min. on the firſt, is 18 deg. 40 min. on the ſecond: So much is the Suns Amplitude, at ſuch time as his decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is 11 deg. 30 minutes. Or,</p>
                  <p>Suppoſe the Suns, or a Stars declination were known to be 20 degrees, then without altering the lines from the place they were firſt ſet to, right againſt 20 deg. on the firſt, is 33 deg. 10 min. on the ſecond, the Amplitude ſought: And ſo againſt any other declination on the firſt, is the Amplitude on the ſecond.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. IV. The Latitude of the place, the Suns greateſt decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation with his diſtance from the next Equino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctial point being had, to find his Amplitude.</head>
                  <p>THe Latitude is 51 deg. 30 min. whoſe Complement is 38 deg.
30 min. the Suns diſtance from the next Equinoctial point is 18 deg. 40 min. and his greateſt declination 23 deg. 30 min. and the Amplitude required.</p>
                  <p>Set the Co-ſine of the Latitude, 38 deg. 30 min. on the firſt, to 23 deg. 30 min. on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, the ſine of the greateſt declination, and <pb n="101" facs="tcp:108157:55"/> then againſt 30 degrees, the diſtance from the neereſt Equinoctial point on the firſt, is 18 deg. 40 min. on the ſecond: So much is the Suns Amplitude, when his place is in the beginnings of <hi>Taurus, Virgo, Scorpio,</hi> or <hi>Piſces.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. V. The Latitude of the place, the Suns place or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from the next Equinoctial point, with his greateſt declination being known; to find what altitude the Sun will have, when he is on the true Eaſt or Weſt point.</head>
                  <p>LEt the Latitude be 51 deg. 30 min. the Suns place in 10 degrees of <hi>Taurus,</hi> which is diſtant from the next Equinoctial point
40 degrees, and the greateſt declination 23 deg. 30 min. What is the Suns altitude at the true Eaſt or Weſt point?</p>
                  <p>Set 51 deg. 30 min. on the firſt, (the Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the place) to 23 deg. 30 min. the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt declination on the ſecond; and then againſt 40 degrees, the diſtance from the neereſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctial point on the firſt, is 19 degr. 5 min. on the ſecond: So much is the Suns alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, when he is on the true Eaſt or Weſt point: And at his entrance into
<hi>Taurus,</hi> his al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude at that point is 14 degrees 45 minutes. As this, ſo his altitude for any other place is <pb n="102" facs="tcp:108157:56"/> found, without ſtirring the lines, after once ſet together.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. VI. The Latitude of the place, and Suns declination being had; to find what altitude the Sun will be of, when he cometh upon the true Eaſt or Weſt point.</head>
                  <p>LEt the Latitude be 51 deg. 30 min. and the Suns declination
11 deg. 30 min. and his height at his being on the due Eaſt or Weſt point required.</p>
                  <p>Set the ſine of the Latitude, 51 deg. 30 min. on the firſt, to the Radius on the ſecond, and then againſt the ſine of the given declination, 11 deg. 30 min. on that firſt, is 14 degr. 45 min. on the ſecond: So much is the Suns alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude at the time of his being due Eaſt or Weſt, when his declination is 11 deg. 30 min.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM VII. Having the Suns greateſt declination, and his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from the next Equinoctial point; to find his right aſcenſion.</head>
                  <p>THe Suns greateſt declination is 23 degr. 30 min. and his place given is 0 degr. of <hi>Taurus.</hi> Therefore his diſtance from the neereſt <pb n="10" facs="tcp:108157:56"/> Equinoctial point <hi>Aries</hi> is 30 degrees: By theſe known, his right aſcenſion is deſired.</p>
                  <p>Set 90 deg. on the firſt, to the Co-ſine of the greateſt declination, 66 deg. 30 min. on the ſecond; and then on the back-ſide, (being the lines of Tangents) againſt the Tangent of 30 degrees, the Suns diſtance from the neereſt Equinoctial point, on that firſt, is the Tangent 27 degr. 50 min. So much is the Suns right aſcenſion, at that time.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM VIII. The Suns greateſt declination, and his preſent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, being given for a time; to find his right aſcenſion for that time.</head>
                  <p>THe Suns greateſt declination is 23 degr. 30 min. and his preſent declination for a time propoſed, is 11 deg. 30 min. I demand his right aſcenſion thereby.</p>
                  <p>Set the Tangent of 23 deg. 30 min. on the firſt, to the Tangent of the preſent declination, 11 deg. 30 min. on the ſecond; and then up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the other ſide, on the lines of ſines, againſt the Radius on the firſt, is the ſine of 27 deg. 50 min. on the ſecond: So much is the Suns right aſcenſion demanded.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="problem">
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:108157:57"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM. IX. The Latitude of the place, and the Suns declination known; to find how long the Sun riſeth and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, before or after the hour of ſix.</head>
                  <p>THe Latitude of the place is 51 degr. 30 min. North, and the Suns declination, 11 deg. 30 min. I demand the time of Sun-riſing before ſix.</p>
                  <p>Set the Co-tangent of the Latitude, 38 deg. 30 min. on the firſt, to the Tangent of 11 deg. 30 min. the declination given on the ſecond; &amp; then on the other ſide, againſt the Radius on the firſt, is the ſine 14 deg. 50 min. This 14 deg. 50 min. converted into time, by account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing four minutes of an hour to every degree, and one minute of an hour for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> minutes of a degree, and it will amount to 59 minutes of an hour: So long the Sun riſeth before ſix in the morning, and ſets after ſix at night in the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſeaſon; and in the Winter ſeaſon, or Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern ſignes, he riſeth ſo long after ſix in the morning, and ſets ſo long before ſix at night, where the Latitude is 51 deg. 30 min. and when the Suns declination is 11 deg. 30 min. South.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="problem">
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:108157:57"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM. X. The Sun being in the Equinoctial, by knowing his diſtance from the Meridian, and the latitude of the place; to find the Suns altitude at that time.</head>
                  <p>MArch the tenth, the Sun being in the Equinoctial at ten a clock before noon, or at two a clock after noon, he being at that hour diſtant from the Meridian 30 degrees, I would know his height in our Latitude of 51 deg. 30 minutes.</p>
                  <p>Set the Radius on the firſt, to the Co-ſine of the Latitude, 38 deg. 30 min. on the ſecond, and then againſt the Co-ſine of the Suns di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from the Meridian, <hi>viz.</hi> againſt 60 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees on the firſt, is 32 deg. 37 min. on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond: So much is the Suns altitude on the tenth of March, at ten a clock in the fore-noon, and at two a clock after noon.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM XI. The latitude of the place, and the Suns declination Northwards being known; to find the Suns al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, at the hour of ſix.</head>
                  <p>LEt the Latitude of the place be 51 deg. 30 min. the Suns declination 11 deg. 50 min. <pb n="106" facs="tcp:108157:58"/> North: And the Suns height at ſix a clock is deſired.</p>
                  <p>Set the Radius on the firſt, to the ſine of the declination, 11 deg. 50 min. on the ſecond; and then againſt 51 deg. 30 min. the Latitude on the firſt, is 8 deg. 58 min. on the ſecond: So much is the Suns height at the hours of ſix, at morning and night. Or elſe thus:</p>
                  <p>Set the Radius to 51 deg. 30 min. and then againſt 11 deg.
50 min. on the firſt, is 8 deg. 58 min. on the ſecond: For note, that the Radius on the firſt may be ſet to either of the other two terms given on the ſecond, and then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the other term on the firſt, is the anſwer on the ſecond.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. XII. The Latitude and declination of the Sun being known; to find the Suns Azimuth at the hour of ſix, from the North part of the Meridian.</head>
                  <p>IN the Latitude of 51 deg. 30 min. the Suns declination given is 11 deg. 30 min. What is his Azimuth at the hour of ſix?</p>
                  <p>Set the Radius on the firſt, to the Co-ſine of the Latitude, 38 degr. 30 min. on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond; and then againſt the Co-tangent of the declination, 11 deg. 30 min. on the firſt, is the Tangent 82 deg. 47 min. on the ſecond: So <pb n="107" facs="tcp:108157:58"/> much is the Suns Azimuth from the North to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Eaſt, which was required.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM XIII. The Latitude of the place, and the Suns altitude at the point of his being due East or West; to find the hour and minute when he will be ſo due East or West.</head>
                  <p>THe Latitude of the place is 51 deg. 30 min. The Suns height found at his being on the true Eaſt point, is 14 deg. 45 min. I demand the hour of the day.</p>
                  <p>Set the Radius on the firſt, to the Co-ſine of the Latitude, 38 deg. 30 min. on the ſecond; and then on the Lines of Tangents, right againſt the Tangent of the Suns altitude, at his being due Eaſt,
<hi>viz.</hi> 14 deg. 45 min. on that firſt, is 9 deg, 18 min. on the ſecond, the Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent of time from the hour of ſix, either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore or after, that the Sun will be due Eaſt, or due Weſt. This 9 degr. 18 minutes redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced into time, by allowing to every degree four minutes of time, and for fifteen minutes of a degree, one minute of time, amounteth to 37 minutes of time: So then the Sun is due Eaſt on the day given, at 37 minutes after ſix a clock in the morning; and alſo will be <pb n="108" facs="tcp:108157:59"/> due Weſt at
37 minutes before ſix at night, which is at five a clock 23 minutes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM XIV. The elevation of the Pole, the Suns (or a Stars) declination, and diſtance from the Meridian for any time being given; to find the Suns al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude at that time.</head>
                  <p>LEt the elevation of the Pole be 51 deg. 30 min. whoſe Complement to 90, is 38 deg. 30 min. The Suns declination 11 deg. 30 mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes, whoſe Complement is 78 deg. 30 min. his diſtance from the Pole; his diſtance from the Meridian 30 degrees, or which is all one, two hours, that is, either at ten or two a clock, and the Complement of this diſtance to 90 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, is 60 degrees: And let the Suns Alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude for that time be required.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Set the Radius on the firſt, to 60 deg. the Co-ſine of the Suns diſtance from Noon on the ſecond; and then on the lines of Tangents againſt 38 deg. 30 minutes, the Co-tangent of the elevation on the firſt, is the Tangent 34 degr. 33 min. on the ſecond; for the fourth term, which taken from the Suns diſtance from the Pole, the Remainder is 43 degrees, 56 minutes.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="109" facs="tcp:108157:59"/>2 Set the Co-ſine of that 34 deg.
33 min. the fourth term, <hi>viz.</hi> 55 deg. 27 min. on the firſt, to 46 deg. 4 min. the Co-ſine of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder, on the ſecond: and then againſt the ſine of the Elevation, 51 deg. 30 min. on the firſt, is the ſine 43 deg. 18 min. on the ſecond: So much is the altitude of the Sun at that time, the thing required.</p>
                  <p>This is when the Sun hath Northern decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, but when he hath Southern declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then add his declination to 90 deg. and it makes
101 deg. 30 min. the Suns diſtance from the Pole, from which take the fourth term found, and the Remain is 66 deg. 27 min. This done, the ſecond work would be thus:</p>
                  <p>Set the Co-ſine of the fourth term found on the firſt,
<hi>viz.</hi> 55 deg. 27 min. to the Co-ſine of that Remain, which is 23 deg.
33 min. on the ſecond; and then againſt 51 deg. 50 min. the Elevation on the firſt, is 21 deg. 52 min. on the ſecond. The Suns height at ten or two a clock, when he hath 11 deg. 30 minutes of South declination.</p>
                  <p>If the Sun be juſt in the Equinoctial, having no declination; then to find his height on that day at ten or two a clock, the work will be done at one working in this manner.</p>
                  <p>Set the Radius on the firſt, to 60 degrees, the Co-ſine of the diſtance from the Meridian, <pb n="110" facs="tcp:108157:60"/> on the ſecond; and then againſt 38 degr. 50 min. the Co-ſine of the Elevation on the firſt, is the ſine 32 deg. 62 min. So much is the Suns altitude at the hours of ten and two a clock on the Equinoctial day.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM XV. Having the Poles elevation, and the Suns declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; to find the aſcenſional difference.</head>
                  <p>LEt the Poles elevation be 51 deg. 30 min. and the Suns declination 11 deg. 30 min. And by them the aſcenſional difference requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be given.</p>
                  <p>Set 38 deg. 30 min. the Co-tangent of the elevation on the firſt, to the Tangent of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination 11 deg. 30 min. on the ſecond; and then (on the Lines of Sines) againſt the Radius on that firſt, is the ſine of 14 deg. 49 min. on the ſecond: So much is the aſcenſional diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence required at that time, as the Sun hath 11 deg. 30 min. declination.</p>
                  <p>I could ſhew by this aſcenſional difference converted into time, How to find the time of Sun-riſing and ſetting, with the length of day and night, &amp;c. But theſe are things done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Lines, and therefore I paſſe them by, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving limited my ſelf to ſhew onely the uſe of the double Lines.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="problem">
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:108157:60"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM XVI. Having any Planets declination and Latitude, with its diſtance from the next Equinoctial point; to find its right aſcenſion.</head>
                  <p>LEt a Planets declination be 26 degrees, its Latitude 4 degrees, and its diſtance from the neereſt Equinoctial point 70 degrees, (it being in the 10 deg. of <hi>Gemini</hi>) I demand the right aſcenſion thereof, which to attain:</p>
                  <p>Set 64 deg. the Co-ſine of the declination, to 20 deg. the Co-ſine of the Planets diſtance from the next Equinoctial point; and then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt 86 deg. on the firſt, the Co-ſine of the Planets latitude, is 22 deg. 17 min. on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, the Co-ſine of the right aſcenſion: Therefore 67 deg 43 min. (being the Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of 22 deg. 17 min.) is the right aſcenſion of that Planet which was demanded.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM XVII. The Suns greateſt declination, with his diſtance from the next Equinoctial point, being had; to find the Meridian angle, that is, the interſection of the Meridian with the Ecliptick.</head>
                  <p>LEt the Suns greateſt declination be 23 degr. 30 min. and his place juſt entering <hi>Taurus,</hi> 
                     <pb n="112" facs="tcp:108157:61"/> which is diſtant from the neereſt Equinoctial point 30 degrees, I would know the Meridian angle.</p>
                  <p>Set the Radius on the firſt, to 60 degrees, the Co-ſine of the Suns diſtance from the neereſt Equinoctial point on the ſecond; and then on the lines of Tangents, againſt 23 deg. 30 min. the Tangent of the Suns greateſt declination on the firſt is 20 deg. 38 min. on the ſecond, which is the Co-tangent of the angle ſought: Wherefore the Meridian angle is
69 degr. 22 min. being the Complement of 20 degr. 38 min. to 90 degrees.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. XVIII. The Suns declination and amplitude given; to find the heigth of the Pole.</head>
                  <p>LEt the Suns declination given be 14 degr. 51 min. and his amplitude 19 degr. 7 min. And the Poles elevation demanded.</p>
                  <p>Set 19 deg. 7 min. the amplitude on the firſt, to 14 deg. 51 min. the declination on the ſecond; and then againſt the Radius on the firſt, is 51 deg. 30 min. on the ſecond, which is the ſine of the latitude: Wherefore 51 degr. 30 min. is the Latitude ſought.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="problem">
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:108157:61"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM. XIX. The amplitude of the Sun, and time of his riſing being known; to find thereby his declination.</head>
                  <p>LEt the Suns amplitude be 33 degr. 38 min. and the time of his riſing be at 4 a clock 10 minutes; by which two things known, I would find the declination of the Sun. Here firſt convert the 4 hours 10 minutes into de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees and minutes, and they make 62 degr. 30 minutes.</p>
                  <p>Now ſet this 62 degr. 30 min. the time of Sun-riſing converted into degrees on the firſt, to 56 deg. 22 min. the Co-ſine of the ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude on the ſecond; and then againſt the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius on the firſt, is
69 degr. 50 min. on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, the Co-ſine of the declination: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it followeth, that 20 deg. 10 min. is the decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation deſired.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. XX. Having the elevation of the Pole, and the Suns amplitude; to find his declination.</head>
                  <p>LEt the Elevation of the Pole be 51 degr. 30 min. and the Suns amplitude 19 deg. 7 min. By which two things given, the declination is required.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="114" facs="tcp:108157:62"/>Set the Radius on the firſt, to 19 deg.
7 min. the Suns amplitude on the ſecond, and then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt 51 deg. 30 min. the ſine of the elevation on the firſt, is 14 deg. 51 min. the ſine of the declination upon the ſecond: The thing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. XXI. Having the hour of the day, the Suns nltitude and declination; to find the Azimuth.</head>
                  <p>LEt the Suns altitude be 25 degr. 56 min. whoſe Complement is 64 deg. 4 min. his declination 11 deg. 30 min. whereof the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement is 78 degr. 30 min. The hour of the day, 7 hours 56 minutes fore noon, which time is diſtant from noon 4 hours 4 minutes. This time converted into degrees, giveth
61 degrees. Now by theſe things known, the Azimuth is deſired to be found.</p>
                  <p>Set 64 degrees 4 minutes, the Co-ſine of the Suns altitude on the firſt, to 61 degrees, the Suns diſtance from the Meridian on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond; and then againſt 78 degrees 30 minutes, the Co-ſine of the declination on the firſt, is 72 degrees 22 minutes on the ſecond: So much is the Suns Azimuth from the South Eaſtwards.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="problem">
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:108157:62"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM XXII. The Suns declination, altitude, and azimuth being known; to find the hour of the day.</head>
                  <p>SVppoſe the Suns declination be 11 degr. 30 min. his altitude 25 deg. 56 min. and the Azimuth 72 deg. 22 min. Hereby to find the hour of the day.</p>
                  <p>Set 78 deg. 30 min. on the firſt, (which is the Complement of the declination) to 64 deg. 4 min. on the ſecond, which is the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement of the Altitude; and then againſt 72 deg. 22 min. the Azimuth on the firſt, is 61 grees on the ſecond. This 61 degrees conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into time, giveth 4 hours 4 minutes, which taken from 12 hours, the Remain is 7 hours 56 minutes before noon, the time of the day required.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM XXIII. The altitude of the Equator, and the Suns, or a Stars declination being given; to find the angle of the Meridian with the Horizon.</head>
                  <p>LEt the altitude of the Equator be 51 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees 30 minutes, and the declination 22 degrees. And the angle of the Meridian with the Horizon ſought for.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="116" facs="tcp:108157:63"/>Set 68 degrees, the Co-ſine of the declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on the firſt, to the Radius on the ſecond; and then againſt
51 deg. 30 min. the Co-ſine of the Equators altitude, on the firſt, is 57 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees 34 minutes on the ſecond: So much is the angle of the Meridian (or circle of Decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation) with the Horizon.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:108157:63" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX. The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the double Scales in Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphy.</head>
               <div n="1" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM I. Two places lying without the Equinoctial, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving both one Latitude, differing onely in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude, being propounded; to find their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</head>
                  <p>SVppoſe there be two places, lying both in the Latitude of
48 deg. 20 min. differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely in Longitude 16 degrees, as do <hi>Paris</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Vienna</hi> in <hi>Auſtria,</hi> whoſe diſtance is deſired.</p>
                  <p>Set the Radius on the firſt, to 41 degrees 40 minutes, the Co-ſine of the Latitude on the ſecond; and then againſt 16 degrees on the firſt, the difference of Longitude, is 10 degrees 36 minutes, which in miles makes 636: So much is the diſtance between the two places.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="problem">
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:108157:64"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM. II. Two places being propounded, which differ in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude, the one lying under the Equinoctial, and the other having Latitude, to find their diſtance in miles.</head>
                  <p>LEt two places be propounded, the one lying under the Equinoctial, having 313 degrees of Longitude, and the other lying in the Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of 32 deg. 42 min. and in the Longitude of 323 degrees, they differing in Longitude 10 degrees, I would know their diſtance.</p>
                  <p>Set the Radius on the firſt, to 80 degrees on the ſecond, the Co-ſine of the difference of Longitude; and then againſt 57 deg. 18 min. the Co-ſine of the one places Latitude on the firſt, is 55 deg. 58 min. the Co-ſine of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in degrees; the Complement of this 55 deg. 58 min. to 90, is 34 deg. 2 min. which converted into Engliſh miles, giveth 2042 miles: So much is the diſtance between the two places.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="problem">
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:108157:64"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM. III. Two places having ſeveral Latitudes towards one Pole, and differing in Longitude; to find their diſtance.</head>
                  <p>LEt <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> be two places pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, betwixt which the diſtance is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired: The Latitude of
<hi>London</hi> is 51 degrees 30 minutes, the Latitude of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is 32 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees; and their difference in Longitude is 47 degrees. Now to find their diſtance.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Set the Radius on the firſt, to 43 degrees, the Co-ſine of the difference of Longitude on the ſecond; and then on the lines of Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents, againſt the Co-tangent of the greater Latitude, 38 deg. 30 min. is 28 deg. 28 min. on the ſecond; the fourth term. This fourth term, 28 deg.
28 min. taken out of the Complement of the leſſer Latitude, that is here, out of 58 deg. the Remain is 29 deg. 32 min. Then,</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Set 28 deg. 28 min. the fourth term found, to that Remain, 29 deg. 32 min. on the ſecond; and then againſt the Co-ſine of the greater La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, <hi>viz.</hi> 38 deg. 30 min is the ſigne 39 deg. 14 min. the diſtance ſought for in degrees of a great Circle, which converted into miles, makes 2354 miles, the diſtance between <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> and
<hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="problem">
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:108157:65"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM IV. Two places, one having North Latitude, and the other South Latitude, and differing in Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude; to find their diſtance.</head>
                  <p>SVppoſe the one place be in 50 degrees of North Latitude, and the other in 32 degr. 25 min. of South Latitude, and their difference in their Longitude 70 degrees, and betwixt theſe two ſuch places, the diſtance is deſired. To reſolve this demand:</p>
                  <p n="1">1 Set the Radius on the firſt, to 20 degrees, the Co-ſine of the difference of Longitude on the ſecond; and then againſt 50 degrees, the Tangent of the greater Latitude, is the Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent 16 degrees 1 minute, a fourth term. This fourth term, 16 degrees 1 minute, take from 57 degrees 35 minutes, the Complement of the leſſer Latitude, and the Remain is 41 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees 34 minutes, for a fifth term. Now then:</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Set 73 degrees 59 minutes, the Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of 16 degrees 1 minute, the fourth term, to 48 degrees 26 minutes, the Complement of that 41 degrees 34 minutes, the fifth term; and then againſt the ſine, the greater Latitude 50 degrees on the firſt, is the ſine 36 degrees 36 minutes, whoſe Co-ſine 53 degrees 24 mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes <pb n="121" facs="tcp:108157:65"/> is the diſtance in degrees by a great Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle. This 53 degr. 24 min. being turned into miles, by multiplying by 60, maketh 3204 miles, and in leagues 1068: So much is the diſtance ſought for between the two places.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:108157:66"/>
               <head>CHAP. X. Of plain right lined Triangles.</head>
               <div n="1" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. I. In a plain right lined Triangle, right angled, the three angles being known, and one ſide; to find either of the other ſides.</head>
                  <p>IN the Triangle annexed ABD, let the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle at A be a right angle, or 90 degrees, the angle at D 43 deg. 20 min, and the angle at B 46 deg.
40 min, and the ſide AB 230 yards; and let the ſide AD be the ſide ſought.</p>
                  <p>The Reſolution of this Problem upon the Inſtrument is by this Analogie:
<list type="analogy">
                        <item> As the Sine of the Angle oppoſite to the ſide known,</item>
                        <item> Is to the Sine of the Angle oppoſite to the ſide required:</item>
                        <item> So is the ſide known,</item>
                        <item>to the ſide ſought.</item>
                     </list> And therefore in this Example it is,</p>
                  <p>As the ſine 43 deg. 20 min. the angle at D oppoſite to AB the ſide known, is to the ſine of the angle at B, 46 deg. 40 min. which is the angle oppoſite to the ſide ſought AD: So is <pb n="123" facs="tcp:108157:66"/> the length of the known ſide AB 230 yards, to 243 yards and very neer three quarters of a yard, the length of the ſide AD, which was required. Wherefore,</p>
                  <p>Vpon the lines of ſines, Set the ſine 43 deg. 20 min. on the firſt, (the angle at D. oppoſite to the ſide given.) To the ſine 46 deg. 40 min. on the ſecond, (which is the ſine of the angle oppoſite to the ſide required.) And then upon the lines of Numbers, againſt 230, the length in yards of the known ſide on that firſt, is 243 and three quarters very neer: So then the length of the ſide AD, which is ſought, is 243 yards, and very neer three quarters.</p>
                  <p>For further illuſtration hereof; Suppoſe you were ſtanding at A, and would know how far it is from you to ſome notable mark, as to D. Here firſt erect ſome Mathematical In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, as the
<hi>Theodilit,</hi> or ſome other at A, the place of your ſtanding; and by help there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, let a mark be ſet up ſide-wayes, (which way the ground will be beſt for the purpoſe) as at B, in a line making right angles with the viſual line from you at A to D; this done, meaſure from A to your mark B, and find it 230 yards. Then place your Inſtrument at B, and obſerve the angle there as ABD, which find 46 degr. 40 min. this angle had, and the other at B being a right angle, the angle at the mark D muſt needs
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:108157:67"/> be 43 deg. 20 min. being the Complement of the angle obſerved at B to 90 degrees: Theſe things had, the work by my Inſtrument is the ſame, as is afore ſhewed. For,</p>
                  <p>Set 43 deg. 20 min. on the firſt, to 46 deg. 40 min. on the ſecond; and then upon the lines of Numbers, againſt the meaſured length
230 on the firſt, is 243,7 &amp; better on the ſecond: So then the diſtance from you to the mark is 243 yards, and ſomething better than ſeven tenths of a yard, which is very neer three quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. If you pleaſe to work this Example by the Tables of Logarithms, you ſhall find the work of the Inſtrument to agree moſt notably with that of the Tables.</p>
                  <p>I might have placed the Problems of right lined Triangles after thoſe of Spherical; for that theſe require to be reſolved by the lines of Sines, Tangents and Numbers together, whereas thoſe of Spherical Triangles are reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved onely by lines of Sines and Tangents alone, and therefore require the more variety: but the doctine of plain Triangles being uſually firſt taught, I have therefore firſt placed it; and the rather, becauſe by theſe Problemes of right lined Triangles, you may ſee the way to work with both the lines of Numbers, Sines, and Tangents altogether, in any caſe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="problem">
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:108157:67"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM. II. In a plain right lined Triangle oblique angled, the three angles and one ſide being known; to find either of the other ſides.</head>
                  <p>IN the Triangle CBD, let the obtuſe angle at C be 112 deg. 0 min. the angle at D be 43 degr. 20 min. and the angle at B 14 degr. 40 min. and let the known ſide be CD 100 pole, and let the ſide CB be the ſide ſought.</p>
                  <p>The Analogie for reſolution of the preſent Problem, is the ſame as in the former, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is;
<list type="analogy">
                        <item> As 14 deg. 40 min. the angle oppoſite to the ſide known,</item>
                        <item> Is to 43 deg. 20 min. the angle oppoſite to the ſide ſought;</item>
                        <item> So is 100, the length of the ſide known,</item>
                        <item> To 271 the length of that ſide ſought.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore, upon the lines of Sines; Set the ſine 14 deg. 40 min. on the firſt, to 43 deg. 20 min. the ſine of the angle oppoſite to the ſide required on the the ſecond; and then upon the lines of Numbers, againſt 100 on the firſt, is 271 on the ſecond: So much is the length of that ſide ſought. For a further illuſtration:</p>
                  <p>Suppoſe you were ſtanding at C, and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to know how far it is from you to B. Here <pb n="126" facs="tcp:108157:68"/> by reaſon of ſome impediment, as a pond, a wall, a hedge, or ſome other thing, you cannot point out your ſecond ſtation at right angles with the viſual line from C to B, but are infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to work by an angle greater than a right angle; wherefore at C obſerve an angle, as BCD of 122 degrees, and meaſure along from C to D
100 pole, and at D obſerve the angle CDB 43 deg. 20 min. Theſe two angles had, add them together, and they make 165 degr. 20 min. which taken from 180 degrees, leaveth 14 deg. 40 min. for the angle at B. (For in all Triangles, if any two of the angles be known, the third is alſo known, for it is evermore the Complement of them both to 180 degrees.) Theſe things thus had, the Analogie for reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of the <hi>quaere</hi> by the lines, is the ſame as before. Therefore,</p>
                  <p>Set the ſine 14 deg. 40 min. on the firſt, (the ſine of the angle oppoſite to the ſide known) to the ſine 43 deg. 20 min. (the ſine of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle oppoſite to the ſide required) on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond; and then on the lines of Numbers, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt 100, the length of the ſide known on the firſt, is 271 on the ſecond: Therefore 271 pole is the length, or diſtance of B, the mark from your ſtation C, which was deſired.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="problem">
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:108157:68"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM. III. If two ſides of a right lined Triangle, and an Angle oppoſite to one of them ſides being known; to find the angle oppoſite to the other ſide.</head>
                  <p>HEre the Analogie ſtandeth thus by the Lines.
<list type="analogy">
                        <item> As that ſide oppoſite to the angle known,</item>
                        <item> Is to the other known ſide;</item>
                        <item> So is the known angle,</item>
                        <item> To that angle ſought.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example.</hi> In the Triangle BCD, let the one ſide known be the ſide CD, 100 yards; and the other ſide known be CB, 271 yards; and let the angle at B be known to be 14 degr. 40 min. and let the angle at D be ſought.</p>
                  <p>Vpon the lines of Numbers; Set 100, the ſide CD oppoſite to the known angle B on the firſt, to 271 the ſide CB oppoſite to that angle at D ſought for on the ſecond; and then on the lines of Sines, againſt the ſine of the known angle 14 deg. 40 min. on the firſt, is 43 deg. 20 min. on the ſecond: So much is the quantity of the angle D, which was ſought.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="problem">
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:108157:69"/>
                  <head>PROBLEM. IV. Two ſides, and the angle included between them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a right angle; to find the other two angles.</head>
                  <p>IF you would find the leſſer of the two un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known angles: Then the Analogie is,
<list type="analogy">
                        <item> As the greater ſide is to the leſſer,</item>
                        <item> So is the Radius to the Tangent of the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer angle.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example.</hi> In the Triangle ABC, let there be known the ſide AB 230 yards, and the ſide AC 143 and three quarters very neer, and the included angle juſt 90 degrees; and let the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle B, being the leſſer angle, be ſought; the which to find,</p>
                  <p>Upon the lines of Numbers, Set 230, the greater ſide known on the firſt, to 143 and thre quarters, the leſſer ſide on the ſecond; and then upon the lines of Tangents, againſt the Radius on the firſt, is the Tangent 32 degr. 0 min. on the ſecond: So much is the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of the leſſer angle, which is the angle at B; and the Complement of that to 90, is 58 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees: So much is the quantity of the angle C, being the greater of the two angles ſought.</p>
                  <p>If you would find the greater angle firſt, of the two unknown angles, then the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie is thus: <pb n="129" facs="tcp:108157:69"/>
                     <list type="analogy">
                        <item> As the leſſer ſide, is to the greater,</item>
                        <item> So is the Radius, to the Tangent of the greater angle.</item>
                     </list> Therefore,</p>
                  <p>Vpon the lines of Numbers, Set the leſſer ſide known AC, 143 and three quarters on the firſt, to the greater ſide AB 230 on the ſecond; and then on the lines of Tangents, againſt the Radius on the firſt, is the Tangent 58 degrees on the ſecond: So much is the quantity of the greater angle at C, and the Co-tangent thereof is 32 degrees: So much is the quantity of the leſſer angle. For it is to be noted, that alwayes the greater angle is oppoſite to the greater ſide, and the leſſer angle oppoſite to the leſſer ſide.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. V. In any oblique angled Triangle, whether obtuſe or acute, having two ſides, and the angle inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded between them; to find the other angles.</head>
                  <p>IN the Triangle BCD, let the angle known be the obtuſe angle at C 122 degrees, and the two ſides including that angle, be CB the greater ſide, containing 271; &amp; CD the leſſer ſide, containing 100, (which ſides may be rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned poles, yards, feet, inches, or what other meaſure you pleaſe) and let the two angles at B and D be ſought.</p>
                  <p>In this caſe the Analogie will be thus: <pb n="130" facs="tcp:108157:70"/>
                     <list type="analogy">
                        <item> As the ſum of the two ſides known,</item>
                        <item> Is to the difference betwixt the ſame ſides;</item>
                        <item>So is the Tangent of the half ſum of the two angles ſought,</item>
                        <item> To the Tangent of the half of their diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here the two ſides including the known an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, are 100 and
271, which added together, their ſum is 371, for the firſt number in the rule of Proportion. Next take the leſſer ſide 100, from 271 the greater ſide, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder is 171, this is the difference between the ſides, and is the ſecond number in the rule: And then take the known angle 122 degrees from 180 degrees, or two right angles, and the Remainder is 58 degrees: So much is the quantity of both the other two angles at B and C, whereof the half is 29 degrees, this half ſum is the third number in the rule of Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Theſe things had, then according to the Rule it is thus:
<list type="analogy">
                        <item>As 371 is to 171,</item>
                        <item>So is the Tangent 29 deg.</item>
                        <item>To the Tangent 14 deg. 20 min.</item>
                     </list> Therefore,</p>
                  <p>Vpon the lines of Numbers, Set 371 the ſum of the two containing ſides on the firſt, to 171 the difference of the ſame ſides on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond; and then upon the lines of Tangents, againſt 29 degrees, the half ſum of the two angles ſought on the firſt, is the Tangent 14
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:108157:70"/> deg. 20 min. on the ſecond. This 14 degr. 20 min. thus found, is the half of the difference of two angles ſought; therefore, To 29 degr. the half ſum of the angles ſought, add this 14 deg. 20 min. and the ſum is 43 degr. 20 min. So much is the quantity of the angle at D, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the two angles ſought; and this 14 deg. 20 min. taken out of that
29 degr. 0 min. the Remainder is 14 deg. 40 min. So much is the angle B, the leſſer of the two angles ſought.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. VI. In any right lined Triangle, whether right angled, or oblique angled, any two ſides b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing known, with the angle included between them; to find the third ſide.</head>
                  <p>IN the oblique angled Triangle CBD, Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe you have the two ſides given CD 100 yards, and CB 271 yards, and the angle C included betwixt them 122 degr. and you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire to know the ſide DB oppoſite to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuſe angle C. Here firſt you muſt by the laſt Problem find out the two angles unknown, and then having the three angles and two ſides known, you may by the angles and one of the ſides find the third ſide, according to the ſecond Problem: As ſuppoſe you would chooſe the ſide CD 100, and thereby work to <pb n="132" facs="tcp:108157:71"/> find the ſide DB. Then the proportion will ſtand thus:
<list type="analogy">
                        <item> As 14 deg. 40 min. the ſine of the angle op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the choſen ſide,</item>
                        <item> Is to 58 deg. the Complement of 122 deg. the angle C oppoſite to the ſide ſought:</item>
                        <item> So is 100, the length of the choſen ſide CD,</item>
                        <item> To 335, the length of that ſide DB, which is required. </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore upon the lines of Sines, Set 14 deg. 40 m. the ſine of the angle oppoſite to the choſen ſide on the firſt, to the ſine 58 deg. the Complement of 122 deg. to 180; and then upon the lines of Numbers, againſt 100, the length of the ſide choſen on the firſt, is
335 on the ſecond: So many yards is the length of the ſide DB, which was required.</p>
                  <p>Again, Suppoſe in the right angled Triangle BAC, right angled at A you have the two ſides AB 230, and the ſide AC 143 and neer three quarters, and the included angle 90 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees. Then to find the other two angles, work as in the laſt Problem thus: Add the two ſides together, 230 and 143 and three quarters, and the ſum is 373 and three quarters, for the firſt number. Then take the leſſer ſide, 143 and three quarters, out of
320 the greater ſide, and the Remainder is 86, and one fourth for the ſecond number, and the angle A is the third <pb n="133" facs="tcp:108157:71"/> number in the rule of Proportion. Therefore,</p>
                  <p>Set 373 and three fourths, the ſum of the ſides on the firſt, to 86 and one fourth, their difference on the ſecond; and then againſt the Tang. 45 deg. the half ſum of the two angles ſought on the firſt, is the Tang. 13 deg. on the ſecond, theſe 13 deg. added to the 45 deg. and the ſum is 58 deg. for the greateſt of the two angles ſought: And taken from 45 deg. lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth 32 deg. for the leſſer of them two angles.</p>
                  <p>The angles thus had, to find the third ſide CB. Set 32 deg. on the firſt, to 90 on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and then againſt 143 and three fourths on the firſt, (the ſide choſen to work by) is 271 on the ſecond: So much is the length of the ſide CB, which is required.</p>
                  <p>Or elſe, making uſe of the ſide AB, Set the ſine 58 deg. to 90; and then on the lines of numbers, againſt 320 on the firſt, is
271 on the ſecond: The length of the ſide ſought, as before.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM VII. In a right lined Triangle, the three ſides only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing known; to find the Perpendicular, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the three angles.</head>
                  <p>LEt the greateſt of the three ſides of your Triangle be taken for the Baſe, for ſo the <pb n="134" facs="tcp:108157:72"/> Perpendicular will fall within the Triangle; then take the ſum of the two ſides by adding them together, and alſo their difference, by ſubſtracting the leſſer from the greater: As in the Triangle CBD, make DB the Baſe, being the longer ſide 335 foot, and the other two ſides be CD 100, and CB 271, theſe two ſides added together make 371, and the leſſer being ſubſtracted from the greater, their diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is 171. Theſe had, the Proportion is thus:
<list type="analogy">
                        <item> As the Baſe DB 335, is to the ſum of the two ſides 371;</item>
                        <item> So is the difference of the two ſides 171, to a fourth ſum.</item>
                     </list> Therefore,</p>
                  <p>Vpon the lines of Numbers onely, Set 335, the length of the Baſe on the firſt, to 371 the ſum of the ſides on the ſecond; and then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt 171, the difference of the ſides on the firſt, is 189,4 on the ſecond; this 189,4 taken out from the Baſe 335,0, and the Remainder is
145,6, the half whereof is 72,8: So many foot meaſured in the line DB, from D to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards B, (becauſe the angle at D is the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of the two angles at the Baſe) will reach to E, the point where the Perpendicular CE will cut the Baſe DB. By which Perpendicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, the Triangle CDB, is divided into two right angled Triangles, DEC and CEB, <pb n="135" facs="tcp:108157:72"/> which being done, all the other angles may be found by the third Problem of this Chapter: For here you have two ſides DC 100, and DE 72,8, and the right angle DEC oppoſite to the ſide DC. Therefore by that third Problem, to find the angle ECD.</p>
                  <p>Set 100, the ſide oppoſite to the angle known on the firſt, to 72,8 the ſide oppoſite to the angle ſought on the ſecond; and then on the lines of ſines againſt 90 degr. the angle known is 46 degr.
40 min. So much is the quantity of the angle ECD, and its Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to 90 is
43 deg. 20 min. for the quantity of the angle CDE. Thus have you the three angles of the right angled Triangle DEC. And for the length of the Perpendicular, it is thus attained unto by the firſt Problem. For,</p>
                  <p>Set 46 deg. 40 min. the quantity of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle C, oppoſite to the known ſide ED on the firſt, to 43 deg. 20 min. the angle D oppoſite to the Perpendicular EC; and then on the lines of Numbers, againſt
72,8 the length of the ſide known on the firſt, is 68,5 and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more: So much is the length of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendicular EC, which was required.</p>
                  <p>In like manner, as the Angles and Perpendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular in this right angled Triangle are found, even ſo are found the Angles in that other right angled Triangle CEB on the other ſide <pb n="136" facs="tcp:108157:73"/> of the Perpendicular; for you ſhall find the angle EBC 14 deg. 40 min. the angle BCE 75 deg. 20 min. And in concluſion, you ſhall find that the two angles at C, made by the Perpendicular, namely ECD and ECB will make juſt 122 degrees, which was the quantity of the obtuſe angle at C, before the Perpendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular was drawn.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM VIII. In a right angled Triangle, the Angles and the Hypothenuſal being given, to find any one of the ſides including the right angle.</head>
                  <p>JN the right angled Triangle BAC, let the angles known be as afore, at C 58 deg. and at B 32 deg. and the angle at A a right angle, and the Hypothenuſal CB be 271 yards: and you would hereby find the ſides AC and AB, which for to do, the rule is thus by the lines on my Scale.
<list type="analogy">
                        <item> As the Radius, is to the angle oppoſite to the ſide ſought;</item>
                        <item> So is the Hypothenuſal or ſide oppoſite to the right angle, to that ſide ſought.</item>
                     </list> Therefore to find the ſide AC.</p>
                  <p>Set the Radius on the firſt, to 32 deg. on the ſecond, which is the angle oppoſite to the ſide ſought; and then, on the lines of Numbers, <pb n="137" facs="tcp:108157:73"/> againſt 271 the ſide known on the firſt, is 143 and three quarters very neer on the ſecond: So many foot is the length of the ſide AC. And for the ſide AB.</p>
                  <p>Set the Radius on the firſt, to 58 deg. on the ſecond, (which is the angle oppoſite to AB, the ſide ſought;) and then on the lines of Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, againſt 271 the Hypothenuſal on the firſt, 230 on the ſecond: So many foot is the length of the ſide AB.</p>
                  <p>Now for your further inſtruction; Let it be ſuppoſed, that AB is the altitude of ſome bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as a Tree, a Turret, a Steeple, or the like, which you would know, and can come no nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to it than at C; therefore at C take the angle of altitude BCA 58 degrees, and then the angle at B the top of the altitude, made by the viſual line CB, and the altitude AB, will be 32 deg. being the Complement of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved angle to 90 deg. for the altitude is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to ſtand perpendicular, and to make a right angle at the baſe A. Then from C, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure backwards in a right line 100 yards to D, and there obſerve the angle of altitude BDA, and find it 43 deg. 20 min. Theſe two angles thus obſerved keep, and take the firſt obſerved angle at C 58 deg. out of 180 deg. and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder is 122 deg. which is the quantity of the obtuſe angle BCD made by the ſtationary <pb n="138" facs="tcp:108157:74"/> line CD, and the viſual line CB. This angle of 122 deg. and the angle obſerved at D
43 deg. 20 min. add together, and they make 165 deg. 20 min. which taken from
180 degr. the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder is 14 degr. 40 min. So much is the angle at B, the top made by the two viſual lines CB and DB. Thus having attained the three angles of a Triangle CBD, and one ſide be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſtationary diſtance, you may find the ſide or Hypothenuſal CB, by the ſecond Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem, and with the Hypothenuſal, the altitude by this Problem.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:108157:74"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI. Of Trigonometria, ſhewing the uſe of the double Scales of Numbers, Sines and Tangents, in the reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Triangles, either plain or ſpherical.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <div n="1" type="problem">
                     <head>PROBLEM. I. The two ſides of a rectangled Triangle being given, to find the Baſe, which is the ſide oppoſite to the right angle.</head>
                     <p>IN the Triangle ABC of the annexed Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gram, Let the ſide AC be 27 deg. 54 min. and the ſide CB 11 deg. 30 min. be given, and the baſe AB required.</p>
                     <p>For reſolution of this <hi>quaere,</hi> ſay thus:
<list type="analogy">
                           <item> As the Radius is to the Co-ſine of one of the given ſides;</item>
                           <item> So is the Co-ſine of the other given ſide to the Co-ſine of the baſe.</item>
                        </list> Therefore,</p>
                     <p>Set the Radius on the firſt, to 62 deg. 6 min. the Co-ſine of the one ſide given, <hi>viz.</hi> of AC, 27 deg. 54 min. on the ſecond; and then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Co-ſine of BC, 11 degr. 30 min. which is 78 deg. 30 min. on the firſt, is 60 deg. <pb n="140" facs="tcp:108157:75"/> the Co-ſine of the ſide or baſe required: So then the baſe AB is 30 degrees.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="problem">
                     <head>PROBLEM II. The two ſides being given, to find either of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique angles.</head>
                     <p>IN the Triangle ABC aforementioned; Let AC be given 27 deg.
54 min. and BC 11 deg. 30 min. and let the angle A, next the ſide AC, be ſought. Say,
<list type="analogy">
                           <item> As the ſine of the ſide next the angle ſought, is to the Radius;</item>
                           <item> So is the Tangent of the ſide oppoſite to the angle ſought, to the Tangent of the ſame angle.</item>
                        </list> Therefore,</p>
                     <p>Set 27 deg. 54 min. the ſide adjacent to the angle ſought, to the Radius on the ſecond; and then againſt the Tangent of 11 deg. 30 min. the ſide oppoſite to the angle ſought on the firſt, is the Tangent 23 deg. 30 min. on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond: So much is the angle at A that was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired.</p>
                     <p>If the angle ſought for do appear to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 45 deg. as doth the angle B, and the ſides leſſe then 45 deg. then the beſt way to find B, is by the next Problem to find the baſe, and then having the baſe to find the angle B.</p>
                     <p>But if the ſide oppoſite to the angle ſought be above
45 degrees, as ſuppoſe the ſides AC <pb n="141" facs="tcp:108157:75"/> were 61 deg. 53 min. and CB 54 deg. 28 min. and the angle A ſought for. Then work thus.</p>
                     <p>Set the Radius on the firſt, to the ſine of the ſide adjacent to the angle ſought, <hi>viz.</hi> to the ſine of AC 61 degr. 53 min. on the ſecond; and then againſt the tangent 54 degr. 28 min. the ſide oppoſite to the angle ſought on that firſt, is 57 degr. 47 min. the Tangent of the angle A ſought for. Here note, that in exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of this kind the angle found is greater than 45 degrees.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="problem">
                     <head>PROBLEM III. One ſide, and the oblique angle next unto it being given; to find the Baſe.</head>
                     <p>LEt the ſide AC 27 degr. 54 min. and the angle A 23 deg.
30 min. be given, and the Baſe AB ſought.</p>
                     <p>
                        <list type="analogy">
                           <item> As the Co-ſine of the angle given, is to the Radius;</item>
                           <item> So is the tangent of the ſide given, to the tangent of the baſe.</item>
                        </list> Therefore,</p>
                     <p>Set 66 deg. 30 min. the Co-ſine of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle given, to the Radius, and then againſt the tangent 27 deg. 54 min. on the firſt, is the tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent 30 deg. on the ſecond, the baſe ſought.</p>
                     <p>If the ſide given be above 45 degrees, as were the ſide AC, 61 deg. 53 min. and the angle A <pb n="142" facs="tcp:108157:76"/> 57 deg. 47 min. then to find the baſe; Set the Radius to 32 degr. 13 min. the Co-ſine of the angle given, and then againſt the tangent of the ſide 61 degr. 53 min. is the tangent 74 degr. 6 min. for the baſe AB.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="problem">
                     <head>PROBLEM IV. The Baſe, and one of the oblique angles being gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; to find the other oblique angle.</head>
                     <p>IN the Triangle aforeſaid; Let there be given the Baſe
30 degrees, and the oblique angle A 23 deg. 30 min. and the angle B required. Say,
<list type="analogy">
                           <item> As the Radius, is to the Co-ſine of the baſe;</item>
                           <item> So is the Tangent of the angle given, to the Co-tangent of the angle required.</item>
                        </list> Therefore,</p>
                     <p>Set the Radius on the firſt, to 60 degr. the Co-ſine of the Baſe; and then againſt 23 deg. 30 min. the tangent of the angle given, is the tangent 20 deg. 38 min. which is the Co-tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent of the angle B. Wherefore the ſaid angle is 69 deg. 22 min.</p>
                     <p>If the angle given be above 45 degrees; As if the angle given be the angle B, and the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer angle A ſought, then, Set the Co-ſine of AB 60 degrees on the ſecond to the Radius; and then againſt the tangent of the given an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle 69 degrees 22 minutes on that firſt, is
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:108157:76"/> 23 degrees 30 minutes, the Tangent of the Angle A.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="problem">
                     <head>PROBLEM. V. The Baſe, and one of the oblique angles given; to find the ſide next the ſame angle.</head>
                     <p>LEt the Baſe AB 30 degr. and the angle A 23 deg. 30 min. be given, and let the ſide AC adjacent to the angle A be required. Say,
<list type="analogy">
                           <item> As the Radius, to the Co-ſine of the angle given;</item>
                           <item> So is the tangent of the baſe, to the tangent of the ſide ſought.</item>
                        </list> Therefore,</p>
                     <p>Set the Radius on the firſt, to 66 degr. 30 min. the Co-ſine of the angle given on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond; and then againſt the tangent of the baſe 30 degrees, is the tangent of the ſide ſought, 27 deg. 54 min.</p>
                     <p>If the baſe be above 45 degrees; as, Let the baſe AB be
74 deg. 6 min. and the angle A 57 deg. 47 min. and then to find the baſe.</p>
                     <p>Set 33 degr. 13 min. the Co-ſine of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle given on the firſt, to the Radius on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond; and then againſt the tangent of the baſe 74 deg. 6 min. on the firſt, is 61 degr. 53 min. the ſide AC ſought for.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="problem">
                     <pb n="144" facs="tcp:108157:77"/>
                     <head>PROBLEM. VI. The Baſe, and one of the oblique angles given; to find the ſide oppoſite to the angle given.</head>
                     <p>LEt the Baſe AB 30 degrees, and the angle A 23 degrees 30 minutes be given, and let the ſide CB oppoſite to the ſame angle A be ſought.</p>
                     <p>
                        <list type="analogy">
                           <item> As the Radius, to the Sine of the Baſe;</item>
                           <item> So is the Sine of the angle given, to the Sine of the ſide ſought.</item>
                        </list> Therefore,</p>
                     <p>Set the Radius on the firſt, to 30 degrees, the Sine of the Baſe on the ſecond; and then againſt 23 deg. 30 min. on the firſt is 11 degr. 30 min. on the ſecond, the ſide CB, which was ſought for.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="problem">
                     <head>PROBLEM VII. One ſide, and the oblique angle next it being gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; to find the other ſide.</head>
                     <p>LEt the ſide AC, 27 degr. 54 min. and the angle A 23 deg.
30 min. be given, and the ſide BC required. Say,
<list type="analogy">
                           <item> As the Radius, to the Sine of the ſide known;</item>
                           <item> So is the tangent of the angle known, to the tangent of the ſide required.</item>
                        </list> Therefore,</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="145" facs="tcp:108157:77"/>Set the Radius on the firſt, to 27 degr. 54 min. the ſine of the ſide known; and then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the tangent of the angle A, 23 degrees 30 min. on the firſt, is the Tangent 11 degr. 30 minutes for the ſide CB, which was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="problem">
                     <head>PROBLEM VIII. One ſide, and the oblique angle next it being known; to find the other oblique angle.</head>
                     <p>LEt the ſide AC, 27 degr. 54 min. and the angle A 23 deg.
30 min. be given, and the angle B ſought. Say,
<list type="analogy">
                           <item> As the Radius, to the Co-ſine of the ſide given;</item>
                           <item> So is the Sine of the angle given, to the Co-ſine of the angle ſought.</item>
                        </list> Therefore,</p>
                     <p>Set the Radius on the firſt, to 62 deg. 6 min. the Co-ſine of 27 degr. 54 min. the ſide given; and then againſt the Sine of the angle given, 23 deg. 30 min. is the Sine 20 deg. 38 min. the Complement of
69 degr. 22 min. the angle B, which was required.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="problem">
                     <pb n="146" facs="tcp:108157:78"/>
                     <head>PROBLEM. IX. One ſide, and the angle oppoſite to it being known; to find the Baſe.</head>
                     <p>LEt the ſide BC 11 deg. 30 min. and the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle A 23 deg.
30 min. be given, and let the baſe AB be ſought for. Say,
<list type="analogy">
                           <item> As the ſine of the angle given, to the ſine of the ſide given;</item>
                           <item> So is the Radius, to the ſine of the baſe.</item>
                        </list> Therefore,</p>
                     <p>Set 23 deg. 30 min. the ſine of the angle gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven on the firſt, to 11 deg. 30 min. the ſine of the ſide given; and then againſt the Radius on the firſt, is the ſine 30 deg. on the ſecond. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 30 deg. is the baſe ſought for.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="problem">
                     <head>PROBLEM. X. One ſide, and the angle oppoſite to it being given; to find the other ſide.</head>
                     <p>LEt the ſide BC 11 deg. 30 min. and the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle A 23 deg.
30 min. be given, and the ſide AC ſought for. Say,
<list type="analogy">
                           <item> As the tangent of the angle given, is to the tangent of the ſide given;</item>
                           <item> So is the Radius, to the ſine of the other ſide.</item>
                        </list> Therefore,</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="147" facs="tcp:108157:78"/>Set the tangent of the angle A, 23 degr. 30 min. on the firſt, to the tangent of 11 degr. 30 min. on the ſecond; and then againſt the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius on the firſt, is 27 deg. 54 min. The ſine of the ſide AC, ſought for.</p>
                     <p>Sometime it ſo falleth out in this Problem, and ſome others, by reaſon of a great angle or ſide, that the reſolution cannot be readily done by the Analogie ſet down; yet you ſhall ſee ready wayes upon the lines to perform the ſame, or by other Problems to gain the thing ſought.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="problem">
                     <head>PROBLEM XI. One ſide, and the angle oppoſite to it being known; to find the other angle.</head>
                     <p>LEt the ſide CB 11 degr. 30 min. and the angle A 23 deg.
30 min. be given, and the angle B ſought. Say,
<list type="analogy">
                           <item> As the Co-ſine of the ſide given, to the Co-ſine of the angle given;</item>
                           <item> So is the Radius, to the ſine of the angle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired.</item>
                        </list> Therefore,</p>
                     <p>Set 78 deg. 30 min. the Co-ſine of the ſide CB given on the firſt, to 66 deg. 30 min. the Co-ſine of A the angle given; and then againſt the Radius on the firſt, is 69 degr. 22 min. on the ſecond. The ſine of the angle ſought.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="problem">
                     <pb n="148" facs="tcp:108157:79"/>
                     <head>PROBLEM. XII. The Baſe, and one ſide known; to find the oblique angle adjoyning to the ſame ſide.</head>
                     <p>LEt the ſide AC, 27 degr. 54 min. and the Baſe AB 30 degrees, be given, and the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle A adjoyning to the ſide given, ſought for. Say,
<list type="analogy">
                           <item> As the tangent of the Baſe, to the tangent of the ſide given;</item>
                           <item> So is the Radius, to the Co-ſine of the angle required.</item>
                        </list> Therefore,</p>
                     <p>Set the tangent of the Baſe 30 degr. on the firſt, to 27 degr. 54 min. the tangent of AC, the ſide given on the ſecond; and then againſt the Radius on the firſt, is 66 degr. 30 min. on the ſecond, whoſe Co-ſine is 23 degr. 30 min. The ſine of the angle A that was ſought.</p>
                     <p>When the Baſe and ſide be above 45 degr. as, Suppoſe the Baſe AB to be 74 deg. 6 min. and the ſide AC 61 deg. 53 min. then ſet the tangent of that ſide next the angle ſought, <hi>viz.</hi> 61 deg. 53 min. on the firſt, to the tangent of the Baſe 74 degr. 6 min. on the ſecond; and then againſt the Radius on the firſt, is 32 degr. 13 min. the Co-ſine of the angle A. After this manner, by altering the placing of the terms given, one way or other, any <hi>quaere</hi> may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="problem">
                     <pb n="149" facs="tcp:108157:79"/>
                     <head>PROBLEM XIII. The Baſe, and one ſide being given; to find the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle oppoſite to the ſame ſide.</head>
                     <p>LEt the ſide AC, 27 degr. 54 min. and the Baſe AB 30 deg. be given, and the angle B required. Say,
<list type="analogy">
                           <item> As the Sine of the Baſe, to the Radius;</item>
                           <item> So is the Sine of the ſide given, to the Sine of the angle required.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Set 30 deg. the ſine of the Baſe on the firſt, to the Radius on the ſecond; and then againſt 27 deg. 54 min. the ſine of AC the ſide given on the firſt, is 69 deg. 22 min. The ſine of the angle B, which was required.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="problem">
                     <head>PROBLEM. XIV. The Baſe, and one ſide being given; to find the other ſide.</head>
                     <p>LEt the ſide AC 27 degr. 54 min. and the Baſe AB 30 degrees be given, and the ſide BC ſought for. Say.
<list type="analogy">
                           <item> As the Co-ſine of the ſide given, to the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius;</item>
                           <item> So is the Co-ſine of the Baſe, to the Co-ſine of the ſide ſought.</item>
                        </list> Therefore,</p>
                     <p>Set 62 degr. 6 min. the Co-ſine of the ſide given, to the Radius; and then againſt 60 degr. <pb n="150" facs="tcp:108157:80"/> the Co-ſine of the Baſe, is 78 deg. 30 min. the Co-ſine of the ſide BC, 11 degr. 30 min. that was required.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="problem">
                     <head>PROBLEM. XV. The two oblique angles being given, to find the Baſe.</head>
                     <p>LEt the angle A be 23 degr. 30 min. and the angle B 69 degr.
22 min. be given, and let the Baſe AB be ſought.</p>
                     <p>
                        <list type="analogy">
                           <item> As the tangent of one of the angles, is to the Co-tangent of the other angle;</item>
                           <item> So is the Radius, to the Co-ſine of the Baſe.</item>
                        </list> Therefore,</p>
                     <p>Set the tangent of the one angle, (as of that at A 23 degr.
30 min. on the firſt, to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangent of the other angle, <hi>viz.</hi> to
20 degr. 38 min. on the ſecond; and then againſt the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius on the firſt, is the ſine 60 degrees on the ſecond. Which is the Co-ſine of 30 degrees, the Baſe AB, which was required.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="problem">
                     <head>PROBLEM. XVI. The two oblique angles being given; to find either of the ſides.</head>
                     <p>LEt the angle A be 23 degr. 30 min. and the angle B 69 deg.
22 min. and let the ſide AC be ſought. Say, <pb n="151" facs="tcp:108157:80"/>
                        <list type="analogy">
                           <item> As the ſine of one of the angles, is to the Co-ſine of the other angle;</item>
                           <item> So is the Radius, to the Co-ſine of the ſide oppoſite to that angle, whoſe Co-ſine was taken.</item>
                        </list> Therefore,</p>
                     <p>Set the ſine of the angle A 23 degr. 30 min. on the firſt, to 20 deg. 38 min. the Co-ſine of the other angle B 69 degr. 22 min. And then againſt the Radius, is 62 degr. 6 min. which is the Co-ſine of 27 deg. 54 min. the ſine of the ſide AC ſought. Having ſhewed the uſe of the double lines, through all the varieties of right angled Spherical Triangles, I come to the Oblique.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>In Oblique angled ſpherical Triangles.</head>
                  <div n="17" type="problem">
                     <head>PROBLEM XVII. Two angles, and a ſide oppoſite to one of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing given; to find the ſide oppoſite to the other.</head>
                     <p>LEt the Triangle propoſed be ABE, wherein let be given the angle E 38 deg. 15 min. and the ſide BA 30 degrees, and the angle A 23 degrees 30 minutes, and let the ſide BE be ſought. Say,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:108157:81"/>
                        <list type="analogy">
                           <item> As the Sine of the angle oppoſite to the ſide known, is to the Sine of the ſame ſide;</item>
                           <item> So is the Sine of the angle oppoſite to the ſide ſought, to the Sine of that ſame ſide.</item>
                        </list> Therefore,</p>
                     <p>Set 38 deg. 15 min. the ſine of the angle E, to the Sine of the ſide given 30 deg. (<hi>viz.</hi> AB) And then againſt 23 degr. 30 min. the Sine of the other angle A on the firſt, is 18 degr. 47 min. The Sine of BE, the ſide ſought.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="18" type="problem">
                     <head>PROBLEM XVIII. Two ſides, and an angle oppoſite to one of them being known; to find the angle oppoſite to the other of them.</head>
                     <p>IN the Triangle ABE, let the ſide AB be 30 degr. the angle E 38 degr. 15 min. and the ſide BE 18 degr. 47 min. and let the angle A, which is the angle oppoſite to the ſide BE, be ſought. Say,
<list type="analogy">
                           <item> As the Sine of the ſide oppoſite to the angle given, is to the Sine of the ſame angle;</item>
                           <item> So is the Sine of the ſide oppoſite to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle ſought, to the Sine of that ſame angle.</item>
                        </list> Therefore,</p>
                     <p>Set 30 degrees, the ſide AB on the firſt, to 38 deg. 15 min. the Sine of its oppoſite angle on the ſecond; and then againſt 18 deg: 47 min. <pb n="153" facs="tcp:108157:81"/> the Sine of BE the other ſide, is 23 degr.
30 min. the Sine of A its oppoſite angle, which is the thing that was to be ſought.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="19" type="problem">
                     <head>PROBLEM. XIX. Two ſides, and the angle includ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d between them, being known; to find the other ſide oppoſite to that angle.</head>
                     <p>JN the Triangle ABE, let the ſides AB 30 deg. and AE 42 deg. 51 min. with the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle A included between them, be given, and the ſide BE required.</p>
                     <p>Here firſt a Perpendicular muſt be ſuppoſed to be let fall from the unknown angle B, to the ſide AE oppoſite to that angle, and now to find on what part of the ſide AE it will fall. Say,
<list type="analogy">
                           <item> As the Radius, to the Co-ſine of the inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded angle A;</item>
                           <item> So is the Tangent of AB, to the Tangent of AC.</item>
                        </list> Therefore,</p>
                     <p>Set the Radius on the firſt, to 66 deg. 30 min. the Co-ſine of the included angle A; and then againſt the Tangent of AB 30 degrees the leſſer ſide, is 27 degrees 54 minutes, the Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent of the diſtance from A to C, on the ſide AE; therefore C is the point whereon the Perpendicular will fall: This diſtance AC. 27 deg. 47 min. deduct out of the whole ſide AE <pb n="154" facs="tcp:108157:82"/> 42 deg. 51 min. And the Remainder is 14 deg. 57 min. Then ſay,
<list type="analogy">
                           <item> As the Co-ſine of AC, the diſtanee found,</item>
                           <item>Is to the Co-ſine of CE, the Remainder;</item>
                           <item> So is the Co-ſine of AB, the leſſer ſide,</item>
                           <item>to the Co-ſine of BE, the ſide required.</item>
                        </list> Therefore,</p>
                     <p>Set 62 deg. 6 min. the Co-ſine of AC, the diſtance found, to 75 degr. 3 min. the Co-ſine of CE, the Remainder; and then againſt 60 degrees, the Co-ſine of the ſide AB. is 71 deg. 13 min. the Co-ſine of BE, 18 degr. 47 min. the ſide required.</p>
                     <p>It is to be obſerved, that in oblique angled Triangles, when the terms propounded are two ſides and one angle, or two angles and one ſide, and yet not reſolveable by the two laſt Problems before this: That then a Perpendicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar is to be let fall, (or ſuppoſed to be let fall) from one of the unknown angles, to the ſide oppoſite thereto; and ſo of the oblique angled Triangle given, to make two right angled Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angles. Which being done, all the parts of ſuch a Spherical Triangle, may be found out by the former Problems of right angled Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angles. This Perpendicular will ſometime fall within the Triangle, and that is, when the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles at the ends of the ſide whereon the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendicular fals, are both of one kind, that is to
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:108157:82"/> ſay, both acute, or both obtuſe, as in the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angle ABE. And ſometime this Perpendicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar fals without the Triangle, and that is, when the angles at the ends of the ſide wheron it fals, are of differing kinds; that is, one acute, and the other obtuſe, as in the Triangle ADB, where the Perpendicular BC fals on the ſide AD, it being prolonged, as it muſt alwayes be in thoſe caſes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="20" type="problem">
                     <head>PROBLEM XX. Two ſides, with the angle included between them, being given; to find either of the other angles.</head>
                     <p>LEt the ſides AB 30 degr. and AE 42 degr. 51 min. with the angle A 23 degr. 30 min. be given, and the angle E ſought.</p>
                     <p>As in the laſt Problem, ſo here a Perpendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular muſt be let fall on the given ſide AE, from its oppoſite angle B, and ſo of the oblique angled Triangle, make two rectangled Trian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles. This Perpendicular, as afore was ſhewed, is thus found: Set the Radius to 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> degr. 30 min. the Co-ſine of the included angle; and then againſt the Tangent of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>0 deg. the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, is the Tangent 27 degr. 54 min. So much is the part of the ſide AE, betwixt A and the point C, where the Perpendicular fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth. Now if 27 degr. 54 min. be taken from <pb n="156" facs="tcp:108157:83"/> 42 deg. 51 min. the Remain is 14 deg. 57 min. for the ſide of the rectangled Triangle BCE. Now to find the angle E, the Analogie is thus.
<list type="analogy">
                           <item> As the ſine of the ſide CE, is to the ſine of the ſide AC;</item>
                           <item> So is the Tangent of the angle included, to the Tangent of the angle ſought.</item>
                        </list> And therefore,</p>
                     <p>Set the ſine of CE, 14 deg. 57 min. on the firſt, to the ſine of AC, 27 degr. 54 min. the part found; and then againſt the Tangent of A, 23 deg. 30 min. is the Tangent 38 degr. 15 min. the Angle E that was ſought.</p>
                     <p>Otherwiſe, having let fall the Perpendicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and having found CE, 14 deg. 57 min. to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Baſe 18 degr. 47 min. then to find E, work as by the 12 Problem of rectan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled Spherical Triangles, in this manner.</p>
                     <p>Set the Tangent of the Baſe, 18 degr. 47 min. to the Tangent of that part of the ſide CE, 14 degr. 57 min. And then againſt the Radius on the firſt, is 38 degr. 15 min. the ſine of the angle E, as before. In this manner may any of the other terms be alſo found out, by one or other of thoſe Problems.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="21" type="problem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:108157:83"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:108157:84"/>
                     <pb n="157" facs="tcp:108157:84"/>
                     <head>PROBLEM. XXI. Two ſides, and one angle next to the ſide ſought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing given; to find the ſame ſide.</head>
                     <p>LEt the ſides AB 30 degr. and BE 18 degr. 57 min. and the angle A 23 deg. 30 min. be given, and the ſide AE required. Here firſt let fall the Perpendicular BC, and ſay,
<list type="analogy">
                           <item> As 60 deg. the Co-ſine of AB, is to 71 deg. 13 min. the Co-ſine of BE, 18 degr. 47 min.</item>
                           <item> So is the Co-ſine of AC 27 degr. 54 min.
<hi>viz.</hi> 62 deg. 6 min. to 75 degr. 3 min. the Co-ſine of CE.</item>
                        </list> Therefore,</p>
                     <p>Set 60 deg. the Co-ſine of AB, to 71 degr. 13 min. the Co-ſine of BE; and then againſt 62 deg. 6 min. the Co-ſine of AC, is 14 degr. 3 min. the Co-ſine of CE. Wherefore CE is 14 degr. 57 min. which added to AC 27 degr. 54 min. makes 42 degr. 51 min. for the ſide AE, which was ſought.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="22" type="problem">
                     <pb n="158" facs="tcp:108157:85"/>
                     <head>PROBLEM XXII. Two ſides, and an angle adjacent to one of them being given; to find the angle included be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the ſame ſides.</head>
                     <p>LEt the ſides given be AB, 30 degrees, and BE 18 degr. 47 min. with the angle A 23 deg. 30 min. and let the obtuſe angle B in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded betwixt the two ſides, BA, and BE, be required<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> To reſolve this demand, Say,
<list type="analogy">
                           <item> 1 As the Radius, to the Co-ſine of AB;</item>
                           <item> So is the Tangent of the angle A, to the Tangent of aBc.</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="analogy">
                           <item> 2 As the Tangent of BE, to the Tangent of AB;</item>
                           <item> So is the Co-ſine of aBc, to the Co-ſine of cBe.</item>
                        </list> Therefore,</p>
                     <p n="1">1 Set the Radius, to 66 degrees, the Co-ſine of AB, and then againſt the Tangent of A 23 degr. 30 min. is the Tangent 69 degr. 22 min. the angle aBc, made by letting fall the Perpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicular, and is part of the angle aBc ſought. Now to find the Remainder.</p>
                     <p n="1">1 Set 18 degr. 47 min. the Tangent of BE on the firſt, to the Tangent of AB 30 degrees; and then againſt the Co-ſine of aBc, which is 20 deg. 38 min. is 36 deg. 46 min. whoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement 53 degr.
14 min. is the angle cBe, <pb n="159" facs="tcp:108157:85"/> which added to 69 degr. 22 min. makes 122 deg. 36 min. the angle aBe, which is the thing required.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="23" type="problem">
                     <head>PROBLEM XXIII. Two angles, with the ſide lying betwixt them being known; to find either of the other ſides.</head>
                     <p>LEt be given the angles A 23 degr. 30 min. and B 122 degr.
36 min. and the ſide AB 30 degrees, and let the ſide BE be required. In which caſe having let fall the Perpendicular BC, and found the angle cBe. Say,
<list type="analogy">
                           <item> As the Co-ſine of cBe, is to the Co-ſine of aBc;</item>
                           <item> So is the Tangent of AB, To the Tangent of BE.</item>
                        </list> Therefore,</p>
                     <p>Set 36 degr. 46 min. the Co-ſine of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle cBe on the firſt, to the Co-ſine of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle aBc; and then againſt 30 degrees, the tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent of the ſide given, is the tangent 18 deg. 47 min. the ſide BE, which was required.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="24" type="problem">
                     <head>PROBLEM. XXIV. Two angles, with the ſide lying betwixt them being given, to find the third angle.</head>
                     <p>LEt the angle A 23 deg. 30 min. and the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle B 122 degr.
36 min. with the ſide AB <pb n="160" facs="tcp:108157:86"/> 30 degrees be given, and the third angle at E, required.</p>
                     <p>Having let fall the Perpendicular, and found the angles aBc, and cBe. Then ſay,
<list type="analogy">
                           <item> As the Sine of aBc, is to the Sine of cBe;</item>
                           <item> So is the Co-ſine of A, the angle given, to the Co-ſine of E, the angle ſought.</item>
                        </list> Therefore,</p>
                     <p>Set 69 deg. 22 min. the Sine of aBc on the firſt, to 53 degr. 14 min. the Sine of cBe on the ſecond; and then againſt the Co-ſine of A 66 deg. 30 min. on the firſt, is 51 degr. 45 min. the Co-ſine of the angle E. Wherefore E is 38 deg. 15 min.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="25" type="problem">
                     <head>PROBLEM. XXV. Two angles, and a ſide oppoſite to one of them being given; to find the ſide adjacent to both the angles.</head>
                     <p>LEt the angles A 23 degr. 30 min and E 38 15 min. with the ſide BA 30 degrees, being oppoſite to the angle E be given, and the ſide AE required.</p>
                     <p>Having let fall the Perpendicular, and toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with it found AC, a part of AE. Say then,
<list type="analogy">
                           <item> As the tangent of E, is to the tangent of A.</item>
                           <item> So is the ſine of AC, to the ſine of CE.</item>
                        </list> 
                        <pb n="161" facs="tcp:108157:86"/>Therefore,</p>
                     <p>Set 38 deg 15 min. the tangent of E on the firſt, to 23 degr. 30 min. the tangent of A on the ſecond; and then againſt 27 degr. 54 min. the ſine of the ſide of AC on the firſt, is 14 deg. 57 min. on the ſecond, which is the ſine of CE. This 14 degr. 57 min. added to 27 degr. 54 min. the other part AC afore found, makes 42 deg. 51 min. for the whole ſide AE, which was ſought.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="26" type="problem">
                     <head>PROBLEM. XXVI. Two angles, and a ſide oppoſite to one of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing known; to find the third angle.</head>
                     <p>LEt the angles given be A 23 deg. 30 min. and E 38 deg. 15 min. and let the ſide AB, being oppoſite to the angle E, be 30 degr. and let the third angle aBe be required.</p>
                     <p>As in the former Problems, ſo alſo in this; Let fall the Perpendicular BC, and by it gain the angle aBc, which being had, to gain the Remainder of the angle aBe. Say,
<list type="analogy">
                           <item> As the Co-ſine of the angle A, is to the Co-ſine of the angle E;</item>
                           <item> So is the ſine of aBc, to the ſine of cBe.</item>
                        </list> Therefore,</p>
                     <p>Set 66 deg. 30 min. the Co-ſine of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle A on the firſt, to 51 degr. 45 min. the Co-ſine <pb n="162" facs="tcp:108157:87"/> of the angle E on the ſecond; and then againſt 69 degr. 22 min. the ſine of aBc on the firſt, is 53 degr. 14 min. the ſine of cBe. Theſe two angles added together, make 122 degr. 36 min. the angle ABE, which was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="27" type="problem">
                     <head>PROBLEM. XXVII. The three ſides being given, to find any one of the angles.</head>
                     <p>LEt the three ſides be AB 30 degr. AE 42 deg. 51 min. and BE 18 degr. 47 min. and let the angle B be ſought.</p>
                     <p>To reſolve this Problem: Firſt, Add all the three ſides together into one ſum, of which ſum take the half, and then from that half take the ſide oppoſite to the angle ſought, and reſerve the difference. As for Example.
<table>
                           <row>
                              <cell rows="3">The three ſides given, are</cell>
                              <cell>AB</cell>
                              <cell>30 d. 00 m.</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>AE</cell>
                              <cell>42 d. 51 m.</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>BE</cell>
                              <cell>18 d. 47 m.</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>The ſum of the three ſides</cell>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell role="total">91 d. 38 m.</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>The half of that ſum</cell>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>45 d. 49 m.</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>The ſide AE, oppoſite to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired angle B, ſubſtracted</cell>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>42 d. 51 m.</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>And the Differ. to be reſerved is</cell>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell role="total">2 d. 58 m.</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="163" facs="tcp:108157:87"/>This done, to proceed to find the angle ſought. Say,
<list type="analogy">
                           <item>1 As the Radius, is to the Sine of one of the ſides including the angle ſought;</item>
                           <item>So is the Sine of the other ſide, including the ſame angle, to a fourth Sine.</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="analogy">
                           <item>2 As that fourth Sine, is to the Sine of the half ſum;</item>
                           <item>So is the Sine of the reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved difference, to a ſeventh Sine.</item>
                        </list> Therefore,</p>
                     <p n="1">1 Set the Radius on the firſt, to 30 deg. the Sine of one of the ſides given, including the angle ſought; and then againſt
18 deg. 47 min. the Sine of the other including ſide, is 9 degr. 16 min. for a fourth Sine.</p>
                     <p n="2">2 Set this fourth Sine 9 deg. 16 min. on the firſt, to 45 degr. 49 min. the Sine of the half ſum on the ſecond; and then againſt 2 degr. 58 min. the Sine of the reſerved difference, is 13 deg. 20 min. for the ſeventh Sine.</p>
                     <p>This being done (by the help of a pair of Compaſſes, or otherwiſe) divide the diſtance betwixt this point of 13 degr. 20 min. and the Radius into two equal parts, and the middle point is at 28 deg. 42 min. whoſe Complement 61 deg. 18 min. doubled, makes 122 degr. 36 min. the angle a B e, which was ſought.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="28" type="problem">
                     <pb n="164" facs="tcp:108157:88"/>
                     <head>PROBLEM. XXVIII. The three angles being onely known, to find any of the ſides.</head>
                     <p>TO reſolve this Problem, the angles are to be turned into ſides, and the ſides into an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles, (otherwiſe it is unreſolveable) and it is thus done: In ſtead of the greateſt angle, take its Complement to 180 degrees, and then the angles convert themſelves into ſides, and the ſides into angles, and then the reſolution is juſt the ſame as in the laſt Problem.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="diagrams">
                  <pb facs="tcp:108157:88"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>diagram of an oblique-angled triangle</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>diagram of a right-angled triangle</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:108157:89"/>
               <pb n="165" facs="tcp:108157:89"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII. The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the Inſtrument in Navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation.</head>
               <p>THis Inſtrument, with theſe Double Scales inſcribed thereon, is of moſt excellent uſe in Navigation, as I ſhall ſhew in part, and leave the reſt to the Ingenious to find out of themſelves. And firſt, by the Meridian Line, and Line of equal parts joyned together upon the Inſtrument; you may do all things that may be done by the Table of Meridional Degrees, ſet forth by Mr. <hi>Wright,</hi> Mr. <hi>Gunter,</hi> Mr.
<hi>Wingate,</hi> and others treating of Navigation.</p>
               <div n="1" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM I. Two places being propounded, the one under the Equinoctial, and the other without; to find their Meridional Difference.</head>
                  <p>LOok the Latitude of that place ſituate with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Equinoctial, upon the Meridian line, and right againſt it, on the Line of equal parts, is the Meridional Difference of thoſe two places.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="166" facs="tcp:108157:90"/>
                     <hi>Example.</hi> Let the entrance of the River of the Amazons, under the Equinoctial, be one place propounded, and the Lizard in the Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of 50 degrees be the other place, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween which the Meridional Difference is deſired.</p>
                  <p>Look 50 degrees, the Latitude of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard on the Meridian Line, and right againſt it on the Line of equal parts, is 57 degrees 90 centeſimal minutes, which is 57 degrees, and 9 tenth parts of a degree, or 57 degrees, 54 ſexaginary minutes. So much is the Meridio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Difference of thoſe two places.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. II. Two places having both Northerly, or both South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erly Latitude; to find their Meridional Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference.</head>
                  <p>SUbſtract the degrees and minutes which you find on the Line of equal parts againſt the leſſer Latitude, from the degrees and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes found on the ſame Line of equal parts againſt the greater Latitude, and the Remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is the Meridional Difference of thoſe two places.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example.</hi> Lett St. <hi>Chriſtophers</hi> and the
<hi>Lizard</hi> be two places, between which you would find the Meridional Difference; the Latitude of <pb n="167" facs="tcp:108157:90"/> St. <hi>Chriſtophers</hi> is known to be 15 degrees 30 minutes North, to which anſwereth on the Line of equal parts 15 degr. 69 centeſimal mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes: the Latitude of the
<hi>Lizard</hi> is alſo known to be 50 degrees North. To which on the Line of equal parts anſwereth 57 degr. 90 cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſms. Now take 15 degr. 69 cent. the leſſer number of degrees found on the Line of equal parts, out of 57 deg.
90 cent. the greater num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of degrees found on the Line of equal parts, and the Remainder is 42 degr. 21 cent. or 42 deg. 12 min. of the ſexaginary diviſion. So much is the Meridional Difference deſired.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. III. Two places being ſituate, the one Southerly, and the other Northerly; to find the Meridional Difference.</head>
                  <p>TAke the degrees and parts found on the Line of equal parts, againſt the two Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes propoſed, ſought in the Meridian Line, and add them both together, and the ſum of that addition is the Meridional Difference.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example.</hi> Let the two places propoſed be the
<hi>Cape of Good Hope,</hi> in the Latitude of 36 deg. 30 min. South, and
<hi>Japan</hi> in the <hi>East Indies,</hi> whoſe Latitude is 30 degrees North. Now on the Meridian Line, look 36 degr. 30 min. and <pb n="168" facs="tcp:108157:91"/> againſt it on the Line of equal parts, is 39 deg. 15 min. and againſt the 30 degrees is 31 degr. 28 min. Theſe two ſums 39,15, and
31,28, being added together, make 70 deg. 43 min. So much is the Meridional Difference required.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM IV. The Latitude of two places, and their Difference of Longitude being known; to find the Rumb leading from the one to the other.</head>
                  <p>LEt the two places propoſed be the <hi>Lizard</hi> and St.
<hi>Chriſtophers;</hi> the Latitude of the <hi>Lizard</hi> 50 degrees, and of St. <hi>Chriſtophers</hi> 15 degr. 30 min. and their Difference of Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
68 deg. 30 min. And let the Rumb paſſing from the <hi>Lizard</hi> to St.
<hi>Chriſtophers</hi> be required.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, by the ſecond Problem, ſeek the Meridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Difference between the two places, which you find to be 42 deg. 12 min. by that ſecond Problem. Then,</p>
                  <p>Vpon the Line of Numbers, Set 68 degr. 30 min. the Difference of Longitude on the firſt, to 42 degr. 12 min. the Meridional Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence on the ſecond; and then upon the Lines of Tangents againſt the Radius on the firſt, is the Tangent 58 deg. 21 min on the ſecond. So much lieth the Rumb from the Meridian, which is on the fifth Rumb from the Meridian
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:108157:91"/> Weſtwards, and two degrees 6 minutes, over and above that fifth Rumb.</p>
                  <p>And if you be to ſail from the <hi>Lizard</hi> to the
<hi>Bermudas Ilands,</hi> in the Latitude of 32 degr. 25 min. whoſe Difference of Longitude is known to be Weſtwards 70 degrees; and you would know on what point of the Compaſſe you muſt ſteer your courſe thither.</p>
                  <p>Here firſt by the ſecond Problem, ſeek the Meridional Difference, and find it 23 degr. 36 min. And then,</p>
                  <p>Set 70, the Difference of Longitude on the firſt, to 23 deg.
36 min. the Meridional Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence on the ſecond; and then againſt the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius on the firſt, is the Tangent 71 deg. 21 min. on the ſecond; that is, on the point 71 deg. 21 min. from the Meridian, or South point, which is on the ſixth Rumb, and 3 deg. 51 min. over. And becauſe the <hi>Bermudas</hi> lye Weſtwards from the Meridian of the <hi>Lizard;</hi> therefore the Rumb is the Weſt Southweſt point, and 3 deg. 51 min. over.</p>
                  <p>Here is to be noted, that every Rumb from the Meridian containeth 11 deg. 15 min. And therefore the firſt Rumb makes an angle with the Meridian of 11 degr. 15 min. the ſecond Rumb an angle of 22 degr. 30 min. and ſo of the reſt, as in the little Table following ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, wherein you ſee that the ſixth Rumb <pb n="170" facs="tcp:108157:92"/> makes an angle of 67 degr. 30 min. which ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from 71 deg. 21 min. in this laſt Example found, there remained 3 degr. 21 min. over the ſixth Rumb.</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell rows="8">Rumbs</cell>
                           <cell>1</cell>
                           <cell>11 deg. 15 min.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>2</cell>
                           <cell>22 deg. 30 min.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>3</cell>
                           <cell>33 deg. 45 min.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>4</cell>
                           <cell>45 deg. 00 min.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>5</cell>
                           <cell>56 deg. 15 min.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>6</cell>
                           <cell>67 deg. 30 min.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>7</cell>
                           <cell>78 deg. 45 min.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>8</cell>
                           <cell>90 deg. 00 min.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. V. The Latitudes of two places being given with the Rumb; to find the diſtance upon the Rumb.</head>
                  <p>LEt the place from whence you ſail be in the Latitude of 50 degrees, and the Latitude of a place to which you are come, be 52 degr. 30 min. So that the Difference of Latitude is 2 deg. 30 min. find alſo you and that you have ſailed on the firſt Rumb, from the Meridian Northerly, that is, have made an angle with the Meridian of 56 degr. 15 min. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement of the fifth Rumb to eight is 3, which is 33 deg. 45 min. and you would know your diſtance ſailed upon that Rumb.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="171" facs="tcp:108157:92"/>Set 33 degr. 45 min. the Co-ſine of the Rumb on the firſt, to the Radius on the ſecond; and then on the Line of Numbers, againſt 2,50 the Difference of Latitude on the firſt, is 4,50 on the ſecond, that is to ſay, 4 degrees 50 cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſmes, or 4 deg. 30 min. So much is the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſailed upon that courſe, in degrees and minutes.</p>
                  <p>Again, Let the <hi>Lizard,</hi> lying in 50 degrees of North Latitude, be th place from whence you are to go; and let the other place that you are to go unto be St. <hi>Christophers,</hi> in the Latitude of 15 degr. 30 min. North. And the Rumb leading from one to the other, bearing from the Meridian of the <hi>Lizard</hi> 58 degr. 21 min. which is ſomething more than the fifth Rumb. Now by theſe things known, you would know the diſtance upon the Rumb between thoſe two places.</p>
                  <p>Here you muſt firſt of all ſubſtract 15 degr. 30 min. the leſſer Latitude out of 50 degrees, the greater Latitude, and the Remainder 34 deg. 30 min. is the true Difference of Latitude; and then, Set 31 degr. 39 min. the Co-ſine of the Rumb on the firſt, to the Radius on the ſecond; and then on the Line of Numbers, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt 34,30 repreſenting 34 degr. 30 min. the Difference of Latitude on that firſt, is 65,46 on the ſecond, that is 65 deg 46 min. So much <pb n="172" facs="tcp:108157:93"/> in degrees and minutes, is the diſtance upon the Rumb between the <hi>Lizard</hi> and St.
<hi>Chriſtophers.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM VI. The Latitudes of two places, and their diſtance being known; to find the Rumb leading from one to the other.</head>
                  <p>LEt the two places propounded be thoſe mentioned in the laſt Problem, whoſe La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes were 50 degrees, and 52 degr. 30 min. and their diſtance known 4 deg. 30 min. &amp; the Rumb you know not, but deſire to know it.</p>
                  <p>Vpon the Line of Numbers, Set 4,30 repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting 4 deg. 30 minutes, the diſtance known, on the firſt, to 2,30 repreſenting 2 degrees
30 minutes, the Difference of Latitude on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond; and then upon the Lines of Sines, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Radius on the firſt, is the Sine 33 deg. 45 min. on the ſecond, whoſe Co-ſine is 56 deg. 15 min. So much is the diſtance that the courſe lieth from the Meridian, which is upon the fifth Rumb.</p>
                  <p>Or let the <hi>Lizard,</hi> in the Latitude of 50 deg. and St.
<hi>Christophers</hi> in the Latitude 15 degr. 30 min. be the two places propoſed, whoſe Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Latitude is 34 degrees 46 min. and their diſtance known 65 deg. 46 min. and the Rumb that the courſe lieth upon, is deſired.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="173" facs="tcp:108157:93"/>Vpon the Line of Numbers, 65,46 the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance known on the firſt, to 34,46 the Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Latitude on the ſecond; and then on the Lines of Sines, againſt the Radius on the firſt, is 58 degr. 21 min. on the ſecond. So much is the diſtance of the Rumb from the Meridian of the <hi>Lizard,</hi> on which the Courſe lieth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM VII. The Latitude of the place from whence you go, the Rumb you go upon, and the diſtance gone, being given; to find the Difference of Latitude, and thereby the Latitude of the place you are in.</head>
                  <p>LEt the place you go from, be in the Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of 50 degrees, the Rumb you have gone upon, the fifth from the Meridian, and the diſtance gone, 4 degr. 30 min. And by theſe you deſire to know the Difference of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, with the Latitude of the place you are in.</p>
                  <p>Set the Radius on the firſt, to 33 degr. 45 min. the Co-ſine of the Rumb on the ſecond; and then upon the Lines of Numbers, againſt 4,30 repreſenting 4 degr. 30 min. the diſtance gone on the firſt, is 2,30 on the ſecond, that is 2 deg. 30 min. So much is the Difference of Latitude. This 2 degr. 30 min. added to the Latitude of the place you came from, (becauſe <pb n="174" facs="tcp:108157:94"/> the Courſe was Northerly) makes 52 deg. 30 min. for the Latitude of the place you are in.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example.</hi> Suppoſe you were at St.
<hi>Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers,</hi> in the Latitude of 15 degr. 30 min. and from thence had ſailed Northwards neer upon the fifth Rumb from the Meridian; or on the true point of 58 deg. 21 min. from the Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian, and at length came to a place, where you found that you had ſailed 65 deg. 46 min. from St.
<hi>Christophers,</hi> and now do deſire to know in what Latitude you are.</p>
                  <p>Set the Radius on the firſt, to 31 degr. 39 min. the Co-ſine of the Rumb on the ſecond; and then upon the Line of Numbers, againſt 65,46 repreſenting 65 deg. 46 min. the diſtance gone on the firſt, is 34,30 on the ſecond, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying 34 deg. 30 min. So much doth the Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude you are in, differ from that you came from, and becauſe the Courſe was Northerly, the Latitude is increaſed. Therefore this Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference found, 34 degr. 30 min. is to be added to the known Latitude, 15 degr. 30 min. and they both make 50 degrees juſt: Therefore the Latitude of the place you are in, is 50 degrees of North Latitude.</p>
                  <p>If the place you went from had been the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard,</hi> in
50 degrees of Latitude, and you ſail from thence more Southwards upon the point 58 degr. 21 min. from the Meridian Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, <pb n="175" facs="tcp:108157:94"/> and on this Courſe have ſailed 65 degr. 46 min. and ſo found, that you have altered your Latitude 34 degr. 30 min. and are come to a place of unknown Latitude. In this caſe, becauſe the Courſe is Southerly (the Latitude of the place you are in, is leſſe than that you came from) you muſt take the Difference of Latitude found 34 deg. 30 min. from 50 degr. the Latitude known, the Remainder is 15 deg. 30. The Latitude of the place you are in.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM VIII. The Latitude of the place you are in, and the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of the place you went from, with the Rumb being given; to find the Difference of Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</head>
                  <p>LEt the two places be, one the <hi>Lizard,</hi> in the Latitude of 50 degrees, from whence you go, and the other place St.
<hi>Chriſtophers,</hi> in the Latitude of 15 degr. 30 min. and the Rumb 58 degr. 21 min. from the Meridian, and the thing deſired is the Difference of Longitude.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, by the ſecond Problem, find out the Meridional Difference, 42 deg. 12 min. which had; Set the Tangent of the Rumb, 58 degr. 21 min. on the firſt, to the Radius on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond; and then upon the Line of Numbers, againſt 42 deg. 12 min. on the firſt, is 68 deg.
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:108157:95"/> 30 min. on the ſecond. Wherefore 68 degr. 30 min. is the Difference of Longitude be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt your two places, the <hi>Lizard</hi> and St. <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtophers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And if the place you came from, be in the Latitude of 50 degrees, and of that you are in, be 52 degr. 30 min. and the Rumb you have come upon, be the fifth from the Meridian, and you deſire the Difference of Longitude. Then,</p>
                  <p>Set 56 deg. 15 min. the Tangent of the fifth Rumb on the firſt, to the Radius on the ſecond, and then upon the Line of Numbers, againſt 2 deg. 30 min. the Meridional Difference of Latitudes on the firſt, is 3 deg. 45 min. on the ſecond. So much is the Difference of Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude deſired, according to the projection of the common Sea-Chart.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. IX. In any Parallel of Latitude, to find how many leagues anſwer to one degree of Longitude in that Parallel.</head>
                  <p>THis Problem is grounded upon this Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie.
<list type="analogy">
                        <item>As the Radius, is to the Co-ſine of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude;</item>
                        <item>So is the number of leagues, in one E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctial degree, to the number of leagues anſwering to one degree in that Latitude.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="177" facs="tcp:108157:95"/>
                     <hi>Example.</hi> In the Latitude of 18 deg. 12 min. I demand how many leagues ſailing along in that Parallel, will alter the Longitude one degree?</p>
                  <p>For Anſwer, to my deſire, I ſet the Radius on the firſt, to 71 deg. 48 min. the Co-ſine of the Latitude on the ſecond; and then on the Line of Numbers, againſt 20 on the firſt, the number of leagues in one Equinoctial degree, I ſee 19 on the ſecond: And therefore every 19 leagues ſailing along in that Parallel, alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Longitude one degree: And on the contrary, for every degree that you alter your Longitude, you ſail
19 leagues in that Parallel.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 In the Latitude of 51 degrees 32 minutes, it is demanded, How many leagues in that Parallel, do anſwer to one degree of Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude?</p>
                  <p>Set the Radius on the firſt, to 38 degr. 28 min. the Co-ſine of the Latitude on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond; and then on the Line of Numbers, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt 20 on the firſt, is 12 and 4 tenths on the ſecond. So many leagues ſailing in that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel of 51 degr. 30 min. altereth the Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude one degree.</p>
                  <p>If you would know how many miles alter one degree of Longitude in any Parallel. Then,</p>
                  <p>Set the Radius on the firſt, to 38 degr.
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:108157:96"/> 28 min. the Co-ſine of the latitude on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond; and then on the lines of Numbers, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt 60 on the firſt, is 37 and about one third, which is 37 miles, and one third of a mile, to make one degree of longitude in that Parallel of latitude. And contrariwiſe, if you find you have altered your longitude one degree, you are then removed 37 miles, and about one third of a mile.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM X. To find how many miles anſwer to many degrees of Longitude in any Parallel.</head>
                  <p>SVppoſe you ſhould ſail along in the Paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel of 50 degrees, until you have altered your longitude 35 degrees, and then would know how many miles you have ſailed.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, reduce 35 Equinoctial degrees into minutes, by multiplying them by 60, and they make 2100 minutes. Then,</p>
                  <p>Set the Radius on the firſt, to 40 degr. the Co-ſine of the latitude on the ſecond; and then againſt 2100, the Difference of longitude in minutes, upon the firſt on the line of Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, is 1350 on the ſecond. So many miles anſwer to 35 degrees, in that Parallel.</p>
                  <p>But if you would know how many leagues you have ſailed, in altering your longitude 35 <pb n="179" facs="tcp:108157:96"/> degrees, then reduce the 35 degr. into leagues, by multiplying them by 20, and they make 700. Now, Set the Radius to 40 degrees, as afore, and then right againſt 700, in the line of Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers on the firſt, is 450 on the ſecond. So ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny leagues you have ſailed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM XI. Upon any Rumb propoſed, to find how many leagues do anſwer to one degree of latitude in the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian, or of any great circle.</head>
                  <p>THis Problem is reſolved by this Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie.
<list type="analogy">
                        <item> As the Co-ſine of the Rumb from the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian,</item>
                        <item>Is to the Radius;</item>
                        <item> So is 20 leagues, the meaſure of one degree in any great circle,</item>
                        <item>To the leagues that anſwer to one degree upon that Rumb.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example.</hi> Suppoſe you ſail upon the fourth Rumb from the Meridian, which is the point of Northeaſt, or Northweſt; or elſe the point Southeaſt, or Southweſt, and deſire to know upon that Rumb, how many leagues do anſwer to one degree of the Meridian, or alter the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude one degree.</p>
                  <p>Set 45 degrees, the Co-ſine of the Rumb on the firſt, to the Radius on the ſecond; and then on the line of Numbers, againſt 20, the
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:108157:97"/> number of leagues in a degree of a great circle on the firſt, is 28 and almoſt an half. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 28 leagues and an half, make one degree, or alter the Latitude one degree, in ſailing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that Rumb.</p>
                  <p>If you deſire to know how many miles ſail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on any Rumb, alter the Latitude one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, as here in this Example of the fourth Rumb; then ſet 45 degrees, the Co-ſine of the Rumb on the firſt, to the Radius on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecond; and then on the lines of Numbers, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt 60 on the firſt, is 85 and ſomething above on the third. So many miles, on that fourth Rumb, altereth one degree of Latitude.</p>
                  <p>I am now in the middeſt of the Sea, where if I ſhould ſail through all particulars that my Inſtrument is capeable of, I ſhould with my travel fill a great Volume, I will therefore leave off wading any further in this Subject, and leave the reſt to the ingenuous Practition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in Navigation, to whom I wiſh proſperity in all their honeſt and laudable undertakings.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="181" facs="tcp:108157:97"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII. The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the double Scales of Sines and Tangents on the Inſtrument, in Dialling.</head>
               <div n="1" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. I. To find the diſtance of the hours from the Line of twelve a clock, in Horizontal Dials, made for an oblique Sphere.</head>
                  <p>LEt an Horizontal Dial be propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, to be drawn for the elevation of the Pole 51 deg. 30 min. For making whereof the Analogie ſtandeth thus:
<list type="analogy">
                        <item> As the Radius,</item>
                        <item>Is to the Sine of the Eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</item>
                        <item> So is the Tangent of the hours in a right Sphere from
12,</item>
                        <item>To the Tangent of the ſame hours from the line of 12, in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Sphere propounded.</item>
                     </list> Therefore,</p>
                  <p>Set the Radius on the firſt, to the Sine of the Elevation given, <hi>viz.</hi> to 51 deg. 30 min. on the ſecond; and then the Inſtrument unremoved, againſt 15 deg. the Tangent of an Equinoctial hour on the firſt, is 11 degr. 51 min. the Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent of one hours diſtance from the line of 12 <pb n="182" facs="tcp:108157:98"/> a clock in the oblique Sphere of 51 degr. 30 min. and againſt 30 degrees on the firſt, being the diſtance of two Equinoctial hours, is 24 deg. 19 min. on the ſecond, for the diſtance of two hours from the line of 12, in that given latitude. And likewiſe, againſt the Tangent of 45 degrees on the firſt, the diſtance of three Equinoctial hours, in a right Sphere on that firſt, is the Tangent of 38 degr. 3 min. on the ſecond, for the diſtance of the hours of 3 and 9 a clock, from the hour-line of 12, in that gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven latitude.</p>
                  <p>But now for the fourth and fifth hours, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Tangents of thoſe hours be above 45 degrees, you muſt work backwards in this manner: The Inſtrument not ſtirred, look 60 degrees, the equall diſtance of the fourth hour, in a right Sphere on the ſecond; and then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that Tangent of 60 degrees on that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, is the Tangent 53 degr. 35 min. on the firſt, for the hours of four and eight; and alſo againſt the Tangent of 75 degrees, the fifth equal hour on that ſecond, is the Tangent 71 degr. 6 min. on the firſt, for the hours of 5 in the fore-noon, and 7 after noon: As for the hours of 6 and 6, they are at juſt 90 degr. from the hour-line of 12 a clock, and ſo for any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther latitude: for the hours of 5 and 4 in the morning, they are equally diſtant from the
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:108157:98"/> hour of 6, as is 7 and 8; and ſo in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, the hours of 7 and 8 are equally diſtant from 6, as is 5 and 4. By the ſame rule ſhall you find half hours and quarters, as when you would have the true diſtance of one hour &amp; an half from the noon-line, then work by the Tangent of 22 degr. 30 min. and in ſo doing, you ſhall have 17 degr. 38 min. to be the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of one hour and an half from the noon-line, in the latitude of 51 degr. 30 min. and ſo for any other.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM II. A Dial being made, and the Elevation for which it was made not being known; to find for what Latitude it is made.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt of all, get the diſtance between the hours of 12 and
1, which had, Set the Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent of 15 deg. on the firſt, to the Tangent of that diſtance on the ſecond; and then againſt the Radius on the firſt, is the Sine of the Eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſought for on the ſecond.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example.</hi> There is an old Dial, which doth appear to be a good one, and I deſire to know for what Latitude it was made, as alſo whether it be true made, or not; which to do, I firſt ſeek the diſtance betwixt 12 and 1, and find it 11 degr. 51 min. Therefore I ſet the Tangent
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:108157:99"/> of 15 degrees on the firſt, to the Tangent of that diſtance, 11 deg. 51 min. on the ſecond; and then againſt the Radius on the firſt, is the Sine 51 degr. 30 min. on the ſecond. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I conclude, that the Dial was made for the Elevation of 51 degr. 30 min. Thus may you examine any Dial, whether it be truely made, or not.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM III. To find the diſtances of the hour-lines, from the line of 12 a clock in a direct South Dial, for any Elevation propounded.</head>
                  <p>IN the Latitude of 51 degr. 30 min. a Dial is to be made, wherein to find the diſtance of the hour-lines from the line of 12 a clock.</p>
                  <p>Say as in the firſt Problem,
<list type="analogy">
                        <item> As the Radius,</item>
                        <item>To the Co-ſine of the Poles Elevation;</item>
                        <item> So is the Tangent of any hour given,</item>
                        <item>To the Tangent of the hour-line from the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian.</item>
                     </list> Therefore,</p>
                  <p>Set the Radius on the firſt, to 38 degr. 30 min. the Co-ſine of the Latitude on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond; and then againſt the Tangent of
15 deg. on the firſt, is the Tangent of 9 degr. 28 min. on the ſecond, for the hours of 1 and 11; and againſt 30 degr. on the firſt, is the Tangent
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:108157:99"/> 19 deg. 46 min. on the ſecond, the diſtance of the hours of 2 and 10, from the line of 12. And againſt the Tangent 45 on the firſt, is the Tangent 31 deg. 54 min. on the ſecond, for the diſtance of the hour-lines of 9 and 3, from the line of 12. And now backwards, againſt the Tangent of 60 deg. on the ſecond, is 47 degr. 10 min. on the firſt, the Tangent of the diſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the hour-lines of 4 and 8, from the line of 12. And laſtly, againſt 75 degr. on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, is 66 deg. 43 min. on the firſt, the Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent of the diſtance of the hour-lines of 7 and 5, from the line of 12. For the hours of 6 and 6, they make right angles with the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. IV. In a vertical Dial inclining, having the Eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Pole above the Plane; to find the diſtance of the hour-lines from the hour-line of 12 a clock.</head>
                  <p>LEt ſuch a Plane be propounded, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe North part is elevated above the Horizon 16 deg. 30 min. which taken from the Eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the place 51 degr. 30 min. leaveth 35 degrees, for the Elevation of the Pole above the Dials Plane: Wherefore to find the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the hour-lines in ſuch a Dial from the Meridian, or hour-line of 12. Say, <pb n="186" facs="tcp:108157:100"/>
                     <list type="analogy">
                        <item> As the Radius,</item>
                        <item>Is to the Sine of the Eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion above the Plane;</item>
                        <item> So is the Tangent of any Equinoctial hour,</item>
                        <item>To the diſtance of the ſame hour-line from the Meridian.</item>
                     </list> Therefore,</p>
                  <p>Set the Radius on the firſt, to 35 degrees, the Sine of the Poles Elevation above the Dials Plane; and then againſt the Tangent of 15 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, which is the Tangent of one Equinoctial hour on the firſt, is 8 degr. 45 min. on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, the Tangent of the diſtance of the hours of 1 and 11, from the hour-line of 12: and againſt 30 degr. on the firſt, is 18 degr. 19 min. on the ſecond, for the hours of 2 and 10. And for the reſt of the hours, you ſhall have them, as you had thoſe in the former Dials.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. V. In any erect declining Dial, to find the diſtance of the Styll from the Subſtyll, and of the Subſtyll from the Meridian.</head>
                  <p>IN the Latitude of 52 degr. I would make a Dial to a wall, declining from the true South point 45 deg. wherein firſt to find the diſtance of the Styll from the Subſtyll, the work is thus:
<list type="analogy">
                        <item> As the the Radius,</item>
                        <item>To 45 degr. the Co-ſine of the declination of the Dials Plane from the true South point.</item>
                        <pb n="187" facs="tcp:108157:100"/>
                        <item> So is 38 degr. the Co-ſine of the Latitude,</item>
                        <item>To 25 degr. 48 min. the diſtance of the Styll from the Subſtyll.</item>
                     </list> Therefore,</p>
                  <p>Set the Radius on the firſt, to 45 degr. the Co-ſine of the Declination on the ſecond; and then againſt 38 degr. the Co-ſine of the Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude on the firſt, is 25 degr. 48 min. on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond. So much is the diſtance of the Styll from the Subſtyll, or height of the Styll.</p>
                  <p>Or ſet the Radius to 38 deg. and then againſt 45 deg. is
25 deg. 48 min.</p>
                  <p>And then for the diſtance of the Subſtyll from the Meridian, this is the Rule.</p>
                  <p>Take 64 degr. 12 min. the Co-ſine of that 25 degr. 48 min. the diſtance found, and 52 degr. the Latitude of the place, and count the greater of them two Sines for the firſt term in the rule of Proportion, and the leſſer of them for the ſecond term, and the Radius for the third term. And then,</p>
                  <p>Set the Sine 64 degr. 12 min. on the firſt, (which is the Co-ſine of that ſine afore found) to the Radius on the ſecond; and then againſt 52 degrees, the Latitude of the place on the firſt, is 61 degr. 5 min. on the ſecond, whoſe Complement is 28 deg. 55 min. So much is the diſtance of the Subſtill from the Meridian, in ſuch a declining Dial. And ſo of any other.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="188" facs="tcp:108157:101"/>But I ſee by my Dial, that the Sun is decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from the Meridian far into the Weſt, caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his ſhadow at half an hour paſt ſix a clock after noon, and Saturday night,
<hi>August</hi> the firſt 1657, time to leave work. And for as much as my occaſions call me another way for the next week, and for many weeks after, I muſt leave off proceeding any further in this Subject of Dialling.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notice">
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>THe Reader might here expect to have found the figure of the Inſtrument, but it would have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him little or no ſatisfaction; beſides, the Deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption thereof is ſo well known to Mr. <hi>Anthony Thompſon,</hi> living in <hi>Hoſier-Lane</hi> neer <hi>Weſt Smithfield,</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> who most accurately ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth this, and all other Mathematical Inſtruments, either in Braſſe or Wood, that I found it wholly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary and uſeleſſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>S. P.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:108157:101"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
